<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/tags/mining/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/tags/mining/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Mechanical Transmission of Power (2): Jerker Line Systems</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-system_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="101713" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Field motor on steel frame with steel jerker rods on the James Field. Image: &amp;amp;ldquo;Conservation district study appendix&amp;amp;rdquo;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Field motor on steel frame with steel jerker rods on the James Field. Image: &#34;[Conservation district study appendix](http://www.lambtononline.ca/home/residents/planninganddevelopment/Oil%20Heritage%20Conservation%20District%20Plan%20Documents/Forms/AllItems.aspx)&#34;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the 1860s to 1940s, many oil wells were pumped by a technology that originates in a sixteenth-century power transmission system used in the mining industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One engine operated up to 45 pumps in different locations, each up to a mile away. Power was transmitted by means of wooden rods or steel cables that moved back and forth, snaking through the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system was so efficient that an engine used for pumping an oil well could operate a whole cluster of pump jacks. The technology, which still operates in a handful of small oil fields, could also work with renewable energy sources, and shows great potential for efficient small-scale energy use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerker line systems can be used to operate water pumps or sawing machines, to forge iron, to process food or fibres, or to make paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the 1500s onwards, engineers developed mechanical power transmission and distribution systems that became ever more sophisticated: &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/&#34;&gt;Stangenkunsten&lt;/a&gt;. Networks of pivoted, wooden field-rods conveyed power from waterwheels in the valleys to mining machinery in the mountains over distances of up to 4 km, operating pumps and bellows, hoisting ores, and transporting miners up and down shafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steam engines, which started replacing water wheels from the 1860s onwards, were not dependent on the proximity of a stream or river, and could thus be located close to the mine shaft. This eliminated the need for mechanical power transmission. However, the Stangenkunst did not disappear. On the contrary, the technology became even more popular after, rather than before, the invention of the steam engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, it found a new application in oil production, initially in the United States but later all over the world. It was in the oil industry that the Stangenkunst reached the pinnacle of its development, and became known as the &amp;ldquo;jerker line system&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-canadian-jerker-line-system&#34;&gt;The Canadian Jerker Line System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right from the start of modern oil production in the late 1850s, the Stangenkunst played an important role. It was first used for pumping oil in Oil Springs, Ontario, Canada. While the oil here was of very good quality, production was marginal. The high cost of operating a steam engine at each was not economically viable. In 1863, only four years after the industry came into production, a solution was found by John Henry Fairbank, who set up a system for the transfer of power from a steam engine to multiple oil pumps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/stangenkunst-ontario_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Stangenkunst in Oil Springs, Ontario, Canada. Image: Markus Wandel.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Stangenkunst in Oil Springs, Ontario, Canada. Image: [Markus Wandel](http://wandel.ca/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method, which became known as the &amp;ldquo;Canadian Jerker Line System&amp;rdquo;, was remarkably similar to the Stangenkunsten. Fairbank used wooden rods, which swung back and forth from wooden hangers that were suspended from wooden poles, and connected to wooden pump jacks. He didn&amp;rsquo;t even bother to apply the more efficient pantograph system developed in the 1590s, but used the original single-rod system. This made sense: it was cheaper to build, and friction was less of a problem since the system aimed at distributing power rather than transferring it long-distance (most oil pumps were within one mile of the central power source).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;subdividing-and-distributing-power&#34;&gt;Subdividing and Distributing Power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some differences between the Fairbank method and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/&#34;&gt;pre-industrial Stangenkunsten&lt;/a&gt;. Two cranks converted the circular motion of the steam engine&amp;rsquo;s wheel to a reciprocating motion that moved two parallel wooden rods back and forth, just as in the older systems powered by water wheels. In Fairbank&amp;rsquo;s model, however, a mechanism was introduced to slow down the revolution speed of the steam engine. It consisted of a leather belt placed between the wheel of the steam engine and the cranks. Another addition was the bull wheel, a cast-iron wheel making back-and-forth quarter turns. It was housed in a timber frame just outside the engine shed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/bull-wheel-oil-springs_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A bull wheel in Oil Springs, Ontario. Source: &amp;amp;quot;Conservation district study appendix&amp;amp;quot;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A bull wheel in Oil Springs, Ontario. Source: \&#34;[Conservation district study appendix](http://www.lambtononline.ca/home/residents/planninganddevelopment/Oil%20Heritage%20Conservation%20District%20Plan%20Documents/Forms/AllItems.aspx)&#34;,
Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bull wheel allowed the reciprocating motion of the two cranks to be subdivided over a greater number of rod lines. In the picture above, for instance, power is distributed from the steam engine to the bull wheel via the two wooden rods on the lower left side. It is transferred to a double field line which runs diagonally from upper left to lower right (the main line) while a single rod line extends to the centre and back of the picture. Thus, in this case, five rod lines branch off from the central power instead of one or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/field-wheel-oil-springs_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A field wheel in Oil Springs, Ontario. Source: &amp;amp;quot;Conservation district study appendix&amp;amp;quot;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A field wheel in Oil Springs, Ontario. Source: \&#34;[Conservation district study appendix](http://www.lambtononline.ca/home/residents/planninganddevelopment/Oil%20Heritage%20Conservation%20District%20Plan%20Documents/Forms/AllItems.aspx)&#34;,
Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional subdivision of power to other field rods (branch lines) could happen further along the main line, by means of a &amp;ldquo;field wheel&amp;rdquo; — a
similar cast-iron, oscillating wheel in a timber frame. The field wheel was also used for diverting a main rod line 90 degrees, as can be seen in the picture above. Field wheels replaced the &amp;ldquo;Kunst Kreuzen&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Engine Crosses&amp;rdquo; used in pre-industrial Stangenkunsten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;V-shaped wooden assemblies, lying on their sides, were used to make less sharp turns. The point of the V was anchored, and acted as the pivot for the mechanism. When the jerker line pulled on one leg of the V, the lines comes from the other direction were pulled out, too. A similar V-rod placed upright was used to change direction in the vertical plane when the line crossed a hill or valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pennsylvania-jerker-line-system&#34;&gt;The Pennsylvania Jerker Line System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian jerker line system spread to other oilfields but was eventually superseded by a more sophisticated system in which steel cables and iron bars replaced wooden rods. The metal rods were usually called &amp;ldquo;shackle lines&amp;rdquo;. This method was developed in 1879 by Pennsylvania oilman Edward Yates and became known as the &amp;ldquo;Pennsylvania Jerker Line System&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/pennsylvania-jerker-line-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: Old Iron.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: [Old Iron](http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The famous Pennsylvania oilfields (home to Rockerfeller&amp;rsquo;s Standard Oil Company) came into production around the same time as the Ontario oil fields. However, unlike in Canada, steam engines were used to power each well for the first two decades. Oil wells in the Allegheny Plateau had a high initial production, which was followed by a rapid drop off. The incentive for pumping these low production wells after their initial outflow was small, as new fields were continually being discovered and drillers would simply sink a new well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1870s, following a decline in oil prices and production per well, economising the oil production process became key to profitability. This drive for efficiency resulted in the adoption of the jerker line system, which made using previously-abandoned wells economically viable again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/pennsylvania-jerker-line-system-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: Old Iron.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: [Old Iron](http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1885, the jerker line system was used widely in Pennsylvania (then the largest oil producer in North America). Thereafter, it spread to other US oil fields. By the early twentieth century, the system was used in oil fields around the world. By then, the technology had improved and numerous oil-well supply companies had developed standardised systems that could be purchased in part or whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/pennsylvania-jerker-line-system-3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A schematic of a Pennsylvania jerker line system, showing both geared power and bandwheel power system. Drawing by Eric S. Elmer. Source: Library of Congress.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A schematic of a Pennsylvania jerker line system, showing both geared power and bandwheel power system. Drawing by Eric S. Elmer. Source: [Library of Congress](http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/pa3551.sheet.00003a/resource/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Canadian jerker line system was reminiscent of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/&#34;&gt;Stangenkunsten operating in pre-industrial times&lt;/a&gt;, the Pennsylvania jerker line system looked radically different. The prime mover (mostly a gas engine supplied from a nearby well) operated a &amp;ldquo;central power&amp;rdquo; (either geared or bandwheel) which slowed down the engine speed, converted the engine&amp;rsquo;s rotary motion to reciprocating motion, and distributed power to all the rod lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-engine-powers-45-pumps&#34;&gt;One Engine Powers 45 pumps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A back-and-forth motion was imparted to the rod lines by an &amp;ldquo;eccentric&amp;rdquo;, placed either above or below the geared or bandwheel power, to which 8
to 15 rod lines were hooked that fanned out in all directions. The eccentric was mounted slightly off-center from the power&amp;rsquo;s central vertical shaft, with the rod lines attached to the outer slip ring. As the eccentric rotated within the slip ring, the slip ring oscillated, pulling the rod lines. For each rotation of the slip ring, the rod lines completed one full stroke (see the illustration below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/eccentric-motion-jerker-line_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Eccentric motion jerker&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Eccentric motion jerker 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, the mechanism produced 12 to 20 oscillations per minute, pulling the attached shackle lines an equal number of times. Depending on the number of wells, up to three eccentrics could be mounted on the central shaft, so that a total of 45 oil wells in different locations could be pumped. (More commonly, however, 10 to 25 pumps were powered as they wanted to limit the amount of temporarily unproductive wells in case of an engine breakdown.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;implications-for-field-layout&#34;&gt;Implications for Field Layout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These different approaches to subdividing and distributing power led to distinct field layouts. In the Pennsylvania system, all oil pumps in the cluster were directly connected to the central power via jerker lines, which radiated out of the engine shed in all directions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/lockwood-power-jerker-line_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;An axonometric view of the Lockwood Poer (built in 1909), near Warren, pennsylvania, showing the spatial relationship of machinery to structure inside a typical octagonal power. Drawing by Eric S. Elmer. Source: Library of Congress.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 An axonometric view of the Lockwood Poer (built in 1909), near Warren, pennsylvania, showing the spatial relationship of machinery to structure inside a typical octagonal power. Drawing by Eric S. Elmer. Source:
[Library of Congress](http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/pa3551.sheet.00003a/resource/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Canadian jerker line system, none of the pump jacks were directly connected to the central power. Motion was transferred to the bull wheel and then further subdivided along the main lines using field wheels. As a result, the Pennsylvania jerker line system generally produced web-like patterns, while the Canadian jerker line system usually created linear patterns with dendritic lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be seen clearly in the James Field in Ontario, which still has both systems still operating. The spider-like systems use metal rods, while the linear systems use wooden rods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/james-field-jerker-line-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Inventory map of the James field with its well numbers, central powers and additional features. The spider-like systems use metal rods, while the linear systems use wooden rods. Source: &amp;amp;ldquo;Conservation district study appendix&amp;amp;rdquo;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Inventory map of the James field with its well numbers, central powers and additional features. The spider-like systems use metal rods, while the linear systems use wooden rods. Source: &#34;[Conservation district study appendix](http://www.lambtononline.ca/home/residents/planninganddevelopment/Oil%20Heritage%20Conservation%20District%20Plan%20Documents/Forms/AllItems.aspx)&#34;,
Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-balanced-system&#34;&gt;A Balanced system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web-like layout of the Pennsylvania system offered an important advantage. Because a Stangenkunst was always a combination of horizontal and vertical power transmission, gravity delivered part of the power. A water wheel or steam engine had to deliver all the power needed to make the horizontal stroke that pulled the vertical mechanism upwards, but gravity aided the return stroke. In the case of oil pumping, the weight of the grasshopper pump made the return stroke, saving energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-system-interior_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: Old Iron.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: [Old Iron](http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This effect was doubled when each well was matched with one in the opposite direction. When the sucker rods in one well raised (the upstroke), those in the opposite well lowered under their own weight (the downstroke), helping raise the rods in the well undergoing the upstroke. In other words, the pumps were powering each other with their own weight. This minimized the load on the engine: the only power required was for overcoming inertia and friction, plus the weight of the oil lifted at each stroke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-power-transmission_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Image: Old Iron.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Image: [Old Iron](http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web-like layout of the Pennsylvania system made balancing loads much easier. At all times, half the dead load of rods and mechanisms in the field was being lifted while the other half descended. The steel rods attached to the eccentric could be hooked to, or unhooked from, shackle lines that were connected to the oil pumps. If one well was disconnected, the well in the opposite direction was removed to maintain balance. If this was not possible, the eccentric rod of the disconnected well was hooked to a counterbalance. Since all pumps were directly connected to the central power, one worker could balance the load of all the wells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/balancing-a-jerker-line-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Balancing a jerker line system&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Balancing a jerker line system 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made it possible for a cluster of about 15 to 30 oil wells to be pumped with almost the same engine capacity required to pump one well. In &lt;em&gt;Surface Machinery and Methods for Oil-Well Pumping&lt;/em&gt; (1925), H.C. George writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the early days of the oil industry, all nonflowing wells were pumped individually &amp;ldquo;on the beam&amp;rdquo; by steam engines. This system wasted both labor and power, as each well required a man and a steam power plant. At present a group of 15 to 30 similar wells is pumped with a central &amp;ldquo;power&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;jack&amp;rdquo; plant with practically the same labor and the same energy capacity as was then used at each well.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Many oil wells if pumped individually would show a loss, but operated as members of a group they show a profit. The older fields of Pennsylvania, Ohio, West Virginia, and Illinois exemplify efficiency in group operation. In Pennsylvania the 59,000 operating oil wells show an average of less than a quarter of a barrel production per well per day, yet are being operated at a profit by the group method.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wells of like characteristics, such as pumping time, length of stroke, and size of tubing should be balanced for best results. Some oil companies pump wells of like characteristics at the same time, then take those wells off the power and put on other wells of like characteristics. This practice is common in some of the eastern oil fields, where many wells do not pump more than a few hours per week, and where powers handle 15 to 30 wells, each pumped only several hours at a time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;shacklework&#34;&gt;Shacklework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of steel cables instead of wooden rods also made it easier to navigate difficult terrain. The Pennsylvania jerker line system made use of a variety of devices to support the lines and change their direction &amp;ndash; these were generally called &amp;ldquo;shacklework&amp;rdquo;. The steel cables were hung from tripods or supported by &amp;ldquo;friction posts&amp;rdquo;, which were fixed in the ground, or &amp;ldquo;rocking posts&amp;rdquo;, which were mounted on a pivoting base to allow a rocking motion. &amp;ldquo;Hold-ups&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;hold-downs&amp;rdquo; guided the lines up or down, while &amp;ldquo;butterflies&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;ring swings&amp;rdquo; allowed them to change direction in order to carry the lines around obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: Old Iron.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: [Old Iron](http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &amp;ldquo;butterfly&amp;rdquo; was a triangular wooden or metal frame, which allowed up to 90 degree turns and was reminiscent of the V-rods used in the Canadian and pre-industrial system. A &amp;ldquo;ring swing&amp;rdquo; was used for lesser changes in direction and was even simpler. It consisted of three rings:
one large ring, attached to a another suitable mounting spot, and two smaller rings attached to the large ring and the shackle line. Pendulums and rockers were sometimes used to make the length of the stroke at the well differ from that imparted to the jerker line at the central power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, the shacklework was made from recycled parts, such as discarded rods or pipes. In 1925, H.C. George wrote that &amp;ldquo;the power or jack plant, and the machinery, shackle line, and jack are all usually standard and purchased from oil-well supply companies, but the shackle line structures are usually designed and built by the operating oil company. This results in a multiplicity of designs and a variety of material.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/schacklework_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/rocker-type_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/butterfly_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-system-supports_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Images: Jerker line system supports.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Images: Jerker line system supports.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some American towns, shacklework from neighbouring oil fields rocked back and forth over streets and alleys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jerker-line-systems-still-in-operation&#34;&gt;Jerker Line Systems Still in Operation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pennsylvania jerker line system became the dominant technology used to pump secondary oil wells up till the 1940s, pumping wells up to 3,500 feet deep, and remained in use until the 1960s and 70s. A few installations are stilll running today, or operated until recently. Some of the pictures above and below (there are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/&#34;&gt;many more if you follow this link&lt;/a&gt;), show the last two oil leases in Flat Rock, Illinois, which used a central power source and rod lines of the Pennsylvania type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-system-flatrock_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: Old Iron.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pennsylvania jerker line system, Flat Rock, Illinois, US. Source: [Old Iron](http://www.herculesengines.com/FlatRock/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each is run with a 35 horse power oil-engine and pumps 10 or 11 wells. The rods rest on wood stakes 15 to 20 feet apart and the power moves the rods about 40 cm back and forth. In some places, the rods are rigged to cross a creek or make a turn and head in a different direction. The systems were photographed in 2003, when they were still operational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most remarkable, however, are the central power systems in Oil Springs, Ontario, which have been in operation for 150 years now. Some of these oil fields still make use of the Canadian jerker line system, which was the original technology used to pump oil in the mid-nineteenth century when the fields came into production. Most of the lines on the Fairbank field, and some of the lines on the James field, use wooden rods that operate wooden pump jacks, while some lines on the James field, and all lines on the neighbouring fields, use the original Pennsylvania jerker line system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/canadian-jerker-line-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Canadian jerker line system, Ontario. Source: Markus Wandel.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Canadian jerker line system, Ontario. Source: [Markus Wandel](http://wandel.ca/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are obviously sentimental reasons for using nineteenth and early twentieth century technology — the owner of the fields is a great-grandson of John Henry Fairbank, designer of the Canadian jerker line system — the site is not a museum, but a working field that is economically viable. Instead of holding on to the past and trying to recreate a historic oil field, the technology has been continuously improved to maintain its profitability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-efficient&#34;&gt;More Efficient&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One major change in the technology is that steam engines have been replaced by small electric motors, which are cheaper, more efficient and easier to maintain. Most are equipped with reduction gearing, which has made the bulky powerhouse mechanism redundant. Individually-powered pump jacks have replaced the central power system in locations where running a jerker line has failed to be cost-effective, but where the central power system is still in use, it is so because it remains the most efficient and economical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/stangenkunst-in-ontario_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Stangenkunst in Ontario, Canada. Source: Markus Wandel.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Stangenkunst in Ontario, Canada. Source: [Markus Wandel](http://wandel.ca/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the remaining wooden field rods have been improved: metal hangers that once supported the wooden jerker lines have been replaced with nylon rope for ease of maintenance. The wood for jerker lines and pump jacks is not original, of course, since it is exposed to the elements:
the rebuilding of wood equipment has been an on-going historic process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/canadian-jerker-line-system-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Canadian jerker line system, Ontario. Source: Markus Wandel.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Canadian jerker line system, Ontario. Source: [Markus Wandel](http://wandel.ca/).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oil extraction is usually thought to be large in scale and finite in its lifecycle. However, in Oil Springs, it has been conducted on a continuous, small-scale basis since the late 1850s, while all other oil fields from those times have long been pumped dry using much more powerful technology. One cannot help but wonder how the world would have looked like if all oilmen had stuck with nineteenth century technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-applications&#34;&gt;Future Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jerker line system has value, and could be very helpful for those looking for ways to live comfortably life without excessive energy use. The system in the picture below — which still operates today in Oil Springs — is one that any maker could bolt together quickly in no time. With this set-up, one small electric motor could operate four machines in different locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/images/dithers/jerker-line-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Field motor on steel frame with steel jerker rods on the James Field. Image: &amp;amp;ldquo;Conservation district study appendix&amp;amp;rdquo;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Field motor on steel frame with steel jerker rods on the James Field. Image: &#34;[Conservation district study appendix](http://www.lambtononline.ca/home/residents/planninganddevelopment/Oil%20Heritage%20Conservation%20District%20Plan%20Documents/Forms/AllItems.aspx)&#34;, Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan, The Corporation of the County of Lambton.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do this instead of powering each device individually? One: you save three electric motors. Two: there is no need to provide batteries or electric outlets at any of the locations. Three: you can balance the system so that one device helps power the other, saving a considerable amount of energy. The electric motor shown above can also be replaced by &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;a windmill&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2010/11/boat-mills-water-powered-floating-factories/&#34;&gt;a water wheel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/07/the-bright-future-of-solar-thermal-powered-factories/&#34;&gt;a solar thermal plant&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/05/pedal-powered-farms-and-factories-the-forgotten-future-of-the-stationary-bicycle/&#34;&gt;a stationary bicycle&lt;/a&gt;. In these cases, you can distribute mechanical energy without conversion losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a Stangenkunst or jerker line system can only transfer mechanical energy via reciprocating motion, it has seen a remarkable variety of applications &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/&#34;&gt;throughout its 450 years of operation&lt;/a&gt;:
pumping (either oil or water), ventilation (operating bellows), processing ores (operating trip-hammers), and even transporting people and goods up and down shafts (operating man engines and bucket hoists). Reciprocating motion could also be used to operate sawing machines or, using trip-hammers, to forge iron, process food or fibres, or make paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc12407/m1/1/&#34;&gt;Surface Machinery and Methods for Oil-Well Pumping&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
H.C. George, Bulletin 224, Bureau of Mines, Department of     Interior, 1925.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lambtononline.ca/home/residents/planninganddevelopment/Oil%20Heritage%20Conservation%20District%20Plan%20Documents/Forms/AllItems.aspx&#34;&gt;Oil Heritage Conservation District Plan     Documents&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
The Corporation of the County of Lambton, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lcweb2.loc.gov/pnp/habshaer/pa/pa3500/pa3551/data/pa3551data.pdf&#34;&gt;Historic American Engineering Record; Addendum to Allegheny     National Forest Oil     Heritage&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;
(PDF), HAER No. PA-436, Michael W. Caplinger, 1997&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Allegheny Oil Powers: Documenting Endangered Cultural Resources in     Allegheny National Forest&amp;rdquo;, Christopher Marston, 2000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Technology on the Frontier - Mining in Old Ontario&amp;rdquo;, Dianne Newell,     1986&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Petroleum Mining and Oil-Field Development — a Guide to the     Exploration of Petroleum Lands, and a Study of the Engineering     Problems connected with the Winning of Petroleum.&amp;rdquo;, A. Beeby     Thompson, 1910.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wandel.ca/oil/&#34;&gt;Oil History in Ontario&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Markus Wandel -   &amp;ldquo;Early development of oil technology&amp;rdquo;, Wanda Pratt and Phil     Morningstar, 1987&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mechanical Transmission of Power (1): Stangenkunst</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/stangenkunst-1763_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="22571" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/stangenkunst-1763_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&amp;amp;lsquo;Stangenkunst, showing driving wheel, feldkunst, and kunstkreuz&amp;amp;rsquo;. Image: &amp;amp;lsquo;Acta historico-chronologico-mechanica circa Metallurgiam&amp;amp;rsquo;, Hennig Calvör, 1763&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 &#39;Stangenkunst, showing driving wheel, feldkunst, and kunstkreuz&#39;. Image: &#39;Acta historico-chronologico-mechanica circa Metallurgiam&#39;, Hennig Calvör, 1763
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-distance power transmission predates the invention of electricity by almost four centuries. From the 1500s onwards, engineers developed mechanical power transmission and distribution technologies, called &amp;ldquo;Stangenkunsten&amp;rdquo;, that became ever more sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Networks of pivoted, wooden field rods conveyed power from water wheels in the valleys to mining machinery up the mountains over distances of up to 4
km, operating pumps and bellows, hoisting ores, and transporting miners up and down shafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later systems replaced wooden rods by steel cables. Many Stangenkunsten remained in use well into the twentieth century, long after the introduction of steam engines and electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;revival-of-the-mining-industry&#34;&gt;Revival of the Mining Industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electricity allows us to build power plants in distant locations because it is easy to transport using power transmission lines. Before the advent of electricity, however, the configuration for any wind or water-powered industrial process usually placed both the machinery and the power source in the same location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mill not only housed the sails or the wheel, but also the machinery that it operated. The power generated by wind or water was transferred to the machinery over a very short distance via a set of wooden gears or cranks. This meant that factories and workshops using wind or water as an energy source could only be operated in locations were a mill was available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this was not always possible. Power production was especially problematic in the mining industry, since mines are situated in relation to mineral deposits, regardless of whether wind or water power is available. Mines needed mechanical energy for draining and ventilating mine shafts, for hauling up ores, for transporting miners, and for processing ores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European mining activity had declined substantially after the demise of the Roman Empire, but an &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/09/medieval-smokestacks-fossil-fuels-in-pre-industrial-times/&#34;&gt;urban revival at the turn of the millenium&lt;/a&gt;
brought a revival of the mining industry along with it. New mines were discovered and exploited, most notably in Germany. The Rammelsberg mines in the Harz Mountains were opened in 968 AD, followed by the Freiberg mining field in the Ore Mountains (&amp;ldquo;Erzgebirge&amp;rdquo;) in 1168 AD. Silver, copper and lead were the most important products of these famous mines, which would remain active for many centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/stangenkunst-huttall_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Stangenkunst in Huttal, east of Clausthal-Zellerfeld in the Harz Mountains, 1765. The drawing was made by the GeoMuseum of the Technische Universität Clausthal.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Stangenkunst in Huttal, east of Clausthal-Zellerfeld in the Harz Mountains, 1765. The [drawing](http://geomuseum.tu-clausthal.de/histoharz.php?section=43110&amp;level=14&amp;name=Huttaler%sp%Wasserregal&amp;details=on&amp;select=0&amp;nr=0&amp;art=) was made by the GeoMuseum of the Technische Universität Clausthal.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, mining operations required relatively little energy, as ores were extracted from shallow depths. Hauling up the ores and draining the mine of unwanted water, if necessary, was done by means of human-powered machines. However, when the most easily accessible ore deposits became exhausted and miners were forced deeper underground, more powerful machines were needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rammelsberg mines resorted to this in the twelfth and thirteenth centuries, with the Freiberg mines following in the fourteenth century. The main problem the mines faced was drainage: once you dig shafts and tunnels below groundwater level, flooding becomes a constant concern. Hauling up water to the surface requires more energy as the mine gets deeper, as does hauling up ores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/stangenkunst-sweden_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Stangenkunst in Pershyttan, Sweden. Image: Bengt Oberger.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Stangenkunst in Pershyttan, Sweden. Image: [Bengt Oberger](http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pershyttan_konstg%C3%A5ng_01.JPG).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution, already applied by Roman miners, was the construction of drainage adits. These gently sloping tunnels, which could be many kilometres long, connected the mine and a neighbouring valley. Excess water drained into the valleys by gravity alone. However, this only worked as long as the adit could be built above ground level. If miners dug deeper than the valley floor, the problem persisted. Initially, the solution lay in more efficient pumps and in substituting animal-powered lifting machines for human-powered lifting machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, horse whims were very expensive to operate and water-powered machines soon replaced them. (Wind power was not very practical for use in mining.) This implied, of course, that a running stream of water was available at the mine shaft. Most often, this was not the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solution-one-bring-water-to-the-mine&#34;&gt;Solution One: Bring Water to the Mine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common method of sourcing water involved the construction of leats, derivation channels, tunnels and aqueducts. This solution also took care of energy storage by using dams and ponds. The Romans had done it before: one Roman gold mine in Spain (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_M%C3%A9dulas&#34;&gt;Las Medulas&lt;/a&gt;) used seven aqueducts, carved in the rocks, to tap water from local rivers. Starting in the late Middle Ages, ever more sophisticated water distribution networks were built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/water-management-harz-mountains_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Water management methods and Stangenkunsten were often combined, such as in the Harz Mountains in Germany.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Water management methods and Stangenkunsten were often combined, such as in the Harz Mountains in Germany. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water management infrastructure in the Freiberg mining field had some 50 km of covered ditches, connecting about a dozen large dams. Most of it was built in the sixteenth century, with further extensions in the eighteenth, nineteenth and early twentieth centuries — today, the system is used to supply drinking water to the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water management infrastructure in the Harz Mountains, the largest pre-industrial water management system ever built for mining operations, had more than 600 km of canals and more than 140 dams. Nearly all the infrastructure was built in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, with some further improvements added in the nineteenth century. By 1868,
the system powered 200 waterwheels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stangenkunst-transporting-water-power-uphill&#34;&gt;Stangenkunst: Transporting Water Power Uphill&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these hydraulic engineering works only made sense when the waterwheels were lower than the river because gravity distributes the water. If the machinery was on a mountain and the river in a valley, quite common in mining operations, a means for energy to be transported uphill was necessary. It was in this context that mechanical power transmission originated during the 1500s. Power was transmitted from a waterwheel in a valley stream to machinery on a mountain by means of long lines of linked levers, rocking back and forth on pivots. This is how it worked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wooden rods were hooked together lengthwise, extending from the waterwheel to the mine shaft. The rods were hung from wooden poles, set in the ground along their path at sufficiently close intervals to prevent any undue sag between the points of suspension. Wooden hangers that swung like pendulums were hooked to the top of the poles and to the rods, holding the line up and allowing it to swing back and forth in a reciprocating motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each swing bracket acted as a lateral guide and a support, so that side-wind pressures did not deflect the rods far from a straight line. Friction was reduced to a minimum by the attachment of a strip of wood, against which the swinger rubbed only if deflected from a straight line. The size of the timber used for the rod lines depended on the power to be transmitted. A crank was used (&lt;a href=&#34;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:St%C3%A5ngg%C3%A5ng_video_2012.ogv&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;) to convert the circular motion of the waterwheel to a reciprocating motion that moved the rods back and forth — a mechanism that was already applied in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hierapolis_sawmill&#34;&gt;Roman water-powered stone sawmills&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/stangenkunst-jean-errard_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Power transmission via single suspended rod, Jean Errard, 1584&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Power transmission via single suspended rod, Jean Errard, 1584 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system became known as &amp;ldquo;Stangenkunst&amp;rdquo;, where &amp;ldquo;Stangen&amp;rdquo; can be translated as &amp;ldquo;rods&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Kunst&amp;rdquo; refers to a mechanism. Mining nomenclature is largely German in origin, because it was especially German metallurgists who pioneered and exported more sophisticated mining technology from the 1500s onwards, leaving their mark on metal production in large parts of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Graham Hollister-Short, one of the few historians who dedicated himself to the history of the Stangenkunst, the technology was probably invented in 1510 by Italian metallurgist Vanoccio Biringuccio, who designed a contraption that allowed a waterwheel to work the bellows at four separate forges at an ironworks. Though his system was used for distributing rather than transporting energy, some decades later the Germans applied the same approach to the transmission of mechanical energy over much longer distances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/Vanoccio-Biringuccio-Stangenkunst_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Vanoccio Biringuccio&amp;amp;rsquo;s Stangenkunst, drawing by Graham Hollister-Short.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Vanoccio Biringuccio&#39;s Stangenkunst, drawing by Graham Hollister-Short. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first Stangenkunst was introduced in the Ore Mountains in 1550 and at the Harz Mountains in the 1560s. By about 1590, the Stangenkunst was introduced at the Kopparberg mines in Sweden, and by 1600 it had reached Italy, England and what is now Belgium. By 1700, the system was extensively used in North and Central European mines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vertical-power-transmission&#34;&gt;Vertical Power Transmission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of mechanical power transmission that followed the contours of the landscape, paralleled the development of a similar technology for vertical power transmission in mine shafts. These can only be understood in relation to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever deeper mineshafts required a new power source to operate pumps and hoisting machines, as well as new types of pumps and hoisting machines. During the course of the fifteenth century, two new drainage machines appeared that allowed for deeper mining below adit: the rag and chain pump (around 1430) and the bag hoist (around 1470). By the 1530s, however, the limits of these machines had been reached. In his treatise on mine-pumping machinery, Graham Hollister-Short writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rag and chain pumps could raise water no more than 80 metres, while bag hoists, able to manage about 150 metres, worked so slowly that only modest inflows could be handled. As extraction neared these limits, the prospect of enforced abandonment of mines on a large scale must have appeared alarmingly close.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under these circumstances, a new type of pumping machine appeared: the rod pumping engine. In this machine, water was transported upwards via a series of communicating suction pumps and water boxes placed above one another. The basic design of the rod engine involved &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;the rotation of a horizontally acting assembly through 90 degrees so as to produce a vertically operating system&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. In other words, it was a Stangenkunst turned on its side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/rod-engine_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Left: The rod engine, as it is shown in Agricola&amp;amp;rsquo;s De Re Metallica (1556). Right: Agricola&amp;amp;rsquo;s rod engine, as redrawn to scale by Graham Hollister-Short.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Left: The rod engine, as it is shown in Agricola&#39;s De Re Metallica (1556). Right: Agricola&#39;s rod engine, as redrawn to scale by Graham Hollister-Short.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first prototypes appeared in Georgius Agricola&amp;rsquo;s famous 1556
book on mining, &lt;em&gt;De Re Metallica&lt;/em&gt;, in which the author notes that the machine had been around for ten years. The rod engine spread rapidly during the second half of the sixteenth century, gaining several improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horizontal &amp;ldquo;field rods&amp;rdquo; and vertical &amp;ldquo;shaft rods&amp;rdquo; were connected to each other by means of an &amp;ldquo;engine cross&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;Kunst Kreuz&amp;rdquo;), which switched the line of motion by 90 degrees. One beam of the cross was attached to the field rods, the other held the shaft rods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, from the late seventeenth century onwards, many writers defined the Stangenkunst as the combination of field rods, shaft rods, and a power source (one or more waterwheels), instead of just referring to the reciprocating field rods. It is this definition which is now generally accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/mines-Thurmhof-vein-Valentin-Fritzsche-1608_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A drawing of the 3rd, 4th and 5th mines on the Thurmhof vein made by Valentin Fritzsche in 1608, showing multiple rod engines.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A drawing of the 3rd, 4th and 5th mines on the Thurmhof vein made by Valentin Fritzsche in 1608, showing multiple rod engines.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;round-corners-up-hill-down-dale&#34;&gt;Round Corners, Up-hill, Down-dale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of three centuries, the technology used to transmit power from waterwheels to mineshafts became more sophisticated. During the 1590s, engineers developed a set of balanced rods, resembling a pantograph, which was more efficient than the single-rod machines because less energy was lost through friction. Single-rod systems remained in use whenever power was abundant, but the double-rod system offered great benefits when this was not the case. Graham Hollister-Short explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There are now a series of pairs of legs, each pair carrying an iron axle on which the swing arm is mounted. The ends of the swing arms support the upper and lower field rods in a rather complex fashion. The ends of each swing arm are cut out to provide slots. The slots housed not only the rods but also the small pivoted pieces of hard wood on which they reciprocated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efficiency of the double-rod system allowed for longer power lines. By the 1600s, the system was used to transmit energy over a distance of up to 2 km. By the 1700s, it reached up to 4 km.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/Power-transmission-contouring-double-rods-Georg-von-Lohneyss-1617_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Power transmission and contouring by means of double rods, Georg von Löhneyss, 1617&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Power transmission and contouring by means of double rods, Georg von Löhneyss, 1617 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, every Stangenkunst ran in a straight line, but by the 1640s, engineers had learned how to transmit power round corners as well as up-hill and downhill. They managed to round corners using a &amp;lsquo;Kunst Kreuz&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;engine cross&amp;rsquo;, a lever in the shape of a cross. It was this same component that was used to connect horizontal field-rods and vertical shaft-rods, but turned on its side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engine cross also allowed the attachment of a new branch of wooden rods to the line, so that one waterwheel could power machines in several locations. V-rods allowed for a change of direction up or down a slope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/panorama-harz-mines_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Panorama of the Harz mines (detail), Daniel Lindemeier, 1606.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Panorama of the Harz mines (detail), Daniel Lindemeier, 1606. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most Stangenkunsten were used to drive drainage pumps, they were also connected to bellows for ventilating mine shafts, and to pestles for processing ores. In order to further improve the scope of power transmission, the Stangenkunst could be combined with water management infrastructure; for instance, an aqueduct was used to supply a waterwheel which operated a Stangenkunst. Finally, even the horse whim was integrated in the power distribution network by connecting it to a Stangenkunst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-hoisting-machines-of-christopher-polhem&#34;&gt;The Hoisting Machines of Christopher Polhem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water-powered machines designed by Swedish engineer Christopher Polhem between 1690 and 1710 further extended the possibilities of the Stangenkunst. On the one hand, Polhem built several &amp;rsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo;
Stangenkunsten for Swedish mines, connecting pumps in mine shafts with waterwheels up to 2,500 m away. The picture below shows the rods of a Stangenkunst at the Bispberg mine. Polhem used a double set of wooden rods, which sat parallel to each other. The system is similar to the pantograph system, but turned on its side and with metal hangers instead of wooden ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/Stangenkunst-Bisperg-mine-Sweden-1700_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Stangenkunst at the Bisperg mine, Sweden, built around 1700 (the picture was taken in 1922).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Stangenkunst at the Bisperg mine, Sweden, built around 1700 (the picture was taken in 1922).
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Polhem also constructed rod systems for hoisting up ore from mines shafts. Strictly speaking, these were not Stangenkunsten (they were called &amp;ldquo;Hakenkunsten&amp;rdquo;), but the design principle was nearly identical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first Hakenkunst was completed at Blankstöten in the Falun copper mine in 1694. The water-powered machine hoisted buckets loaded with ore out of a mine shaft, carried them to a dump, emptied them, and automatically returned the empty buckets to the mine. The whole mechanism was operated by reciprocating rods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy from a waterwheel was transmitted via horizontal rods to the mine shaft. The horizontal rod was joined to two pairs of hooks furnished with vertical poles suspended into the pit. Buckets were hooked onto the poles at the lowest level, and then lifted vertically to a higher pair of hooks by the alternate motion of the pairs of poles. This motion continued until the bucket was raised up the surface. The buckets were emptied by means of an iron chain which hooked onto the bottom. The vertical poles were 60 metres long and had 15 pairs of hooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/hakenkunst-polhem_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hakenkunst by Polhem in the Falun copper mine. SOurce unknown.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hakenkunst by Polhem in the Falun copper mine. SOurce unknown. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar hoisting machine was completed in 1698 for the Humboberget mine. This machine consisted of two sets of poles with attached hooks. One set brought the loaded carriers to the surface, while the other brought the empty carriers down the mine. In 1701, Polhem completed another hoisting machine for the King Karl XI shaft at the Falun mine. He used two rope drums for raising the ore barrels, which were rotated by a complicated wooden rod transmission from a reversible water-wheel with one crankshaft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/hoisting-mechanism-polhem_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The hoisting mechanism at Blankstöten, Polhem&amp;amp;rsquo;s first machine at the Falun mine, completed in 1694. Note that the distance between the water wheel and the mine shaft is distorted. Engraving by Jan van Vianen, from a drawing by Samuel Buschenfelt.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The hoisting mechanism at Blankstöten, Polhem&#39;s first machine at the Falun mine, completed in 1694. Note that the distance between the water wheel and the mine shaft is distorted. Engraving by Jan van Vianen, from a drawing by Samuel Buschenfelt.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/hoisting-apparatus-polhem_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Polhem&amp;amp;rsquo;s hoisting apparatus at the King Karl XII shaft at the Falun mine in Sweden, built in 1701. Illustration by Samuel Sohlberg (1731)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Polhem&#39;s hoisting apparatus at the King Karl XII shaft at the Falun mine in Sweden, built in 1701. Illustration by Samuel Sohlberg (1731)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/hoisting-with-rods-polhem_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hoisting mechanism with double set of rods at the Humboberget mine, Sweden. Drawing by C.J. Cronstedt, 1729.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hoisting mechanism with double set of rods at the Humboberget mine, Sweden. Drawing by C.J. Cronstedt, 1729.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;man-engines&#34;&gt;Man Engines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mines became deeper, miners needed more time to descend and ascend mine shafts, and it could take up to two hours to ascend a mine which was 500 to 600 m deep. This led to the development of the &amp;ldquo;man engine&amp;rdquo;,
also known as the &amp;ldquo;power-ladder&amp;rdquo;, which was another adaption of the Stangenkunst. The principle of operation was identical to that of the bucket hoists designed by Polhem, but applied to the transportation of miners. The man engine allowed the miners to ascend and descend the mine about three times faster and with less energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/man-engine_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A man engine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A man engine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first man engine was installed in 1833 in the Harz mining region. From there the design spread to Belgium, England, Austria-Hungary, Norway, France, Australia, and the United States. In total, more than 100 man engines were built from the 1830s to the 1880s. The average man engine reached a length of 400 to 500 m, with the longest reaching 1,009 metres in 1883. It was not always necessary to hang new rods in the shaft, as the rods needed for pumping could be used at little increased cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man engines were built as single or double-rod systems. In the first case, the single rod was furnished with steps, while a series of platforms was fixed at different levels of the shaft. In the second case, miners jumped between platforms from two reciprocating rods. The miner, quitting one step, waited on the platform until the next step reached him. The rods, which were fastened together and reached to the bottom of the mineshaft, offered a reciprocating motion of typically 3-5
m. (These animations show how &lt;a href=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/52/BergbauKunstAnimation.gif&#34;&gt;double-rod&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.iomtoday.co.uk/hosted/mines/animation/magmanengine.html&#34;&gt;single-rod man engines&lt;/a&gt; work). Counterweights — large boxes filled with stones — were installed in order to avoid the full weight of the shaft and men weighing on the top linkage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single-rod engines could be used simultaneously by miners ascending and descending, provided that there was sufficient room upon the fixed platforms, while double-rod engines did not have this advantage. The person operating the engine regulated the supply of water according to the number of miners ascending. For descent, no power was required to set the man engine in motion thanks to gravity. Descending miners could also raise the men who had finished their shifts by gravity alone, with the waterwheel only regulating motion and reducing friction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stangenkunsten-during-the-industrial-revolution&#34;&gt;Stangenkunsten during the Industrial Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steam engines started replacing waterwheels from the 1860s onwards. Contrary to waterwheels, steam engines were not dependent on the proximity of a stream or river, and could thus be located close to the mine shaft. This eliminated the need for mechanical power transmission. Furthermore, steam engines could be placed at the bottom of the mine to power the pumps directly, making the vertical transmission of power redundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the Stangenkunst did not disappear. On the contrary, many systems remained in use well into the twentieth century, long after steam engines had been replaced by gas engines, petrol engines and electric motors. Moreover, new systems continued to be built. In fact, most Stangenkunsten appeared after, rather than before, the invention of the steam engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/operating-stangenkunst_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Stangenkunst with wooden rods in Lauthental, Harz Mountains, 1932. Source: Technische Kulturdenkmal, C. Matschoss.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Stangenkunst with wooden rods in Lauthental, Harz Mountains, 1932. Source: Technische Kulturdenkmal, C. Matschoss.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were three reasons for the persistent use of this technology. For one, not all regions were quick to replace waterwheels (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;wind mills&lt;/a&gt;) with steam engines. By 1900, the mine shafts in the Harz Mountains were more than 1,000 m deep, and both suction pumps and man engines were still powered by waterwheels and wooden field rods. This was probably because the technology worked well, suggests Robert Mulhaus in his treatise on mine pumping technology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The connection between the urgency of the problem of mine drainage in England, and the invention of the steam engine, has often been suggested. Perhaps the &amp;lsquo;backwardness&amp;rsquo; of Germany in steam engine experimentation, and later in the introduction of the Newcomen engine, was to some extent due to the adequacy of existing machinery to meet the problem of mine flooding, for it is not clear that this problem existed on the continent.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Harz Mountains, some Stangenkunsten powered by waterwheels operated until the 1970s. Even on the British Isles, which were at the forefront of the Industrial Revolution, some water-powered Stangenkunsten could be seen in the 1940s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stangenkunsten-on-rails&#34;&gt;Stangenkunsten on Rails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second reason for the survival of the Stangenkunst was the evolution of the technology during the Industrial Revolution. Most improvements were made possible by the availability of much cheaper and more durable iron and steel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/flat-rods-running-on-rails_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Flat rods running on rails at the Laxey mine, working for show (1939). Image: &amp;amp;ldquo;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&amp;amp;rdquo;.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Flat rods running on rails at the Laxey mine, working for show (1939). Image: &#34;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&#34;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such innovation was the use of rails, which reduced friction and made it possible to transmit greater amounts of power. (A similar innovation was applied around the same time for &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;turning windmills towards the wind&lt;/a&gt;). A good example of this is the Lady Isabella waterwheel on the Isle of Man — one of the most powerful water wheels ever built. It operated from 1850 to 1929, powering mine pumps up to 200 m away by means of wooden rods, and transmitting about 150 horse power. The wooden field-rods, which ran over a viaduct and worked to and fro with a 3 m stroke, were not supported by metal hangers but ran on wheels, which in turn moved back and forth on rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;steel-cables-replace-wooden-rods&#34;&gt;Steel Cables Replace Wooden Rods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important innovation, however, was the replacement of wooden rods by round iron bars or steel cables with forged eyes at the end. These metal rods, rocking back and forth, lay either in grooved wheels, which revolved in the tops of forked posts, or were supported by rocking posts. Angle bobs (supported by wheels running on rails) drove the field-rods around corners, while V-rods changed their direction down or up a steep slope. The four pictures below show some examples of their use in England. These devices are part of a Stangenkunst powered by waterwheels and used to drain mines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/angle-bobs-flat-rods_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Two lines of flat rods at Carloggas in 1938. These rods were led round a small angle by single-arm fend-off bobs, whose outer ends had a small wheel on a curved rail. Image: &amp;amp;ldquo;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&amp;amp;rdquo;.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Two lines of flat rods at Carloggas in 1938. These rods were led round a small angle by single-arm fend-off bobs, whose outer ends had a small wheel on a curved rail. Image: &#34;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&#34;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/angle-bob-for-turning-flat-rods_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;An angle bob for turning flat rods through a greater angle than the single-arm fend-off bob shown below. Wheal Remfry Clay Works. Image: &amp;amp;ldquo;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&amp;amp;rdquo;.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 An angle bob for turning flat rods through a greater angle than the single-arm fend-off bob shown below. Wheal Remfry Clay Works. Image: &#34;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&#34;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/v-bob-flat-rods_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;V-bob leading the flat rods down into the pit. Wheal Martyn in 1939. Source: &amp;amp;ldquo;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&amp;amp;rdquo;.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 V-bob leading the flat rods down into the pit. Wheal Martyn in 1939. Source: &#34;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&#34;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/01/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-1-stangenkunst/images/dithers/rocking-post-supporting-flat-rod_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;In the foreground: a flat rod supported on a rocking post at Carloggas&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 In the foreground: a flat rod supported on a rocking post at Carloggas 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clay Works in 1935. Lines of rods entirely supported on rocking posts have been used elsewhere. Image: &amp;ldquo;Steam engines and waterwheels: a pictorial study of some early mining machines&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of metal rods was more durable, less maintenance-intensive, and allowed for a more flexible system when transmitting mechanical energy over long distances: the steel or iron field rods could easily pass through roofs, bushes, forests, and tunnels. An account of this is given in Frank D. Woodall&amp;rsquo;s book the 1975 book &lt;em&gt;Steam Engines and Waterwheels:
a Pictorial Study of some Early Mining Machines&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Even in 1946 it was still possible to see waterwheels driving pumps in the china clay works of Cornwall. At Wheal Martyn near St. Austell a 35ft diameter waterwheel drove a remarkable layout of rods. Following them away from the wheel one soon found difficulty, for the rods passed through the roof of a large clay-drying shed. Making a detour the observer saw a smaller waterwheel and the rods from the large wheel close at hand. A footpath, presumably used by the man who oiled the wheels in their forked posts, helped one to follow the rods through a thicket of prickly bushes to another hazard. The rods worked in a low tunnel through a mass of made ground.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Woodall notes, systems like this were still in use in the 1970s:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Not many years after Wheal Martyn finished working the pumping shaft was caved in during WWII the only other set of flat rods, at Carloggas near St Austel, fell into disuse, but although it was the last flat rod system to work in Britain a similar system remained in use in Germany. Two waterwheels each driving two lines of rods were seen working at Bad Kreuznach in 1965. The rods were not on wheels but on inverted pendulums and looked to be of recent construction. Other waterwheels driving pumps can be seen at the salt springs in the Bavarian town of Bad reichenhall.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-stangenkunst-embraces-the-steam-engine&#34;&gt;The Stangenkunst Embraces the Steam Engine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third reason for the sustained popularity of the Stangenkunst was the fact that field-rods were combined with steam engines (and later also gas and petrol engines as well as electric motors) instead of waterwheels. In this way, one steam engine could operate multiple pumps, which was cheaper than setting up a steam engine (or other power source) for every mine shaft or pump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from pumping water out of mine shafts, or operating man engines, this configuration found a new application in oil production, initially in the United States but eventually all over the world. It was in the oil industry that the Stangenkunst reached the pinnacle of its development. &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/02/the-mechanical-transmission-of-power-2-jerker-line-systems/&#34;&gt;See part 2: Jerker line systems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The first half century of the rod-engine (c1540-c1600)&amp;rdquo;, Graham     Hollister-Short, in &amp;ldquo;Bulletin of the Peak District Mines Historical     Society&amp;rdquo;, Vol. 12, No. 3, Summer 1994. Historical Metallurgy Society     Special Publication: Mining before powder. -   &amp;ldquo;The vocabulary of technology&amp;rdquo;, Graham Hollister-Short, in &amp;ldquo;History     of Technology&amp;rdquo;, second annual volume, A. Rupert Hall and Norman     Smith, 1977&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mine pumping in Agricola&amp;rsquo;s time and later&amp;rdquo;, Robert P. Multhauf, in     &amp;ldquo;Contributions from the museum of history and technology: paper 7&amp;rdquo;,
United States National Museum Bulletin 218, 1959.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Polhem, the mining engineer&amp;rdquo;, Herman Sundholm, in &amp;ldquo;Christopher     Polhem, the father of Swedish technology&amp;rdquo;, William A. Johnson, 1963
(original version in Swedish, 1911)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Steam Engines and Waterwheels: a Pictorial Study of some Early     Mining Machines&amp;rdquo;, Frank D. Woodall, 1975&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dictionary of arts, manufactures, and mines containing a clear     exposition of their principles and practice&amp;rdquo;, Part 3, Andrew Ure,     1875&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fahrkünste - vom Harz in die Welt&amp;rdquo;, Thomas Krassmann, 2010&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stronger than a hundred men: A history of the vertical water     wheel&amp;rdquo;, Terry S. Reynolds, 1983&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;De Re Metallica&amp;rdquo;, Georgius Agricola, 1556&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Histoire générale des techniques, Tome I, II, III.&amp;rdquo;, Maurice     Daumas, 1962&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Contemporary reviews of mine water studies in Europe&amp;rdquo;, Christian     Wolkersdorfer and Rob Bowell, in &amp;ldquo;Mine water and the environment&amp;rdquo;,
2005, 24.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Revierwasserlaufanstalt Freiberg&amp;rdquo; &amp;amp; &amp;ldquo;Lower Harz Pond and Ditch     System&amp;rdquo;, Wikipedia in English and German, retrieved December 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;A textbook of ore and stone mining&amp;rdquo;, Clement Le Neve Foster, 1894&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aerial Ropeways: Automatic Cargo Transport for a Bargain</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/adam-wybe-aerial-ropeway_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="78343" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/adam-wybe-aerial-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Ropeway in Gdansk, built by Wybe Adam, 1644.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Ropeway in Gdansk, built by Wybe Adam, 1644. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, we use them almost exclusively to transport skiers and snowboarders up snow slopes, but before the 1940s, aerial ropeways were a common means of cargo transport, not only in mountainous regions but also on flat terrain, with large-scale systems already built during the Middle Ages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aerial ropeways can be fully or partly powered by gravity, and some deliver excess power that can be utilized to generate electricity or to drive cranes or machinery in nearby factories. Some innovative systems have been constructed in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-crossing-river_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Venetian Fausto Veranzio illustrated a refined bicable passenger ropeway in the &amp;amp;ldquo;Machinae novae&amp;amp;rdquo;, published in 1615 and 1617.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Venetian Fausto Veranzio illustrated a refined bicable passenger ropeway in the &#34;Machinae novae&#34;, published in 1615 and 1617. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we start, it is important to note that aerial ropeways (also known as aerial tramways or cableways) can be divided in two groups: monocable and bicable mechanisms. In a monocable system, one endless rope serves to both support and move the carriers in transit. In a bicable (or tricable) system, separate ropes sustain these functions: one or two static support ropes, the &amp;ldquo;carrying ropes&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;track cables&amp;rdquo;, and one or two light travelling &amp;ldquo;haul ropes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ancient and medieval ropeways were of both variety, while modern ropeways (from the 1850s onwards) were initially exclusively monocable systems. Later, bicable systems took over almost completely. At the end of the 19th century, both ropeway methods were also applied to canal transportation (see the article on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/12/trolley-canal-boats/&#34;&gt;trolley canal boats&lt;/a&gt;), with monocable systems used for &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/09/water-powered-cable-trains/&#34;&gt;cable trains&lt;/a&gt;. Bicable mechanisms are much better suited if the track spans larger distances and/or has steeper grades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If only one endless rope would be used on a track which includes a long span or a steep grade, it would become necessary to make the entire double length of the moving rope strong enough for the special strain that appears on that spot. Increasing the size of the rope affects the dimensions of the supports, sheaves and other fixtures throughout the line, adding to the costs. In a bicable system, the stationary carrying cable can be locally graduated to the strains it has to bear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ancient-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Ancient ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Ancient ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ropeways-in-ancient-times&#34;&gt;Ropeways in ancient times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways have been used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theelevatormuseum.org/f/f_5b.htm&#34;&gt;for more than 2,000 years&lt;/a&gt;, transporting both passengers and goods. The first sign of their use comes from the rugged Asiatic countries of China, India and Japan, where it is speculated that they may have been in operation since 250 BC. Men used rope to cross ravines, rivers and river-gorges, initially transferring themselves, hand over hand, with the body suspended by a crude harness. The harness eased the load and allowed a rest as the loop was slid along the rope track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ancient-ropeway2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Ancient ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Ancient ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ancient-ropeway-3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Ancient ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Ancient ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next application was to pull oneself back and forth in a basket or cradle, usually with a few belongings in tow. This was made possible by means of thinner cords fixed to the front and the back of the basket, or by gravity in case the arrival point was at a lower height than the starting point. The empty sling or basket was then drawn back to its original position by a smaller cord attached to the back as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the rope was threaded through a hollow piece of bamboo before being attached, so that the person could slide down the rope without burning their hands. All that was needed to build a ropeway was a rope, knots to tie the rope to a rock or tree or anchor on both sides, and a bow and arrow to shoot the rope across. After the invention of the crossbow by the Chinese, heavier cables could be shot over longer distances. Sometimes the rope was supported on simple wooden trestles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/animal-powered-cableway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: moving animals across a ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: moving animals across a ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/animal-powered-railway-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: animal-powered ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: animal-powered ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways were also used to transport pack animals. Inversely, pack animals were sometimes used to pull the ropeway. These early aerial ropeways were the forerunners of later technologies such as the suspension bridge and the elevator. They were also the closest approach to aerial navigation at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ropeways-in-the-middle-ages&#34;&gt;Ropeways in the Middle Ages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first mention of ropeways in medieval times appears in the &amp;ldquo;Taiheiki&amp;rdquo;, a Japanese historical epic written in the late 14th century. It relates how a Japanese emperor escaped via ropeway over a valley when surrounded by enemy forces. In Europe, initial reference to the use of ropeways can be found in Bellifortis, a weapons catalogue from 1405. A 1411 book is the first to show a drawing of a ropeway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1411 and 1440, when technologies such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2010/11/boat-mills-water-powered-floating-factories/&#34;&gt;water mills&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;windmills&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2010/03/the-sky-is-the-limit-human-powered-cranes-and-lifting-devices/&#34;&gt;harbour cranes&lt;/a&gt; became increasingly popular, references to both monocable and bicable operations increased. In South America, aerial ropeways to transport gold have been reported as far back as 1536.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/medieval-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: 1724 drawing of a ropeway. Leupold la macchina di Danzica.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: 1724 drawing of a ropeway. Leupold la macchina di Danzica. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 17th century saw an increase in design sophistication. Venetian Fausto Veranzio illustrated a refined bicable passenger ropeway in the &amp;ldquo;Machinae novae&amp;rdquo;, published in 1615 and 1617. It consisted of a wooden box in which the passengers rode, travelling on pulleys over a fixed rope (second picture from the start). The vehicle was propelled over the river by the occupants pulling themselves along by means of this slack loop. Dutchman Wybe Adam erected a successful large-scale operational system in 1644, which is described in the Danzig Chronicles (picture introduction and picture below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-construct-fortress-danzig_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Medieval ropeway in Danzig.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Medieval ropeway in Danzig. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam engineered a continuously circulating ropeway to carry the earthworks material in baskets for a hilltop fortress in Gdansk/Danzig. Ropeways were also constructed by monasteries built high on pinnacles, where they were used to lift supplies and visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ropeways-from-the-1850s-onwards&#34;&gt;Ropeways from the 1850s onwards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From about 1650 to 1850, no further progress was made. The technology had reached its maximum potential at the time, limited by the strength of the available ropes. This all changed with the arrival of the much stronger wire rope in the mid-nineteenth century, which led to the most successful period of aerial ropeways in history. Another breakthrough was the standard coupling designed in the early 1870s by the Austrian von Obach, which allowed the cars to be disengaged and reattached to the trackway. Last but not least, new power sources appeared: first steam engines, then electric motors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;motive-power&#34;&gt;Motive power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the end of the nineteenth century, aerial tramways had been powered by humans (sometimes using a windlass or a treadwheel), by animals (mostly gins worked by horses or mules), by waterwheels and/or by gravity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last option was (and is) only available in mountainous areas: the descending carriers deliver all or part of the necessary power to haul up the ascending carriers. If the descending cargo is sufficiently heavier than the ascending cargo, and the angle of descent is great enough, the ropeway could be kept running without any additional power input, making it a full-fledged zero emission transport mode. The speed of the descending carriages was governed by means of hand or water powered brakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-colour_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway station.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway station. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when the ascending load was heavy, gravity could be used to transport cargo up the mountain; where water was available at the highest point of the ropeway, it was possible to run materials up alone, employing the descending carrier as a counter-balance filled with water. The system is reminiscent of those used by &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/09/water-powered-cable-trains/&#34;&gt;some early 1900 cable trains&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;net-producer-of-energy&#34;&gt;Net producer of energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some gravity powered lines, where the surplus power delivered by the descending cargo was larger than the power required to haul up the ascending carriages, the cableway could be a net producer of energy. Power could be taken off at any point along the track and utilized to drive nearby machinery, for instance driving ore crushers, pumps or sawmills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ropeway thus offered the additional possibility of powering neighbouring factories solely by gravity. Before the arrival of electricity, this excess energy was transmitted by mechanical means (wire ropes). Present-day cargo ropeways (see further below) use the excess power to generate electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;extremely-efficient&#34;&gt;Extremely efficient&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of electricity as a power generator did not make aerial ropeways unsustainable - far from it. An electrically powered aerial ropeway is one of the most efficient means of transportation available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-colour-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It offers all the advantages of electric transmission (energy-efficient, relatively silent, power can be produced by renewable sources) while eliminating the many problems that come with batteries and charging stations (as is the case with electric cars). In mountainous regions, the electric motor can be assisted by gravity power from the descending carriers, further improving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, an aerial tramway offers some additional benefits in power consumption compared to other sustainable options such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/07/get-wired-again-trolleybuses-and-trolleytrucks/&#34;&gt;cargo trains, cargo trams (streetcars) or trolleytrucks&lt;/a&gt;. Firstly, energy delivery is more efficient with a fixed electric propulsion system in a single terminal than with transmission over large distance by wire. Secondly, because there is no interference with surface traffic, a constant speed can be maintained, again improving energy efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;applications-of-cargo-ropeways&#34;&gt;Applications of cargo ropeways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparatively, few aerial ropeways were built for passenger transportation at the turn of the 20th century, where their primary function was solidified as a means for cargo transportation. Applications were many and diverse, and they occurred all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-receptacles_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway carriers.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway carriers. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no information to be found on the total amount of ropeways that were once in existence, but some sketchy bits of data give us an idea. A source from 1899 names 900 aerial ropeways of a certain technical type in operation worldwide. A product catalog from 1909, still well before the heydays of cargo ropeways, names a figure of 2,000 ropeways worldwide of a certain brand (the Bleichert system), aggregating over 1300 miles in length and transporting 160 million tons annually. Evidently, this was not an obscure technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;warfare&#34;&gt;Warfare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early modern ropeway technology was led by the Europeans, particularly Germany and the Alpine countries - Austria, Switzerland, France and Italy. Aerial ropeways were extensively used for warfare in the Alps between the early 1900s and 1945. Italy used ropeways in the war against Turkey in 1908. During World War I and World War II, aerial ropeways were widely used in the mountain battles between Italy and Austria. Almost 2,000 ropeways were operated by the Italians and over 400 by the Austrians, with most of them being portable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-in-alps_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Military ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Military ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They could quickly be disassembled, moved using pack animals, and assembled somewhere else. Military ropeways were used to reinforce difficult terrain with troops, supplies, howitzers, ammunition and fortification building materials. They were also a short term solution for destroyed bridges and other water crossings, or to lower casualties to hospitals in stretcher carriages (as an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notechmagazine.com/2010/03/a-manual-for-the-transport-of-sick-and-wounded-by-pack-animals.html&#34;&gt;alternative to specially equipped pack horses&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mining&#34;&gt;Mining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many cargo cableways were utilized for mining purposes - the first ropeways in the US were for transporting materials when mining in the West was booming. There are many references to ropeways that carried ores (gold, silver, iron, copper), coal, stone, slate, clay, sand, granite, quartz, lime, phosphate rock and brownstone. These goods were usually transported from the mine to a crusher, a railway, a ship or (in the case of coal) a steam engine. Terminals could be set up on a short section of rail, and gradually moved towards the other terminal as the material was removed from before it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;agriculture&#34;&gt;Agriculture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important application was the carriage of agricultural products: fruits (like bananas), cereals (like wheat), and other plantation produce like cotton, tea-leaf or sugar cane. These goods were mostly transported from the fields to a mill or railway station. Aerial ropeways were in use on sugar plantations in Demerara, Jamaica, Mauritius, Martinique, St. Kitts, Guatemala, Australia and elsewhere, for the delivery of canes to the crushing mills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-agriculture_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway for transport of produce in agriculture.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway for transport of produce in agriculture. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrangement shown below was extensively adopted in Mauritius: several wire ropeways driven from the same point discharged on the same cane carrier. A great advantage was that the canes were delivered in a continuous stream direct on to the cane carriers and in quantities that were at no time large enough to demand redistribution in feeding the mill - somewhat similar to today&amp;rsquo;s just-in-time principle. Only one man took care of the discharge of the carriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/three-wire-tranway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Several wire ropeways driven from the same point discharged on the same cane carrier.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Several wire ropeways driven from the same point discharged on the same cane carrier. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases an agricultural ropeway was employed in combination with cartage, the canes being brought to certain points along the line by the carts. Ropeways were used for the carriage of beetroot to the sugar factories, in Holland for instance, where the system was used on flat land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-and-cart_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A horse cart passing under an aerial ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A horse cart passing under an aerial ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wood-products&#34;&gt;Wood products&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology was popular for the transport of wood and wood products: logwood, cordwood, sawed timber, charcoal, wood pulp, paper pulp and paper. These were usually transported from a forest to a sawmill or from a sawmill to a railway station. Aerial tramways were applied by builders to convey bricks and materials to the desired points. A ropeway could carry cement from the kilns to the works, and the empty carriers could be used for conveying up coal to the kilns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-carries-wood_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: An aerial ropeway for the transportation of logs.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: An aerial ropeway for the transportation of logs. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;factories&#34;&gt;Factories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another application was the transport of materials within factories - this could be anything, from manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s supplies, to refuse, materials in process of manufacture, merchandise of all kinds, and particularly products requiring careful manipulation, such as explosives, liquids or glassware. The ropeways in factories were generally short, and the cables could be frequently supported at many points from brackets fixed to the walls of adjacent buildings, saving costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-in-harbour_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway in a harbour.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway in a harbour. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways were in operation in many print works, linoleum works, mills and other factories. Examples were at artificial manure works near London (the line passed over buildings, dwelling-houses and yards full of workmen) and linoleum works near Middlesex (where the line - driven by water power - passed over a river and many of the workshops and roofs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways were used for connecting lines of railway at opposite banks of rivers where bridge building would be unduly costly or difficult. One of these lines was constructed to pick up wagons with their loads, traverse and put them on track at the other side and vice versa. On a much smaller scale, at the end of the 19th century, miniature wire ropeways were introduced in shops &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notechmagazine.com/2011/01/cash-ropeway-in-south-africa.html&#34;&gt;for transporting cash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;harbours&#34;&gt;Harbours&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In manufacturing establishments, cableways were operated to distribute material taken from boats or cars to certain storing places in the yards. Aerial ropeways were used by ship owners for the loading and unloading of their cargoes and/or for the bunkering of fuel (coal for the steam engine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways provided a means of forming piers for loading and discharging materials when ships and lighters were forced to lie at some distance from the shore because of the shallowness of the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-harbour_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway in a harbour.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway in a harbour. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-harbour-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway in a harbour.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway in a harbour. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these ropeway piers, at the Cape de Verde Islands, measured 1200 feet (365 metres) in length, of which 960 feet extended along the beach, and about 240 feet at right angles to the longer section to the end of the pier, where the coal was received and dispatched. The ropeway carried 15 to 25 tons per hour in either direction, and the motion of the rope was also utilized in working cranes at each terminal for raising or lowering coal. All this was powered by a 16 HP steam engine. The erection of the site took a mere three months. Similar installations were built in New Zealand and South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-supplies-ship_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway for unloading ships.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway for unloading ships. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/aerial-ropeway-ship_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeways were also tested to transport coal between ships on the sea.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeways were also tested to transport coal between ships on the sea. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;receptacles&#34;&gt;Receptacles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle. Below are some examples for minerals, produce, manure, coke, sacks of flour, textile goods (protected from the weather), cement, petroleum, wine and beer. Some of these carrier receptacles were unloaded by striking a catch, causing the bottom to open or the whole receptacle to capsize or tip up. Loading was mostly (though not always) done by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/receptacles1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/receptacles2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/receptacles3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: For every material carried by a tramway, there was a specially designed carrier receptacle. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;length-speed-and-capacity-of-the-lines&#34;&gt;Length, speed and capacity of the lines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lenghth, speed and capacity of aerial tramways gradually increased throughout the century. In 1911, aerial ropeway lines were typically 1,000 to 15,000 feet (305 to 4,600 metres) long, with a daily cargo capacity of 15 to 200 tons and speeds of around 2 to 5 mph (3,2 to 8 km/h). Some gravity powered installations were faster, with speeds around 15 to 30 mph (24 to 48 km/h), but higher speeds were considered to be a negative influence on wear and tear. Weight of the individual loads varied from 25 to 375 kilograms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/tree-trunk-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Aerial ropeway transporting lumber.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Aerial ropeway transporting lumber. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motive power, if applied, was generally from about 2 to 15 HP. The fall was between zero (almost horizontal lines) and 4,000 feet (1,220 metres). Working staff amounted to 2 to 5 people. Some lines were built parallel to each other in order to increase cargo capacity (the maximum capacity of a single ropeway was about 800 tonnes per day). Some early ropeways were longer and more powerful. The Usambara ropeway in Africa was 5.6 miles (9 kilometres) long and transported tree trunks weighing up to one tonne each (picture above). At its highest point, the ropeway was 130 metres above the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/argentinian-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Argentinian ropeway (1906-1927), picture by Patricio Lorente.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Argentinian ropeway (1906-1927), picture by [Patricio Lorente](http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archivo:Cable_line_of_the_Mexican_Mine_in_Chilecito,_Argentina.jpg). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Garrucha ropeway, an installation at iron ore mines in Almeria, Spain, was 9.75 miles (15 km) long. The construction of the line took only 6 months. It had a daily transport capacity of 420 tons (working ten hours per day), powered by a 100 HP engine. Similar tramways were built in mines in Basque country, north-western Spain (two pictures below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Transylvanian wire ropeway, an installation at blast furnaces in Hungary transporting charcoal and ore, was nearly 19 miles (30,6 km) in length, and had a fall of almost 3,000 feet (915 metres). Capacity was around 800 tons per working day. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Mina_La_Mejicana&#34;&gt;ropeway in Argentina&lt;/a&gt; (picture above), in operation from 1906 to 1927, was 21.3 miles (35 km) long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-spain_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: An aerial ropeway in Spain.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: An aerial ropeway in Spain. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1920s saw the construction of even longer ropeways. The longest in Europe was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.adurcal.com/enlaces/cultura/zona/historia/cable/cabledurmotril.htm&#34;&gt;the line erected in 1925 in Granada, Spain&lt;/a&gt;. It was used to carry goods from the city to the harbour in Motril over a distance of 39 kilometres. The infrastructure consisted of 240 towers and 7 stations. The 300 vehicles with a loading capacity of 700 kg each travelled at a speed of 3 metres per second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the ropeway was built, the port of Motril quickly attracted more traffic. In 1929, an additional 200 vehicles were added to the line. Interestingly, the Granada ropeway was a public service - anybody and everybody could make use of it. Operations ceased in 1950, following the demise of local industry and agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-bilbao-1891_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: An aerial ropeway in Bilbao, Spain.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: An aerial ropeway in Bilbao, Spain. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The longest cargo tramway in the world during the 1920s was used for the transport of coffee &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.banrepcultural.org/blaavirtual/exhibiciones/ferrocarriles/secciones/cable_mariquita.htm&#34;&gt;from Manizales to Mariquita&lt;/a&gt;, Colombia. More than 800 vehicles travelled on the 72 kilometre line (45 miles), which was supported on more than 400 towers. The ropeway was opened in 1923 and remained in service until 1961.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1930s and 1940s saw the construction of the longest ropeways ever built, with lengths of up to 96 kilometres (60 miles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1930s and 1940s saw the construction of the longest ropeways ever built. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forsby-K%C3%B6ping_limestone_cableway&#34;&gt;Swedish Forsby-Köping limestone ropeway&lt;/a&gt; was the longest in Europe at the time of construction (42 km or 26 miles, in operation from 1939 to 1997), but this record was beaten by the 96 km (60 miles) long &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norsj%C3%B6_aerial_tramway&#34;&gt;Norsöj aerial tramway&lt;/a&gt;, also in Sweden. It had 514 towers and 25 tension stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tramway, which was in operation from 1943 to 1987, was built in just 370 days and is the longest cableway ever constructed. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainweb.org/italeritrea/teleferica1.htm&#34;&gt;Massawa-Asmara ropeway in Eritrea&lt;/a&gt;, built by the Italians, was 75 km (46.5 miles) long and was used from 1937 to 1941. In 1959, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COMILOG_Cableway&#34;&gt;76 km long cableway&lt;/a&gt; with 858 support towers started operation in the Republic of Congo. It remained in use until 1986, operating 24 hours per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;transport-infrastructure&#34;&gt;Transport infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeway towers could be constructed from timber or iron and were generally between 100 and 300 feet (30 to 90 metres) apart, although much longer spans were possible if necessary. In bicable ropeways the tension in the track cables was produced by weights applied at one of the terminal stations. However, in longer lines it became necessary to apply additional tension at intermediate points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this purpose tension stations were built at distances of about 3000 to 6000 feet. The cars passed from one section of the cable to the next by means of intervening rails - so that no interruption occurred in the continuity of the track. This means that there are no limits to the length of a ropeway: each (longer) ropeway consisted of multiple sections that could be considered as separate ropeways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeways-parts_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A ropeway station.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A ropeway station. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-angle-station_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A ropeway tension station.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A ropeway tension station. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same technique was applied to &amp;ldquo;angle stations&amp;rdquo;, which were used to make a curve in a ropeway (tension stations and angle stations could be combined - see the illustration above). The largest drawback of an aerial tramway, also relevant today, is that it can only be built in a straight line. Every angle in a ropeway requires the erection of an angle station, which raises capital costs. However, in general, few angle stations are needed because ropeways can be constructed above most obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, each tension and/or angle station can also double as a loading or unloading station. Goods could even be sent along different routes via a switch if more ropeways met at a single point. The picture above shows a ropeway switchyard of a German coal plant (described in a 1914 book) where three lines of carriers converge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-infrastructure_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A ropeway angle station.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A ropeway angle station. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/guard-net-for-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A tramway passsing under a ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A tramway passsing under a ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To guard against the risk of accident from the premature discharge of a bucket or other cause when crossing public highways or railroads, wire nets were usually suspended between supports on either side, or structures especially erected for the purpose. An arrangement of a shelter bridge as required by a county council to hide the cableway where it passed over a public road can be seen on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-a-ropeway&#34;&gt;Installing a ropeway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instalment of ropeways in the mountains was not an easy task. The long rope was usually shipped on reels holding several thousand feet, but where the upper part of the line was inaccessible to wagons, the rope, like the rest of the machinery, had to be packed so that it could be loaded on mules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each animal carried about 250 pounds (115 kg) - including the piece of slack rope fifteen or twenty feet long connecting its load to the next one in the rear. This piece was usually held up by a walking person so that it would not drag on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/installing-ropeway-donkeys_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Packing traction rope over a mountain trail.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Packing traction rope over a mountain trail. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/mule-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A mules train transports a wire rope up the mountain.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A mules train transports a wire rope up the mountain. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accidents happened, of course. A 2 mile long ropeway in Mexico for conveying wood to a mill had a fall of 3,575 feet. The constructor notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The transport of this rope was, owing to the rough nature of the country to be traversed, a matter of very serious difficulty. It was accomplished by dividing the rope into ten lengths, each length made up into seven coils, with an intermediate length of ten feet, and each of the coils was loaded upon the back of a mule, the entire train being composed of 70 mules and three men being provided to each seven mules, or thirty men altogether.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;During the conveyance of the section of rope to the upper terminal an accident occurred which was productive of very considerable delay, and demonstrated the difficulties attendant upon the operation. The head mule, at a point where a rise immediately followed a steep descent, started to take the rise with a rush until checked by the rope, which threw him backwards over the bank, he taking two other mules with him, and had not the last of these caught on a tree, the rest of the train would have followed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-many-advantages-of-ropeways&#34;&gt;The many advantages of ropeways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did aerial ropeways become so successful at the turn of the twentieth century? The main reason was that they were considerably than their alternatives, be it transport by horses and carts or transport by railroad. The ropeway was economical in operation and required only a minimal capital outlay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investment that would be entailed in a hilly country by the necessity of making tunnels, cuttings and embarkments for a line or railway was avoided. A cableway could be constructed and worked on hilly ground at a cost not greatly exceeding that which would be called for on a level country. Rivers and ravines could be crossed without the aid of bridges. Gradients quite impractical to ordinary railroads could be worked with ease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/chinese-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Cross-section of a Chinese ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Cross-section of a Chinese ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One calculation showed that a ropeway only 1 mile (1,630 metres) long with a difference in altitude of 0.4 miles (645 meters), would require a railway of 15 miles (24 km) to reach the same point. Ropeways were also generally half as expensive to operate when compared to cartage by mules, horses, and oxen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, an aerial tramway could be up and running in no time. Some lines could be easily moved from one place to another with comparative ease. An installation of 1 mile length at a beetroot farm in Holland, with a daily capacity of 50 tons, could be taken down and put up again in a fresh place in one day, by the aid of 20 men, provided the distance to cart the component materials did not exceed 5 miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/hoist-conveyor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Hoist conveyor in the USA.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Hoist conveyor in the USA. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways continued to work during weather conditions that would bring surface hauling to a standstill (like floods or heavy snow, especially interesting in mountain areas) and they could be operated at night without hazards. Wear and tear were relatively low. Ropeways did not occupy any material quantity of ground, and the intervening land between posts could be left for cultivation or other use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terminals could be arranged so that the material transported could be delivered at the exact spot where it was needed, saving all the expense of rehandling. One disadvantage thet ropeways had was that they were more vulnerable to high winds and electrical storms than other transportion options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cargo-tramways-today-renewed-interest&#34;&gt;Cargo tramways today: renewed interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantages of aerial cargo ropeways are so numerous that it is no surprise that they are - slowly - being rediscovered. Worries about global warming, peak oil and environmental degradation have made the technology even more appealling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not only concern energy use: contrary to a road or a railroad track, a cargo ropeway can be built straight through nature without harming animal and plant life (or, potentially, straight through a city without harming human life). Traffic congestion also plays into the hands of cableways, because the service is entirely free from interference with surface traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/modern-aerial-ropeway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A modern aerial ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A modern aerial ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practical Action has been designing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notechmagazine.com/2009/10/aerial-ropeways-in-nepal.html&#34;&gt;cargo ropeways in Latin America&lt;/a&gt; for some time now as an appropriate tech solution. In this case, aerial ropeways are mostly a substitution for pack animals, as they were one century ago in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2007, another non-governmental organization built a gravity powered cargo ropeway in India that &lt;a href=&#34;http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=48170&#34;&gt;serves 2,000 families&lt;/a&gt;. It costs just 14,000 dollars and transports agricultural produce downhill while taking manure to fertilize the fields uphill (&lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/&#34;&gt;a very wise thing to do&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some companies have started offering commercial cargo ropeways again. One of these is Femecol, a Colombian enterprise that offers relatively small-scale solutions. But the big guys are moving, too. French company Poma, one of the largest manufacturers of chair lifts, gondola lifts, funiculars and people movers, has constructed industrial applications of ropeways in France, Brazil, Iran and Peru. In these and in the follwing applications, aerial ropeways are mostly a substitute for cargo transportation by trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-over-motorway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: a modern ropeway crosses a highway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: a modern ropeway crosses a highway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-over-motorway-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: a modern ropeway crosses a highway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: a modern ropeway crosses a highway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first modern Poma cargo tramway was built in 1990 in Grenoble, France. It is operated for a cement factory and crosses a river and a motorway (pictures above). The line is 1.8 km long, climbs 121 metres and can handle 324 tonnes per hour - a capacity that is considerably higher than that of older systems (though the line is rather short). Each of the 56 vehicles can hold 900 kg and travel at a maximum speed of 18 km/h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, a similar cargo ropeway was built in La Oroya, Peru for the lead, zinc and copper mining company Doe Run. It has a similar length to the line in France but climbs 1.65 km (pictures below). It is much slower (5.4 km/h) and it has a lower capacity (70 tonnes per hour - similar to the capacity of the larger systems built in the first decades of the twentieth century).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-mining_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A ropeway for a mining company.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A ropeway for a mining company. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be said that the ropeway - which replaced a much older system with a smaller capacity - seems to be the only sustainable element of the mining company, because Doe Run is in hot water with local environmentalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;innovation-the-ropecon-system&#34;&gt;Innovation: the RopeCon system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main competitor to Poma, the Austrian/Swiss conglomerate &amp;lsquo;Doppelmayr Garaventa Group&amp;rsquo;, takes cargo tramways even more seriously. On their website, they offer &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.doppelmayr.com/es/productos/telefericos-para-transporte-de-materiales/&#34;&gt;cargo ropeways&lt;/a&gt; with lengths of up to 10 km, transport capacities of up to 1,500 tonnes per hour and individual loads of 40 tonnes. A temporary, 2 kilometre long system is being built to help in the construction of a pumped storage hydropower plant in Switzerland. But the company also designed a new concept that further improves upon the cargo ropeway: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.doppelmayr-mts.com/loesungen/ropeconr/?country=all&#34;&gt;RopeCon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mining Weekly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.miningweekly.com/article/costefficient-highcapacity-material-transport-over-difficult-terrain-2008-05-30&#34;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; it as &amp;ldquo;a bulk material and unit load handlling conveyor, which combines the benefits of well-proven ropeway technology with those of a conventional conveyor belt&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RopeCon system in Jamaica saves 1,200 truck journeys per day and generates 1,300 kWh of braking energy per day, which is fed back into the power network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the advantages over the traditional ropeway are a higher load capacity, better wind resistance, and the need for fewer towers (which makes the lines even easier to integrate into existing terrain). The overhead conveyor system consists of a belt with corrugated side walls and integrated sets of wheels that run on fixed anchored track ropes, guided over tower structures. Individual sections can be built up to a length of 20 kilometres, with a maximum transport capacity of 10,000 tonnes per hour. To date, about 6 lines have been built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropecon-jamaica_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A Ropecon system in Jamaica. Credit: Doppelmayer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A Ropecon system in Jamaica. Credit: Doppelmayer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropecon-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A Ropecon system in Jamaica. Credit: Doppelmayer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A Ropecon system in Jamaica. Credit: Doppelmayer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most spectacular system, which has been tested in hurricane winds of 249 km/h, was built in 2007 for a Jamalco/Alcoa bauxite mine on Mt Olyphant in Jamaica (picture above). It is 3.4 kilometres long and has a vertical descent of 470 metres. The installation conveys some 1,200 tonnes of bauxite per hour from the mine to the processing plant, saving about 1,200 truck journeys per day and generating about 1,300 kWh of braking energy per day, which is fed back into the power network. The transport network thus doubles as a renewable energy plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable cargo installation is the RopeCon for fiber manufacturer Lenzing, which is used for the transport of wood chips from the storage area to the processing plant. The 665 metre long automatic transport system crosses existing plants and conveyor systems, a river and several roads with minimum tower structures (pictures above and below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ropeway conveys 350 tonnes per hour, and although the system does not generate energy because it is built on flat terrain, the engine output is only 53 kW - similar to that of a small car. The line was designed to guarantee 100 percent availability at wind speeds of up to 130 km/h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropecon-system-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A Ropecon system. Credit: Doppelmayer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A Ropecon system. Credit: Doppelmayer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropecon-siberi_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A Ropecon system in Papua New Guinea. Credit: Doppelmayer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A Ropecon system in Papua New Guinea. Credit: Doppelmayer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/future-ropeways_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A Ropecon system in Papua New Guinea. Credit: Doppelmayer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A Ropecon system in Papua New Guinea. Credit: Doppelmayer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since May 2008, a system on the island of Simberi in Papua New Guinea transports gold ore over a distance of 2.7 km while using only three support towers over the entire length. The ore is transported from the mine in the interior of the country through the tropical rain forest and fissured terrain to the smelting facility at the harbour. The vertical rise is 237 metres. Transportation capacity is 450 tonnes per hour and the system generates 221 kWh of energy per day through braking power, which is utilized in the gold refinery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A temporary RopeCon installation was set up for the construction of a tunnel in Austria, where it was used for the transport of rock excavation material. Conveying capacity was 600 tonnes per hour, while engine output was very modest at 30 kW. The line was 270 metres long, with a vertical rise of 23 metres. It eliminated 115,000 truck journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future-of-ropeways&#34;&gt;The future of ropeways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be perfectly possible to construct similar lines all over the place and get most cargo traffic off the road - not only when it comes to gold or bauxite mines. A cargo tramway could be built from a train station or parking lot outside the city to a shopping mall, or along the motorway between two towns or cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could send produce from agricultural fields and goods from factories straight into shopping districts or into a moored ship, without ever touching the ground. There would be no delays due to gridlocks or traffic accidents. Noise and vibration would be minimal. The low energy requirements could easily be met by renewable, stationary energy sources. In short, a ropeway offers all the benefits of an &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2008/02/a-world-without-trucks-underground-freight-networks/&#34;&gt;underground freight network&lt;/a&gt; without the enormous capital costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could even build a fully-fledged local, regional or even national or international transportation network of cableways using switch stations that would be cheaper in capital and operational costs than any other alternative (including trolleytrucks, cargo trams, trains and cable cars).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/images/dithers/ropeway-line_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: An aerial ropeway.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: An aerial ropeway. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, yesterday&amp;rsquo;s ropeways are not suited to handle today&amp;rsquo;s freight loads. For example, today, 400 trucks of 30 tonnes each drive up and down daily between Granada and the harbour in Motril, Spain. That is a total load of 12,000 tonnes, while the local ropeway that was in operation from 1925 to 1950 had a capacity of only 210 tonnes per day (for 10 working hours).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as noted, Doppelmayr now offers cargo tramways with capacities of up to 1,500 tonnes per hour, which would be more than enough to get all trucks off the road again. RopeCon systems offer even higher capacities. On the other hand, lowering demand for cargo transport would defenitely make ropeway technology a more realistic option, just as lowering energy demand would surely help the greening of the energy infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ropeways won&amp;rsquo;t work everywhere, and they are most advantageous in mountainous or moderately level regions. This is not only because a vertical rise can turn the ropeway into a power generator instead of a power consumer, but also because the alternatives (rail, road) are more expensive and complicated to build than on level terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, even on flat ground a cargo ropeway could be a more sustainable option than most other alternatives. The only motorized transport option that seems to be able to compete with the ropeway in terms of both capacity, efficiency and cost is canal transport - even more so if &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2009/12/trolley-canal-boats/&#34;&gt;trolleyboats&lt;/a&gt; were used. Canal transport is best suited for level regions and thus perfectly complementary with cableways. And what about those trucks? They are so twentieth century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;About ropeways&amp;rdquo;, The Information Center for Ropeway Studies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hercules Aerial Tram Mobility Study &amp;amp; Report&amp;rdquo;. Investigates a wider application of passenger ropeways, but also has interesting information on cargo ropeways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The wire rope and its applications&amp;rdquo;, 1896&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ropeways&amp;rdquo;, The Elevator Museum, website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Aerial or rope-ways: their construction and management&amp;rdquo;, 1911&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Transport by Aerial Ropeways&amp;rdquo;, W.T.H. Carrington, The Engineering Times, 1899&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die Drahtseilbahnen&amp;rdquo;, 1914&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chemins de fer funiculaires - transports aériens&amp;rdquo;, 1894.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wire rope tramways with special reference to the Bleichert patent system&amp;rdquo;, Edmund Gybbon Spilsbury, 1890.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wire rope transportation in all its branches&amp;rdquo;, Trenton Iron Co. 1896&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Bleichert system of aerial tramways&amp;rdquo;, 1909&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Across the Chilkoot pass by wire cable&amp;rdquo;, William Hewitt, 1898&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;El cable Dúrcal-Motril (Granada)&amp;rdquo;, Francisco Calvo Poyo, Universidad de Granada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Hallidie endless wire ropeway&amp;rdquo;, California Wire Works, 1902&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Un po&amp;rsquo; di storia degli impianti a fune&amp;rdquo;, Associazione Nazionale Italiana Tecnici Impianti Funiviari.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;El bandido que asaltaba el cable más largo del mundo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The genius of China: 3,000 years of science, discovery and invention&amp;rdquo;, Robert Temple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Science and technology in China&amp;rdquo;, Volume IV:3, Joseph Needham.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
