<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>/tags/health-care/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/health-care/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Sustainable is High-tech Health Care?</title>
      <link>/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/the-surgeon_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="71049" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/the-surgeon_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The surgeon, a painting by David Teniers, 1670s.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The surgeon, a painting by David Teniers, 1670s. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-environmental-footprint-of-the-health-care-sector&#34;&gt;The environmental footprint of the health care sector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health care is one of the most important economic sectors in high income countries, but its environmental footprint is underreported and not often considered. Most research into sustainable health care is less than five years old. A 2019 research paper calculated that the sector accounts for 2-10% of national carbon footprints across all OECD countries, China, and India, with an average share of 5.5% overall. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data refer to the year 2014, when the health care sectors of all these 36 countries combined were responsible for 1.6 Gt of greenhouse gas emissions. This corresponds to 4.4% of the global total emissions that year (35.7 Gt) – almost double the share of aviation. The US has the most carbon-intensive health care system, accounting for up to 10% of national carbon emissions. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It also produces 9% of national air pollution, 12% of acid rain, and 10% of smog formation nationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The environmental footprint of health care keeps increasing. For example, in the US, the health care sector’s greenhouse gas emissions grew by 30% between 2003 and 2013. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The rise in emissions couples an increase in spending – in fact, the emissions are often calculated based on spending. US national health expenditures as a percentage of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) increased from 3% in 1930, to 5% in 1960, to 10% in 1983, to 15% in 2002, and to 17.7% in 2019. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the EU, health care spending per capita more than doubled between 2000 and 2018, and total spending is now at 9.9% of GDP. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the whole world would copy today’s US health care system, the global carbon footprint of the health care sector would amount to almost half of total emissions worldwide in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 36 countries whose health care systems together cause 4.4% of global emissions only have 54% of the worldwide population. The remaining 46% of the population produces little or no health care related emissions because they don’t have access to health care. If we were to extend the OECD-China-India health care system globally, emissions would double to about 8% of the worldwide total. Furthermore, there are very large differences between these 36 countries. If the whole world were to copy the US health care system, the global carbon footprint of the health care sector would amount to around 16 Gt – almost half of total emissions worldwide in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;intense-spotlights-high-power-medical-equipment&#34;&gt;Intense spotlights, high power medical equipment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes modern health care so resource-intensive? &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; To start with, modern hospitals are high energy users, primarily because of large plug loads from medical devices, lighting, ventilation and air-conditioning. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In operating rooms, the high power use is mainly due to the use of intense spotlights and ultra clean ventilation canopies. In intensive care units and diagnostic imaging departments, medical equipment dominates the power load. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/operating-room_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Technologically Advanced Operating Room. iStock.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Technologically Advanced Operating Room. iStock. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/MRI-scanner-3T_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;An MRI-scanner in Taipei, Taiwan (2006). Image: Kasuga Huang (CC BY-SA 3.0).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 An MRI-scanner in Taipei, Taiwan (2006). Image: Kasuga Huang (CC BY-SA 3.0). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like so many other sectors in modern society, health care has come to rely on all types of machines and devices. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some of this medical equipment has very high power use. For example, an MRI-scanner, one of the most powerful diagnostic imaging technologies, can use as much electricity as more than 70 average European households. A 2020 study calculated that high-tech medical diagnostic technology (both MRI- and CT-scanners) was responsible for a whopping 0.77% of global carbon emissions in 2016. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power use of smaller medical equipment is poorly researched, but an inventory of two US hospitals showed that they had 14,648 and 7,372 energy using devices, of which the infusion pumps alone consumed more electricity on aggregate than an MRI-scanner. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The high density of medical equipment also increases the electricity use of air-conditioning in hospitals. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resource-use-along-the-supply-chain&#34;&gt;Resource use along the supply chain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more energy – around 60% of the total – is used indirectly along the supply chain. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This concerns the procurement of medical equipment, pharmaceuticals, and other medical products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, the growing number of medical devices used in hospitals also needs to be manufactured and brought to market. This requires activities such as the mining of resources and the construction and operation of research laboratories, factories and transport vehicles. This &amp;ldquo;embodied energy&amp;rdquo; of the medical equipment supply chain is very poorly researched. A study calculated that the production of an MRI-scanner requires more than half the fossil fuels used in the production of a passenger jet, and that the embodied energy is one third of the total energy use of the machine. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern health care is also highly dependent on pharmaceuticals, which account for between 10 and 25% of total health care emissions, depending on the country. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A 2019 study revealed that the global pharmaceutical industry produces more greenhouse gases than the global automotive industry: 52 MtCO2 versus 46 MtCO2. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, there is almost no data about the environmental footprint of specific pharmaceuticals, because corporate secrecy prevents scientists from making life cycle analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/pharma-lab_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Laboratory. Source: iStock.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Laboratory. Source: iStock. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/gloves-production_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Rubber gloves production line. Source: iStock.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Rubber gloves production line. Source: iStock. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/mask-production_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Face mask production line. Source: iStock.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Face mask production line. Source: iStock. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single-use disposable products are another source of health care energy use and pollution. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These products are worn by medical personnel and patients (face masks, gloves, overshoes, hats, drapes, gowns). Towels, basins, sterile plastic packaging, and utensils such as syringes, laryngoscopic handles and blades, anaesthetic breathing circuits, and even surgical instruments are also provided for single use. These disposable products are supplied to hospitals in so-called custom packs, which are sets of prepackaged sterile products for any specific medical procedure you can imagine. In principle, once a pack is opened, all items are discarded, even if they were not used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When these practices are questioned, it is often for the hospital waste they create &amp;ndash; the average patient in a hospital produces at least 10 kg of waste per day. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, the environmental footprint increases significantly if the embodied energy and waste in the supply chain for making these disposable products is considered too. A study of cataract surgery in the UK – cataracts are the main cause of blindness worldwide – shows that the manufacturing of disposable materials accounts for more than half of the total carbon footprint of the procedure. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;anesthetics--vaccines&#34;&gt;Anesthetics &amp;amp; Vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, some specialist medical drugs produce emissions too. Inhalation anesthetics, which suppress the central nervous system and are a cornerstone of surgery, are potent greenhouse gases, which evaporate into the atmosphere after they have been inhaled by the patient (vented to the outside through the high energy ventilation systems of modern operating rooms). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Maintaining a 70 kg adult anesthetized for an hour produces from 25 kg (using isoflurane) to 60 kg (desflurane) CO2-equivalents, which corresponds to the emissions of driving an average European car (121gCO2/km) for 200-500 km (or driving it for around 4 hours). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressurized dose inhalers, which are used to treat asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, also release potent greenhouse gases. Globally, around 800 million pressurized dose inhalers are manufactured annually, with a total carbon footprint that corresponds to the yearly emissions of more than 12 million passenger cars. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Vaccines are another key element of modern health care. They release carbon emissions not only through their development and production, but also by their resource-intensive distribution, which involves a dedicated cold chain. I could not find any reference to its environmental footprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;carbon-footprint-of-medical-procedures&#34;&gt;Carbon footprint of medical procedures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health care services often involve all of the above mentioned sources of emissions: medical devices, pharmaceuticals, and disposable materials. When the emissions in hospitals and along the supply chain are combined, it becomes possible to calculate the environmental footprint of medical procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/cardiac-surgery_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Operating room in cardiac surgery, 2020. Source: iStock.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Operating room in cardiac surgery, 2020. Source: iStock. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, studies of cataract surgery and reflux control surgery in the UK estimated the carbon footprint to be 182 kg and 1 ton of emissions, respectively, which corresponds to between 1,517 km and 8,333 km of driving. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Renal dialysis, a treatment to replace kidney function, produces 1.8 to 7.2 tonnes of emissions per patient per year, equal to the emissions of 15,000 to 60,000 km of driving. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-limitations-of-carbon-and-energy-efficiency&#34;&gt;The limitations of carbon and energy efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although data on its environmental footprint is still incomplete, it seems quite clear that modern health care is not compatible with a transition to a low carbon society. The big question is whether or not this can be fixed without lowering the levels of care, pain relief, and longevity that people in high income societies have grown accustomed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many efforts and studies into health care sustainability aim to reduce energy use and emissions without affecting the quality of medical treatments, often explicitly so. For example, the authors of a 2020 study into the Austrian health care system write that it’s “crucial to understand how the health care sector can reduce its emissions without undermining its service quality”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Elsewhere, researchers write that “any solution that would reduce environmental impacts while reducing performance at the same time cannot be deployed”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence, many researchers tend to focus on improving carbon and energy efficiency. These strategies aim to deliver the same &amp;ldquo;performance&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;service quality&amp;rdquo; but with less energy (thanks to more energy efficient equipment), or with less emissions (owing to more renewable energy sources). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of medical treatments continues to improve, resulting in extra energy use that erases the carbon or energy savings that result from efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the quality of medical treatments &lt;em&gt;continues to improve&lt;/em&gt;, resulting in extra energy use that erases the savings that result from carbon and energy efficiency. For example, in 2012 researchers calculated that MRI-scanners could be made 10-20% more energy efficient with relatively simple changes in design and operation. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some of their proposed changes are now in use, but the energy use of MRI-scanners has not decreased, on the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/medical-scientist_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Medical Scientist working on brain tumor cure in a Research Center. Source: iStock.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Medical Scientist working on brain tumor cure in a Research Center. Source: iStock. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first reason is that MRI-scanners now come with higher field strengths (which offer diagnostic images of higher accuracy) and with larger boreholes (which improve patient comfort and allow obese or very muscular patients to be scanned). These innovations have improved the quality of care, but they have done so at the expense of extra energy use. In the 2012 study, the average power consumption per scan before the energy efficiency improvements was 15 kWh. A 2020 study measured an energy use of 17 kWh and 23.6 kWh per scan for an MRI-scanner with a field strength of 1.5 and 3 Tesla, respectively. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:33&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, MRI-scanners with better diagnostic capabilities also increase energy use in  unexpected ways, because medical equipment, pharmaceuticals, and treatments shape and change each other. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:34&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example, doctors used to diagnose a patient through physical examination and communication, and only used diagnostic services to confirm the diagnosis, if necessary. Now, diagnostic tests happen upfront and drive the decision process, resulting in more tests and higher energy use. The introduction of new pharmaceuticals can foster increasingly energy-intensive diagnostic practices, too. For example, certain cancer treatment drugs are now being designed to treat a very specific tumor subtype, which requires more and more accurate medical imaging to identify the tumor subtype. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:34&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:34&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding more renewable energy sources could potentially lower the emissions of health care both on-site and throughout the supply chain, but as the energy use of medical treatments continues to increase, this outcome is unlikely. Besides, a quick calculation shows that, even without further growth in energy use, a carbon neutral US health care system would gobble up the entire US renewable energy production – sun, wind, hydroelectric, wood, geothermal, biofuels, and waste. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:35&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:35&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;35&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The challenge is only slightly smaller in other high-income countries. Finally, renewable energy would not solve all of the health care sector’s environmental damage, and would not even eliminate all of its carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sufficient-health-care&#34;&gt;Sufficient health care?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reduce the environmental footprint of modern health care, we need to question the trend towards ever greater reliance on energy-intensive technologies and services. The same holds true in other domains of life. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while some people see the charm and real advantages of frugal and past ways of living when it comes to comfort or convenience, few would be tempted to apply the same principles to health and longevity. After all, the health care equivalent of travelling more slowly or wearing an extra sweater at home may be living a shorter life, suffering more pain, or being less mobile in old age. For example, if we would stop using MRI-scanners, or only use those with a field strength up to 1.5 Tesla, the lower diagnostic accuracy will lead to some cancers not being detected, resulting in lower cancer survival rates, and a lower average life expectancy. Or at least, so it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/barber-surgeon_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Barber-surgeon extracting a tooth, a painting by Adriaen van Ostade, 1630.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Barber-surgeon extracting a tooth, a painting by Adriaen van Ostade, 1630. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If health care is viewed in a historical context, it seems clear that there is a powerful connection between the use of energy-intensive medical technologies on the one hand, and the health and longevity of a population on the other hand. Even looking back less than a century shows much lower health outcomes and survival rates for all kinds of diseases, and today’s global average life expectancy (72.6 years) is higher than in any high-income country back in 1950.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hospitals date back to antiquity, but they merely welcomed those gone mad or awaiting death. In the middle ages, surgery happened at the barbershop, where “barber-surgeons” offered blood-letting, tooth extractions, and amputations alongside the more usual haircuts and shaves. They brew their own anesthetics based on herbs and alcohol, which could be just as deadly as the treatment itself. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:36&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:36&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;36&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A look at the “developing” world today also seems to suggest a clear connection between health care emissions, which are very modest, and life expectancy, which can be 20 to 30 years below that in high income countries. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:37&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:38&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:38&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;38&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:39&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:39&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;39&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:40&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:40&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:41&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:41&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;41&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if one digs deeper, the connection between energy use and longevity is not as strong as it seems. This is proven by the USA, which has the most expensive and unsustainable health care system in the world, but ranks behind most European countries on the &lt;em&gt;Health Care Access and Quality Index&lt;/em&gt; (which measures death rates from 32 causes of death that could be avoided by effective medical care). US citizens also have a lower life expectancy than European citizens. Clearly, there are other factors at play, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resistance-to-disease&#34;&gt;Resistance to disease&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, the quality of a health care system is not the only determinant of health and longevity. Here’s where history does have an important lesson to teach us. Medical knowledge dating back to antiquity viewed health in a more holistic way and placed great emphasis on building up the body’s inherent resistance to disease. For example, Hippocrates, often referred to as the father of Western medicine, prescribed diet, gymnastics, exercise, massage, hydrotherapy, and swimming in the sea. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:42&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:42&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;42&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could argue that our forebears had no other choice than to focus on preventing disease, because they had few treatments available. However, the wisdom of their approach is more obvious than ever. Nowadays in high income societies, many patients need medical treatment because of so-called lifestyle diseases – those caused by poor or excessive nutrition, lack of physical activity, stress, or substance abuse. Typical health risks are cardiovascular disease, diabetes type 2, depression, obesity, some types of cancers, and higher susceptibility to infectious diseases. Industrial society has given us effective medical treatments, but it&amp;rsquo;s also making us sick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that health and longevity can be promoted in other ways than through an increasingly resource-intensive health care system. By addressing the broader determinants of health and longevity, we could make a switch from curative to preventive medicine. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:43&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:43&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Preventive medicine is not about the government telling us not to smoke (and then cashing in tax money on the sales of cigarettes). Rather, it concerns systemic changes that go beyond behavioural change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/cars-health_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Rush hour in São Paulo, Brazil, 2005. Public domain.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Rush hour in São Paulo, Brazil, 2005. Public domain. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, significantly reducing the use of cars in our societies would bring a surprisingly large number of health benefits that would lower the need for energy-intensive medical treatments. It would decrease the health damage done through traffic accidents and through air and noise pollution. It would make people more physically active (preventing many lifestyle diseases), and it would free a lot of public space for people to come together, for kids to play, and for trees to grow (all important factors for the mental health of a population). Finally, reducing the use of cars may easily save more greenhouse gas emissions than the health care system produces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switching to a healthier food production system, addressing the environmental damage done by the plastic industry, reducing poverty and social inequality, introducing shorter work hours, and more meaningful jobs are other examples of preventive medicine. We have not achieved the higher life expectancy of today only because of better health care systems. We also got it because of better education, sanitation, safety and traffic regulations, welfare systems, crime control, and a more reliable food supply. The low average life expectancy in poor countries is also partly due to these factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preventive medicine would also reduce the health damage done by the medical treatments themselves. This concerns health damage resulting from medical errors or side effects of pharmaceuticals and more indirectly from the pollution that the health care sector generates. For example, air pollution from health care services contributes to the prevalence of asthma, which in turn increases the demand for health care. Climate change and other environmental damage threaten younger and future generations with even larger health impacts, for example through crop failures, spread of diseases, extreme weather events, and natural disasters. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:44&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-law-of-diminishing-returns&#34;&gt;The law of diminishing returns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, within a health care system, medical practices with higher energy use do not necessarily lead to increased health outcomes in a proportional way. Like so many other sectors in industrial society, curative health care is vulnerable to the law of diminishing returns: it takes ever more energy to gain ever smaller increases in health outcomes. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Conversely, this means that a relatively small decline in the quality or specifications of medical treatments could yield comparably large reductions in resource use and emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infection control is a good example. The development of general anesthesia in the 1840s made surgery possible, but at the time over 90% of surgical wounds became infected, often leading to death. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:45&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:45&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The first major decrease in infection rates followed antiseptic practices (1880-1900), and the second followed the introduction of antibiotics (1945-1970). By 1985, the overall infection rate had decreased to about 5%. Since then, a lot of resources have been invested to achieve incremental gains towards 100% sterility, mainly by replacing reusable supplies by single-use, disposable products. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/reuse-surgical-instruments_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Operating room nurse preparing instruments for surgery at the 3rd Station Hospital, Korea. 1951. Source: US National Library of Medicine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Operating room nurse preparing instruments for surgery at the 3rd Station Hospital, Korea. 1951. Source: US National Library of Medicine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If properly decontaminated, reusable supplies carry no increased infection risks, but cross-contamination between patients sometimes happens by mistake. Nevertheless, some scientists have advocated for a return to reusable products, which have a much lower environmental footprint in most cases. For example, the use of reusable laryngoscope handles produces 16-25 times less greenhouse gases than single-use, disposable ones. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:45&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:45&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The researchers admit that their approach may increase deaths from surgical infections. Still, they argue that the health damage caused by the production of single-use disposable supplies is even more considerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparisons of cataract surgery in the UK and in India have shown that the same treatment produces only 5% of the emissions and 6% of the solid waste in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to maximizing returns, less affluent societies can teach us some lessons. Comparisons of cataract surgery in the UK and in India have shown that the same treatment (phacoemulsification) in India&amp;rsquo;s Aravind Eye Clinics is much cheaper and produces only 5% of the emissions and 6% of the solid waste in the UK. This is mainly because the Indian surgeons reuse as many supplies, devices, and drugs on as many patients as possible. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:46&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:46&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:47&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:47&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;47&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:48&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:48&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;48&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:49&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:49&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;49&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In addition, they use locally manufactured supplies, implants, and drugs, and they apply a dual-bed system in which one patient is operated while another one is being positioned and prepared in the bed next to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although these practices flout regulations for infection control in high income countries, cataract surgery in India achieves similar or better outcomes and does not cause any more infections than it does in the UK or the US. Consequently, it may well be that the law of diminishing returns has reached its ultimate limit, in the sense that an expensive and unsustainable medical practice does not seem to bring any health benefits at all. The Indian eye clinics demonstrate that an effective model of care is possible without expensive and unsustainable supplies and resources. Medical innovation can happen without new technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;driven-by-profit&#34;&gt;Driven by profit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law of diminishing returns and the focus on curative medicine are both rooted in the fact that medical innovation is primarily driven by profit. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:50&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:50&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;50&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:51&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:51&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;51&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Private companies who develop and sell medical equipment, pharmaceuticals, and other health care products have nothing to win or earn if the demand for new curative health care technologies and products declines, or if medical technologies were to be judged in relation to their resource use. The medical industry &amp;ndash; logically &amp;ndash; wants to increase the sales of its products, and has enormous marketing budgets and lobbying power at its disposal to achieve that goal. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:52&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:52&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;52&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/02/how-sustainable-is-high-tech-health-care/images/dithers/healthcare-1910s_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;King George Military Hospital, electrical treatment and x-ray room. 1915. Source: US National Library of Medicine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 King George Military Hospital, electrical treatment and x-ray room. 1915. Source: US National Library of Medicine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WHO estimates that 20-40% of health care spending is wasted, and argues that “the cost-effectiveness, real need, and likely usefulness of many innovative technologies are questionable”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:44&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:37&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:37&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;37&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; An increasing body of academic literature shows the extent to which patients in high income countries are “overdosed, overtreated, and overdiagnosed”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:44&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is inevitable. A modern health care system could also work in another economic context. For example, some have suggested the open source development of medical equipment and pharmaceuticals, in which health care technology would become a commons. Shifting the tax burden from labour to resources could be another part of the solution. In high income countries, medical equipment, pharmaceuticals, and disposable products partly serve to reduce the expensive human labour force in health care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;age-and-sustainability&#34;&gt;Age and Sustainability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the fragmented data available, it seems likely that the resource use of modern health care systems could be reduced significantly, without bringing us back to the barber-surgeons of the middle ages. A health care system that is more focused on preventive medicine, and which operates outside the logic of the market, could reduce emissions without negatively impacting health, maybe even improving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As medical treatments become increasingly resource-intensive, the chances grow that the public health damage of a treatment outweighs the individual gain of a patient, especially at old age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, the law of diminishing returns highlights opportunities to lower the environmental footprint of health care services. For example, if the environmental footprint of health care was halved, it’s very unlikely that life expectancy would decrease proportionally. Nearly half of lifetime health care expenditures – and thus energy use and emissions – is incurred during the senior years (+65 years old). For those up to age 85, more than one-third of their lifetime expenditures will accrue in the remaining years. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:53&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:53&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;53&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocating for a shorter average life expectancy, even if it may concern a very modest decrease, sounds problematic. However, avoiding the topic is just as problematic. Because of modern health care’s enormous (and still growing) environmental footprint, today’s health and longevity comes at least partly at the expense of the health and longevity of younger and future generations, who have no voice in this debate. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:44&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;44&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we cure one person today, at the expense of making other people sick tomorrow, health care becomes counter-productive. Health is not only a private good but also a public one, and as medical treatments become increasingly resource-intensive, the chances grow that the public health damage of a treatment outweighs the individual gain of a patient, especially at old age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Elizabeth Shove&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pichler, Peter-Paul, et al. &amp;ldquo;International comparison of health care carbon footprints.&amp;rdquo; Environmental Research Letters 14.6 (2019): 064004. &lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/ab19e1/pdf&#34;&gt;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/ab19e1/pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;National estimates of health care sector greenhouse gas emissions have been performed for the UK (2009), the USA (2009 &amp;amp; 2016), Sweden (2017), Australia (2018), Canada (2018), China (2019), Japan (2020) and Austria (2020). For an overview, see [15]. However, because each study has its own methodology, the results are not perfectly comparable. That’s why I quote this source, as it gives comparable estimates.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eckelman, Matthew J., and Jodi Sherman. &amp;ldquo;Environmental impacts of the US health care system and effects on public health.&amp;rdquo; PloS one 11.6 (2016): e0157014. &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0157014&#34;&gt;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0157014&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US National Health Expenditure Data. Centers for Medicare &amp;amp; Medicaid Services. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/NationalHealthExpendData/NationalHealthAccountsHistorical&#34;&gt;https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/NationalHealthExpendData/NationalHealthAccountsHistorical&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tainter, Joseph. The collapse of complex societies. Cambridge university press, 1988. Page 102 &amp;amp; 103.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current healthcare expenditure, 2012-2017, Eurostat. Current health expenditure per capita (current US$) - European Union, World Bank. Current health expenditure per capita, PPP (current international $) - European Union, World Bank. Health spending, OECD.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In what follows, I ignore the resource use and emissions caused by transportation to and from health care facilities, as well as the resource use and emissions caused by the building of the health care facilities themselves.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research in different countries has shown an electricity use of 130 to 280 kilowatt-hour per square metre per year, representing around 50% of total on-site building energy consumption. [11-12] For comparison, residential electricity use in European households is on average 70 kWh/m2/year, and total energy demand is dominated by heating, not electricity. According to a 2016 study, for which scientists collected power data over a period of 18 months in a German hospital, operating rooms have the highest electricity use (438 kWh/m2/year), followed by intensive care units (135 kWh/m2/yr). [9]&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christiansen, Nils, Martin Kaltschmitt, and Frank Dzukowski. &amp;ldquo;Electrical energy consumption and utilization time analysis of hospital departments and large scale medical equipment.&amp;rdquo; Energy and Buildings 131 (2016): 172-183.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wu, Rui. &amp;ldquo;The carbon footprint of the Chinese health-care system: an environmentally extended input–output and structural path analysis study.&amp;rdquo; The Lancet Planetary Health 3.10 (2019): e413-e419. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2542519619301925&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2542519619301925&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bawaneh, Khaled, et al. &amp;ldquo;Energy consumption analysis and characterization of healthcare facilities in the United States.&amp;rdquo; Energies 12.19 (2019): 3775. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/19/3775/pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/19/3775/pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rohde, Tarald, and Robert Martinez. &amp;ldquo;Equipment and energy usage in a large teaching hospital in Norway.&amp;rdquo; Journal of healthcare engineering 6 (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.hindawi.com/journals/jhe/2015/231507.pdf&#34;&gt;http://downloads.hindawi.com/journals/jhe/2015/231507.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black, Douglas R., et al. &amp;ldquo;Evaluation of miscellaneous and electronic device energy use in hospitals.&amp;rdquo; World Review of Science, Technology and Sustainable Development 10.1-2-3 (2013): 113-128. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1172701&#34;&gt;https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1172701&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picano, Eugenio. &amp;ldquo;Environmental sustainability of medical imaging.&amp;rdquo; Acta Cardiologica (2020): 1-5. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00015385.2020.1815985&#34;&gt;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00015385.2020.1815985&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherman, Jodi D., et al. &amp;ldquo;The Green Print: Advancement of Environmental Sustainability in Healthcare.&amp;rdquo; Resources, Conservation and Recycling 161 (2020): 104882. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Brett_Duane/publication/343137350_The_Green_Print_Advancement_of_Environmental_Sustainability_in_Healthcare/links/5f216962299bf134048f8960/The-Green-Print-Advancement-of-Environmental-Sustainability-in-Healthcare.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Brett_Duane/publication/343137350_The_Green_Print_Advancement_of_Environmental_Sustainability_in_Healthcare/links/5f216962299bf134048f8960/The-Green-Print-Advancement-of-Environmental-Sustainability-in-Healthcare.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin, Marisa, et al. &amp;ldquo;Environmental impacts of abdominal imaging: a pilot investigation.&amp;rdquo; Journal of the American College of Radiology 15.10 (2018): 1385-1393. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1546144018308639&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1546144018308639&lt;/a&gt;. The researchers write that “when production and use phases are combined, the total energy consumption of MRI (&amp;gt;309 MJ/examination, abdominal scan, 1.5 Tesla) is comparable with cooling a three-bedroom house with central air-conditioning for a day”.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weisz, Ulli, et al. &amp;ldquo;Carbon emission trends and sustainability options in Austrian health care.&amp;rdquo; Resources, Conservation and Recycling 160 (2020): 104862.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Belkhir, Lotfi, and Ahmed Elmeligi. &amp;ldquo;Carbon footprint of the global pharmaceutical industry and relative impact of its major players.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Cleaner Production 214 (2019): 185-194. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0959652618336084&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0959652618336084&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laufman, Harold, Luther Riley, and Barry Badner. &amp;ldquo;Use of disposable products in surgical practice.&amp;rdquo; Archives of Surgery 111.1 (1976): 20-26. &lt;a href=&#34;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/article-abstract/581229&#34;&gt;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamasurgery/article-abstract/581229&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gilden, Daniel J., K. N. Scissors, and J. B. Reuler. &amp;ldquo;Disposable products in the hospital waste stream.&amp;rdquo; Western journal of medicine 156.3 (1992): 269. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1003232/pdf/westjmed00091-0045.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1003232/pdf/westjmed00091-0045.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherman, Jodi D., and Harriet W. Hopf. &amp;ldquo;Balancing infection control and environmental protection as a matter of patient safety: the case of laryngoscope handles.&amp;rdquo; Anesthesia &amp;amp; Analgesia 127.2 (2018): 576-579. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jodi_Sherman/publication/322407715_Balancing_Infection_Control_and_Environmental_Protection_as_a_Matter_of_Patient_Safety_The_Case_of_Laryngoscope_Handles/links/5a82ba12a6fdcc6f3eadcfab/Balancing-Infection-Control-and-Environmental-Protection-as-a-Matter-of-Patient-Safety-The-Case-of-Laryngoscope-Handles.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jodi_Sherman/publication/322407715_Balancing_Infection_Control_and_Environmental_Protection_as_a_Matter_of_Patient_Safety_The_Case_of_Laryngoscope_Handles/links/5a82ba12a6fdcc6f3eadcfab/Balancing-Infection-Control-and-Environmental-Protection-as-a-Matter-of-Patient-Safety-The-Case-of-Laryngoscope-Handles.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thiel, Cassandra Lee, et al. &amp;ldquo;Life cycle assessment of medical procedures: Vaginal and cesarean section births.&amp;rdquo; 2012 IEEE International Symposium on Sustainable Systems and Technology (ISSST). IEEE, 2012.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Campion, Nicole, et al. &amp;ldquo;Sustainable healthcare and environmental life-cycle impacts of disposable supplies: a focus on disposable custom packs.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Cleaner Production 94 (2015): 46-55.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reusables, Disposables each play a role in preventing cross-contamination”, Elizabeth Srejic, Infection Control Today, April 2016&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainability roadmap for hospitals, American Association of Hospitals. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sustainabilityroadmap.org/topics/waste.shtml#.YCsEOXyYXWc&#34;&gt;http://www.sustainabilityroadmap.org/topics/waste.shtml#.YCsEOXyYXWc&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thiel, Cassandra L., et al. &amp;ldquo;Cataract surgery and environmental sustainability: waste and lifecycle assessment of phacoemulsification at a private healthcare facility.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Cataract &amp;amp; Refractive Surgery 43.11 (2017): 1391-1398. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5728421/&#34;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5728421/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vollmer, Martin K., et al. &amp;ldquo;Modern inhalation anesthetics: potent greenhouse gases in the global atmosphere.&amp;rdquo; Geophysical Research Letters 42.5 (2015): 1606-1611. &lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/2014GL062785&#34;&gt;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/2014GL062785&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salas, Renee N., et al. &amp;ldquo;A pathway to net zero emissions for healthcare.&amp;rdquo; bmj 371 (2020).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brown, Lawrence H., et al. &amp;ldquo;Estimating the life cycle greenhouse gas emissions of Australian ambulance services.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Cleaner Production 37 (2012): 135-141.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connor, A., R. Lillywhite, and M. W. Cooke. &amp;ldquo;The carbon footprint of a renal service in the United Kingdom.&amp;rdquo; QJM: An International Journal of Medicine 103.12 (2010): 965-975. &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/qjmed/article/103/12/965/1584174&#34;&gt;https://academic.oup.com/qjmed/article/103/12/965/1584174&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herrmann, C., and A. Rock. &amp;ldquo;Magnetic resonance equipment (MRI)–Study on the potential for environmental improvement by the aspect of energy efficiency.&amp;rdquo; PE INTERNATIONAL AG, Report (2012).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shove, Elizabeth. &amp;ldquo;What is wrong with energy efficiency?.&amp;rdquo; Building Research &amp;amp; Information 46.7 (2018): 779-789. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/09613218.2017.1361746&#34;&gt;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/09613218.2017.1361746&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heye, Tobias, et al. &amp;ldquo;The energy consumption of radiology: energy-and cost-saving opportunities for CT and MRI operation.&amp;rdquo; Radiology 295.3 (2020): 593-605. &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32208096/&#34;&gt;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32208096/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:34&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue, Stanley. &amp;ldquo;Reducing demand for energy in hospitals: opportunities for and limits to temporal coordination.&amp;rdquo; Demanding Energy. Palgrave Macmillan, Cham, 2018. 313-337.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:34&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:34&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:35&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eia.gov/tools/faqs/faq.php?id=92&amp;amp;t=4&#34;&gt;https://www.eia.gov/tools/faqs/faq.php?id=92&amp;amp;t=4&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:35&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:36&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duffin, Jacalyn. History of medicine: a scandalously short introduction. University of Toronto Press, 2010.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:36&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:37&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHO compendium of innovative health technologies for low-resource settings, WHO; 2016-17. WHO, 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.who.int/medical_devices/publications/compendium_2016_2017/en/&#34;&gt;https://www.who.int/medical_devices/publications/compendium_2016_2017/en/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:37&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:37&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:38&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medical devices: managing the mismatch: an outcome of the priority medical devices project: methodology briefing paper, WHO, 2010. &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/70491&#34;&gt;https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/70491&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:38&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:39&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global Atlas of Medical Devices, WHO, 2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.who.int/medical_devices/publications/global_atlas_meddev2017/en/&#34;&gt;https://www.who.int/medical_devices/publications/global_atlas_meddev2017/en/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:39&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:40&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Page, Brandi R., et al. &amp;ldquo;Cobalt, linac, or other: what is the best solution for radiation therapy in developing countries?.&amp;rdquo; International Journal of Radiation Oncology* Biology* Physics89.3 (2014): 476-480.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:40&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:41&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a survey of surgeons across 30 African nations, 48% reported at least weekly power failures, 29% had operated using only mobile phone lights, and 19% had experienced poor surgical outcomes as a result of it. [28]&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:41&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:42&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parker, Steve. Medicine: The Definitive Illustrated History. DK Publishing, 2016.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:42&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:43&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hall, Peter A., and Michèle Lamont, eds. Successful societies: How institutions and culture affect health. Cambridge University Press, 2009.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:43&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:44&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Borowy, Iris, and Jean-Louis Aillon. &amp;ldquo;Sustainable health and degrowth: Health, health care and society beyond the growth paradigm.&amp;rdquo; Social Theory &amp;amp; Health 15.3 (2017): 346-368.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:44&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:45&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherman, Jodi D., and Harriet W. Hopf. &amp;ldquo;Balancing infection control and environmental protection as a matter of patient safety: the case of laryngoscope handles.&amp;rdquo; Anesthesia &amp;amp; Analgesia 127.2 (2018): 576-579.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:45&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:45&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:46&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steyn, A., et al. &amp;ldquo;Frugal innovation for global surgery: leveraging lessons from low-and middle-income countries to optimise resource use and promote value-based care.&amp;rdquo; The Bulletin of the Royal College of Surgeons of England 102.5 (2020): 198-200. &lt;a href=&#34;https://publishing.rcseng.ac.uk/doi/pdf/10.1308/rcsbull.2020.150&#34;&gt;https://publishing.rcseng.ac.uk/doi/pdf/10.1308/rcsbull.2020.150&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:46&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:47&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haripriya, Aravind, David F. Chang, and Ravilla D. Ravindran. &amp;ldquo;Endophthalmitis reduction with intracameral moxifloxacin in eyes with and without surgical complications: Results from 2 million consecutive cataract surgeries.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Cataract &amp;amp; Refractive Surgery 45.9 (2019): 1226-1233. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aurolab.com/images/JCRS%202%20million.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.aurolab.com/images/JCRS%202%20million.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:47&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:48&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venkatesh, Rengaraj, et al. &amp;ldquo;Carbon footprint and cost–effectiveness of cataract surgery.&amp;rdquo; Current opinion in ophthalmology 27.1 (2016): 82-88.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:48&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:49&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thiel, Cassandra L., et al. &amp;ldquo;Utilizing off-the-shelf LCA methods to develop a ‘triple bottom line’auditing tool for global cataract surgical services.&amp;rdquo; Resources, Conservation and Recycling 158 (2020): 104805.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:49&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:50&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relman, Arnold S. &amp;ldquo;The new medical-industrial complex.&amp;rdquo; New England Journal of Medicine 303.17 (1980): 963-970. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJM198010233031703&#34;&gt;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJM198010233031703&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:50&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:51&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, Richard. &amp;ldquo;Limits to medicine. Medical nemesis: the expropriation of health.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Epidemiology &amp;amp; Community Health 57.12 (2003): 928-928. &lt;a href=&#34;https://jech.bmj.com/content/57/12/928&#34;&gt;https://jech.bmj.com/content/57/12/928&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:51&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:52&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In health care, there is a thin line between marketing and corruption, especially when the target audience is medical personnel that may gain benefits from using or prescribing a medical device or drug, or when regulators are influenced to facilitate practices that increase profits. Transparancy International ranks the procurement of drugs and medical equipment fourth on a list of seven processes that carry high risk of corruption, and calls the problem &amp;ldquo;widespread in all countries&amp;rdquo;. [37]&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:52&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:53&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alemayehu, Berhanu, and Kenneth E. Warner. &amp;ldquo;The lifetime distribution of health care costs.&amp;rdquo; Health services research 39.3 (2004): 627-642. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1361028/&#34;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1361028/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:53&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Electric Hearing Aids Outperform Modern Devices</title>
      <link>/2017/08/non-electric-hearing-aids-outperform-modern-devices/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2017/08/non-electric-hearing-aids-outperform-modern-devices/images/dithers/oortrompet-2_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="61089" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/non-electric-hearing-aids-outperform-modern-devices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2017/08/non-electric-hearing-aids-outperform-modern-devices/images/dithers/oortrompet-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Example of an ear trumpet. Source: Bernard Becker Medical Library Image Gallery (archived)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Example of an ear trumpet. Source: [Bernard Becker Medical Library Image Gallery (archived)](https://web.archive.org/web/20121206034532/http://beckerimages.wustl.edu/cdm/search/collection/p15793coll3/searchterm/VC703!CID/field/all!all/mode/all!all/conn/or!and/order/identi) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;digital-hearing-aids&#34;&gt;Digital Hearing Aids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly 40% of people between the ages of 55 to 74 suffer hearing loss. Eighty percent of them do not wear a hearing aid, even though their disability often has a negative impact on their quality of life as well as others around them. According to a 2013 research paper, the main reason is the limited performance of the devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, these results are in line with those of studies performed at the end of the twentieth century, meaning that the introduction of digital hearing aids has had no positive effect on the popularity of the technology. Electric hearing aids consist of a battery, a microphone, an amplifier and a speaker. The more compact electronic hearing aids also contain a microchip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An additional obstacle in low income countries is the cost of the technology, which concerns the device as well as the batteries, which need to be replaced regularly. Worldwide, roughly 1 billion people suffer from hearing loss. According to the World Health Organisation, only one fifth of them wears a hearing aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ear-trumpets--speaking-tubes&#34;&gt;Ear Trumpets &amp;amp; Speaking Tubes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the seventeenth century onwards, several types of non-electric hearing aids were developed, based on different acoustical principles. The most important devices were ear trumpets and speaking tubes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2017/08/non-electric-hearing-aids-outperform-modern-devices/images/dithers/oortrompet-3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Example of an ear trumpet. Source: Bernard Becker Medical Library Image Gallery (archived)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Example of an ear trumpet. Source: [Bernard Becker Medical Library Image Gallery (archived)](https://web.archive.org/web/20121206034532/http://beckerimages.wustl.edu/cdm/search/collection/p15793coll3/searchterm/VC703!CID/field/all!all/mode/all!all/conn/or!and/order/identi) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the ear trumpet, sound from a funnel-shaped metal tube was conducted to a small opening that was inserted in the listener’s ear. Ear trumpets were often slighty curved at one end so that they could be aimed at the sound source more easily. Some models were collapsible for easy carrying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaking tube consisted of a flexible tube with a funnel-shaped opening on one end through which the speaker could talk, while the other end of the tube was put in the ear of the listener.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stationary-hearing-aids&#34;&gt;Stationary Hearing Aids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking tubes and ear trumpets were also combined, especially in stationary hearing aids such as the acoustical chair. This seating had a pair of large trumpets on each side, which amplified the sound and led it through flexible tubes to the listener’s ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar technology could also be hidden in objects like vases. This was meant for several speakers and listeners gathering around a table. In the days before the telephone, speaking tubes were also used by people with normal hearing to communicate between floors of a building or a ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-amplification&#34;&gt;Sound Amplification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements from the late twentieth century show that these devices perform better than today’s high-tech hearing aids. Ear trumpets and speaking tubes not only yielded a sound amplification of 10 to 25 decibels, they also suppressed sounds that came from other directions, further improving their workings. The speaking tube also reduced the noise between speaker and listener.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2017/08/non-electric-hearing-aids-outperform-modern-devices/images/dithers/slanghoorn_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A speaking tube&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A speaking tube 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important advantage was that both devices were very visible and thus encouraged the speaker to talk slower and more clearly. However, this visibility was also considered to be a problem: well-functioning, non-electric hearing aids are laughable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the nineteenth century onwards, the development of hearing aids took another direction: much smaller ear trumpets and speaking tubes were now hidden in clothing and accessories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vanity&#34;&gt;Vanity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most popular models were worn as a kind of headband, with small trumpets hidden behind the ears, in hats, wigs, beards or scarfs. An extra advantage was that these devices could be operated hands free. Unfortunately, these hearing aids had poor performance compared to earlier models, and sometimes even impaired hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a new trend was set. Since the nineteenth century, the main criterium for a hearing aid is no longer its effectivity but its discretion and compactness. Nevertheless, those who can overcome their vanity can revert to technology that has proven to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large collection of images showing non-electric hearing aids can be found at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20121206034532/http://beckerimages.wustl.edu/cdm/search/collection/p15793coll3/searchterm/VC703!CID/field/all!all/mode/all!all/conn/or!and/order/identi&#34;&gt;Bernard Becker Medical Library Image Gallery (archived)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/6372770/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Non-electric aids to hearing: a short history&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, S.D.G. Stephens &amp;amp; J.C. Goodwin, in &lt;em&gt;Audiology&lt;/em&gt; 23: 215-240, 1984. A full version of the paper can be found online, but for some reason it’s impossible to link to it directly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://beckerexhibits.wustl.edu/did/19thcent/index.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Conceiled hearing aids of the 19th century&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Deafness in Disguise&lt;/em&gt;, Washington University School of Medicine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.3109/14992027.2013.769066&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why do people with hearing aids do not wear them?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; Abby McCormack &amp;amp; Heather Fortnum, &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Audiology&lt;/em&gt;, Volume 52, issue 5, 2013&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recycling Animal and Human Dung is the Key to Sustainable Farming</title>
      <link>/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/recycling-humanure-1_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="36369" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/recycling-humanure-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;© Illustrations in red &amp;amp;amp; black: Diego Marmolejo for low-tech magazine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 © Illustrations in red &amp; black: [Diego Marmolejo](http://ddidak.blogspot.com/) for low-tech magazine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flushing the water closet is handy, but it wreaks ecological havoc, deprives agricultural soils of essential nutrients and makes food production dependent on fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 4,000 years, human excrements and urine were considered extremely valuable trade products in China, Korea and Japan. Human dung was transported over specially designed canal networks by boats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the application of human &amp;ldquo;waste&amp;rdquo; products as fertilizers to agricultural fields, the East managed to feed a large population without polluting their drinking water. Meanwhile, cities in medieval Europe turned into open sewers. The concept was modernized in late 19th century Holland, with Charles Liernur&amp;rsquo;s sophisticated vacuum sewer system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;broken-cycle&#34;&gt;Broken Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The innocent looking water closet breaks up a natural cycle in our food supply. Basically, it turns extremely valuable resources into waste products. When we grow crops, we withdraw essential nutrients from the soil: potassium, nitrogen and phosphate, to name but the most important. During the greater part of human history, we recycled these nutrients through our bodies and returned them to the soil, via excreta, food trimmings and the burial of dead. Today, we flush them mostly into the sea (see the infographic below),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/nutrients-cycle-humanure_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The nutrient cycle. Source: Humanure Handbook&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The nutrient cycle. Source: [Humanure Handbook](http://humanurehandbook.com/contents.html) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is problematic and unsustainable, for three main reasons. To start, dumping sewage in rivers, lakes and seas kills fish and makes fresh water undrinkable. This can only be avoided by extending the water closet and the already very costly sewerage network with an equally expensive infrastructure of sewage stations (which does not completely eliminate the detrimental effect on water life).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we need artificial fertilizers to keep our soil fertile. In 2008, almost 160 million tonnes of inorganic fertilizers were used worldwide (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www3.omu.edu.tr/anajas/pdf/21%282%29/243-248.pdf&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.fao.org/agl/agll/docs/cwfto13.pdf&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;). Without these, our agricultural soils would lose their fertility in just a few years time, followed by an inevitable collapse of food production and human population. A third problem is that the water closet logically consumes large quantities of fresh water to flush everything &amp;ldquo;away&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;water-closets-are-energy-intensive&#34;&gt;Water closets are energy-intensive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fresh water production, the construction and maintenance of sewers, the treatment of sewage (and sewage sludge), and the production of inorganic fertilizers are all energy-intensive processes. Nitrogen (which makes up more than half of total fertilizer consumption) is abundantly available in air, but to convert it to a useful form the gas has to be heated and pressurized. The energy for this (polluting) process is delivered by natural gas or (in China) by coal plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Potassium and phosphate have to be mined (up to depths of several thousands of feet) and transported. It takes more than 150 million tonnes of phosphate rock to produce our current yearly supply of 37
million tonnes of phosphate fertilizer, and 45 million tonnes of potash ore to produce 25 million tonnes of potassium fertilizer. Both operations are energy intensive and pollute the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/medieval-closet_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A medieval closet in a castle.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
  A medieval closet in a castle. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, while potassium is widely distributed and abundantly available (we have enough economically obtainable reserves to last 700 years at our current consumption rate), phosphorus is not. Ninety percent of global phosphate reserves are only found in a handful of countries, and economically recoverable reserves large enough to meet agricultural demand are estimated to last for only 30 to 100 years. Reserves are much larger if mining phosphates from the seabed is included, but this would be extremely energy-intensive, further deterioriating the sustainability of the food and sanitation system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to get nutrients from sea to land is via marine bird droppings - which is of course in very short supply - or by eating fish or seafood. However, once we have digested our fish and chips, the nutrients filter down to the sea via the sewer network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-sign-of-civilization&#34;&gt;A sign of civilization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of the water closet and the accompanying sewer system is seldom questioned. It is viewed as an obvious technology and generally regarded as a sign of civilization - countries that do not have such a system today are considered retarded or backward. The reason for this is because we have been conditioned to believe that the water closet and the sewer system are the only alternatives to stench and disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been conditioned to believe that the water closet and the sewer system are the only alternatives to stench and disease&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the demise of the Roman Empire (with its early sewers and water closets) and right up to the end of the nineteenth century, the concentrated and unorganised distribution of human excrements in groundwater, city canals and rivers brought recurrent deadly epidemics of cholera and typhoid fever throughout the western world. These were caused by drinking water contaminated with faeces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People answered nature&amp;rsquo;s call on the streets or emptied their honey buckets in backyards, open courtyards, badly sealed cesspools or surface waters -
methods that were not conducive to healthy living in densely populated cities. Water closet and sewer system have solved this, at least in the rich world, and nobody wants to go back to the miserable hygienic conditions of those times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;chinese-agriculture&#34;&gt;Chinese agriculture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as obvious as it seems to us today, the water closet is not the only possible answer to the problem of sanitation. There are other, much more sustainable methods to separate human waste from drink water supplies. To start with, the grim sanitary conditions of the Middle Ages and the early Industrial Revolution were a purely western phenomenon. At the turn of the twentieth century in the East, the water in Chinese rivers was safe to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese were as numerous as the Americans and Europeans at the time, and they had large, densely populated cities, too. The difference was that they maintained an agricultural system that was based on human &amp;ldquo;waste&amp;rdquo; as a fertilizer. Stools and urine were collected with care and discipline, and transported over sometimes considerable distances. They were mixed with other organic waste, composted and then spread across the fields (illustration below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/humanure-recycling-china_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: In China, stools and urine were mixed with other organic waste, composted and then spread across the fields.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: In China, stools and urine were mixed with other organic waste, composted and then spread across the fields. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s killing two birds with one stone: no pollution of drinking water, and an agricultural system that could have lasted forever. In fact, it did last 4,000 years, which is considerably longer than even our most abundant resource - potassium, with 700 years of reserves - will allow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese agricultural system, which was also applied in Korea and Japan, is extensively described in &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archive.org/details/cu31924073872685&#34;&gt;Farmers of Forty Centuries&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, a report of a study trip by the American soil scientist F.H. King. The book was published in 1911, around the time of the discovery of the Haber-Bosch process that would lead to the breakthrough of cheap artificial nitrogen fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;King devoted an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archive.org/stream/cu31924073872685#page/n214/mode/1up&#34;&gt;entire chapter&lt;/a&gt; to the collection and use of human fertilizer by the Asians. Joseph Needham also gives an account of the method, in volume VI:2 of &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nri.org.uk/science.html&#34;&gt;Science and civilization in China&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, citing various earlier sources. More recently, Duncan Brown talks about the Chinese system in his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/905727048X?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=905727048X&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Feed or Feedback: Agriculture, Population Dynamics and the State of the Planet&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dung-traders&#34;&gt;Dung traders&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When King visited China, the population was estimated at about 400
million adult inhabitants, compared to some 400 million inhabitants in Europe and 100 million inhabitants in the US. The stools and urine of those 400 million people were collected in terracotta jars, with air-tight seals. The matter was gathered from every home, from the tiny country villages to the great cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cities, special canal networks and boats were constructed for this purpose (picture below). This was the case in Hankow-Wuchang-Hanyang, for example, a city with almost 1.8 million inhabitants living in an area of only 6.5 square kilometres. You could thus argue that the Chinese &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; have a water carriage sewer network, though the difference to ours is stark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/boats-loaded-with-dung_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Boats transporting Dung&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Boats transporting Dung 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the time of King&amp;rsquo;s visit, every year in China more than 182,000,000 tonnes of human manure was collected in cities and villages &amp;ndash; 450 kilogram (900 pounds) per person per year. This was good for a total of 1,160,000 tonnes of nitrogen, 376,000 tonnes of potassium and 150,000 tonnes of phosphate which was returned to the soil. In 1908
Japan, 23,850,295 tonnes of &amp;ldquo;humanure&amp;rdquo; was collected and given back to the soil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shanghai traded and distributed the yield of its inhabitants over a specially designed canal network using hundreds of boats (see map below), a trade that brought in 100,000s of dollars every year. Human manure was considered a valuable commodity. In 1908, a Chinese business man paid the city 31,000 dollar (this would be more than 700,000 dollars today) to obtain the right to remove 78,000 tonnes of humanure per year from a region of the city to sell it to the farmers on the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/shanghai-canal-dung-transport_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Canal network for dung transportation in Shanghai.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Canal network for dung transportation in Shanghai. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Japan, which was much more urbanized than China, people paid less rent when they left their landlord better quality excrements. King describes loads of human dung taken from Tokyo and Yokahama &amp;ldquo;carried on the shoulders of men and on the backs of animals, but most commonly on strong carts drawn by men, bearing six to ten tightly covered wooden containers holding forty, sixty or more pounds each&amp;rdquo;. On the Japanese countryside, it was not unusual to see signs that invited passers-by to please answer nature&amp;rsquo;s call on site. The farmers used the product to manure their fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of recycling human dung in Asian countries repelled some foreign visitors. The Portuguese explorer Fernam Mendez Pinto &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archive.org/details/cu31924011271826&#34;&gt;wrote in 1583&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You must know that in this country there are many of such as make a trade of buying and selling mens Excrements, which is not so mean a commerce among them, but that there are many of them grow rich by it, and are held in good account. They which make a trade of buying it go up and down the streets with certain Clappers, like our Spittle men, whereby they give to understand what they desire without publishing of it otherwise to people, in regard the thing is filthy of itself;
whereunto I will adde thus much, that this commodity is so much esteemed among them, and so great a trade driven of it, that into one sea port, sometimes there comes in one tyde two or three hundred Sayls laden with it.&amp;rdquo; (sic)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 4,000 year old closed-loop system vanished with the arrival of artificial fertilizers, which were imported from the West during the first decades of the twentieth century. Today, China is the largest consumer of inorganic fertilizers with 28 percent of total world consumption. Asia as a whole now uses more than half of the world&amp;rsquo;s
artificial fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-soil-collection-in-europe&#34;&gt;Night soil collection in Europe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collection of human &amp;ldquo;waste&amp;rdquo; also occured in Europe, be it for a much shorter time and on a much smaller scale. The second half of the nineteenth century marked the end of a predominantly agricultural period in Europe; migration to the cities accelerated and the problem of sewage disposal got much worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/night-soil-collection-europe_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Collecting night soil in Amsterdam. Source.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Collecting night soil in Amsterdam. [Source](http://www.bronnenuitamsterdam.nl/weergave.asp?ID=6). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, health experts started to realize that cholera and typhoid fever were the consequences of drinking contaminated water. Since agriculture was increasingly short of animal manure, it appeared that both problems could be solved at the same time. The first system, which was set up in several countries and cities, is generally known as &amp;ldquo;night soil&amp;rdquo; collection and reminds of the Asian method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dung and urine were accumulated in movable wooden receptacles beneath the privy seat and mixed with earth, ashes or charcoal to prevent offensive odours. Night soil collectors came by at more or less regular intervals (mostly at night, hence the name) to pick up the merchandise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/night-soil-collection-netherlands_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Night soil collection in the Netherlands. Source.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Night soil collection in the Netherlands. [Source](http://www.jenneken.nl/bekijk/1900afvoervanmestenhuisvuil.htm). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This happened either by emptying the full tubs into a cart and giving them back immediately (which meant the cleansing had to be done by the users), or by placing the full tubs in a wagon, switching them for fresh ones (which meant the cleansing had to be done by the scavengers). The empty tubs were replaced under the privy seat, and the cargo was transported via horse and cart to a collection point outside the city. There it was converted into compost for use in agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the collection and transport of the waste was not as reliable, efficient and sanitary as was the case in China, Korea or Japan. All was good when air-tight containers were used, but this was not always done. When open carts were applied, the transport caused waste and foul smell (see the 19th century cartoon below, Sewage was spilled while carrying the tubs down the stairs and while emptying them into the carts. Moreover, the collection did not always happen that frequently, especially in poorer neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/stinky-night-soil_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Cartoon of a night soil cart. Source&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Cartoon of a night soil cart. [Source](http://www.bronnenuitamsterdam.nl/weergave.asp?ID=17) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the wooden tub system was an improvement over the comparitive disorder of nightsoil collection in Europe. Throughout the Middle Ages, so-called dung farmers gathered human and animal excrements from streets, backyards and cesspools and sold these to farmers who applied them to their fields. The problem was that these scavengers needed to collect enough dung before they could sell a cartload. Duncan Brown cites Cipolla, who describes the situation concisely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The most pathetically tragic aspect of this business was that of the people, whose poverty was so abject that they collected the manure they found in the streets where they kept it [at their homes] until they had accumulated a sufficient quantity to sell.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were exceptions, notably in Flanders, where an organized nightsoil collecting system that reminds of the Chinese method was set up as early as the Middle Ages. Around the town of Antwerp, the management of organic wastes (human excrements, dung of city horses, pigeon dung, canal mud and food scraps) had become a significant industry by the 16th century. By the 18th century there were great stores along the river the Schelde where the excrements from Dutch towns were transported by barge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-vacuum-sewers-of-charles-liernur&#34;&gt;The vacuum sewers of Charles Liernur&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second collection method was pioneered by Dutch engineer Charles Liernur in 1866
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sewerhistory.org/images/aus/aus4/1892_482439.pdf&#34;&gt;patent&lt;/a&gt; -
pdf). His vacuum sewer system combined the comfort of today&amp;rsquo;s water carriage sewer network with the ecological and manurial advantages of the earlier scavenging methods. A closet inside every home was connected to an underground small diameter pipeline infrastructure, and the stools and urine immediately left the house following deposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Liernur system combined the comfort of today&amp;rsquo;s water carriage sewer network with the ecological and manurial advantages of the earlier scavenging methods&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crucial difference with today&amp;rsquo;s technology, however, was that the Liernur system did not use water but atmospheric pressure as a transport medium. This meant that it avoided the dilution of the manure by the admixture of water, thus preserving its value as a fertilizer - which was Liernur&amp;rsquo;s explicit intention. On the other hand, the vacuum sewer system did away with the need for scavengers to visit every house, lugging around buckets of poo and pee, and disturbing everyone&amp;rsquo;s sleep. It was a clear improvement on the night soil systems, including the one used in Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dutch cities were equipped with the Liernur system: Leiden in 1871,
Amsterdam in 1872 and Dordrecht in 1874. Initially, only a couple of thousand homes were connected to the vacuum sewer network, but in Amsterdam the system was expanded substantially. At the end of the nineteenth century, about 90,000 Amsterdam inhabitants were linked to the Liernur sewer network, some 20 percent of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/liernur-system-sewage-removal_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Liernur system for sewage removal.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Liernur system for sewage removal. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Amsterdam and Leiden, the system remained in operation for almost 40
years. The Liernur system was also introduced on a smaller scale in Prague (Czech republic), Trouville sur Mer (France), Hanau (Germany) and Stansed (England). The system in Trouville, installed in 1892, was operated until 1987
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eauquebec.com/eau/eaux-usees/volume3.pdf&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;, pdf). Today, the method is still being used in ships, trains and airplanes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French designed their own version of the Liernur system - the Berlier system. It was introduced in 1880 for a trial period in Lyon, where it successfully removed sewage over a distance of four kilometres (2.5 miles). In 1881, a five kilometre network was introduced for trial in a Paris neighbourhood. The French took the trials very seriously: the sewage was observed by placing glass pipes at various points. The Berlier system, which was technically superior to the Liernur system, worked flawlessly: the thousand soldiers in the barracks of Pépinière, where it was in operation, were the only troops in Paris that were not affected by a serious typhoid epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-arrival-of-the-water-closet&#34;&gt;The arrival of the water closet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the technical success, the Berlier system never ascended beyond the experimental stage. The Dutch Health Advisory Board advised a general, national introduction of the Liernur system in 1873, following the successful operation in Amsterdam, but this did not happen either. Liernur designed plans for other cities in Europe (Paris, Berlin, Stockholm, Munchen, Stuttgart and Zurich) and in the US (Baltimore), but these were never realised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were several reasons why the pneumatic systems did not became the standard sewerage systems of today. Firstly, there was the arrival of the water closet and the waterworks. In the Netherlands, a growing number of people connected a water closet to the Liernur system, diluting the stools and urine in such a matter that their agricultural value declined considerably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before this happened, the sale of the sewage for use as manure did not give the profits that were expected. Health experts advanced that profits should not be the first aim of a sanitary system, but the problem was that Liernur himself had stressed financial profits as an important advantage of his system. This had attracted investors, and they promptly left the technology behind when they started to lose money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation of a vacuum sewer system is twice as cheap as the construction of a traditional sewer system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important problem, not only in the Netherlands but throughout the western world, was the growing size of cities. Both the night soil system and the more sophisticated methods were eventually beaten by the logistics of maintaining the practice in huge cities supported by far away farms. The last blow for the vacuum sewer system was the appearance of inorganic fertilizers after a cheap production method was found in 1910. The shortage of fertilizers in agriculture was &amp;ldquo;solved&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because cities had started building water carriage systems for the discharge of storm drain water, the next logical step was to allow the discharge of sewage via the same network. Basically, this was a step backwards: excrements were again drained on surface waters, not necessarily in the immediate surroundings but a few miles further downstream. It took another 70 years before sewage stations became (relatively) common in the rich world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;only-three-future-possibilities&#34;&gt;Only three future possibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to restore the natural cycle of our food supply, there are only three technological possibilities. We could develop a modern variant of the scavenging method using composting toilets, in which the stools are collected from individual homes together with other organic waste products. Urine could go to a separate tank that is emptied once a year by a tanker (this method exists in some Dutch and Swedish residential areas where people use so-called urine separation closets). Or, we could develop a modern variant of the Liernur or Berlier system, in which the sewage is collected automatically, but without the use of water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/recycling-humanure-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration by Diego Marmolejo.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration by Diego Marmolejo. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vacuum sewer systems have found a limited application in some new housing estates since the 1960s and 1970s. A few hundred systems are in operation in the US, the UK, Australia, Germany, the Maledives, Southern Africa and the Middle East (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vacuum_sewer#Project_Examples&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/a&gt;). The installation of a vacuum sewer system is twice as cheap as the construction of a traditional sewer system. A vacuum system is also faster to construct and easier to maintain: it consists of much smaller diameter tubes that have to be laid less deep into the ground - a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.quavac.com/products/vacuum/history/&#34;&gt;narrow trench&lt;/a&gt; in the road-surface suffices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a third techno-fix, but it is many times more expensive than the other two: using the diluted sewage from our water carriage system as a fertilizer. Basically, this adds another layer of costly infrastructure and complexity on top of an already very costly and complex system. Diluted sewage not only has to be dried, but also purified. This is because sewage sludge does not only contain human waste but also many other (including toxic) waste resources, both from households and factories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, when we remove urine and excrements from the sewer system, we might as well eliminate the water carriage sewer system altogether, further obtaining substantial cost and energy savings. There are workable alternatives for the removal of storm water (basically &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notechmagazine.com/2009/05/how-to-depave-the-planet.html&#34;&gt;reducing paved surface&lt;/a&gt;) and for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pruned.blogspot.com/2009/06/wetland-machine-of-sidwell.html&#34;&gt;local treatment and re-use of grey water&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;composting&#34;&gt;Composting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human faeces and urine can only be used as a fertilizer following further treatment. This was an already known fact by early Chinese agricultural writers, who warned that untreated humanure could &amp;ldquo;burn and kill plants, rot the shoots and harm human hands and feet&amp;rdquo;. Today we know it also carries more severe health risks. F.H. King and Joseph Needham praise the composting efforts of the early Chinese, who often combined their privy with the family pigsty. However, Duncan Brown is more critical of their composting techniques. The health advantages that the Chinese gained by keeping their drinking water supplies clean, were partly offset by the transmission of diseases via food crops:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Gastro-intestinal diseases were endemic throughout the region. In Korea and Japan, fluke diseases were common because of the practice of eating raw fish grown in ponds fertilized with human excrement. But those diseases could have been largely avoided with a better understanding of their nature and modes of transmission. If properly used, devices like the relatively modern sceptic tank, the more modern oxidation tank or the so-called composting toilet can avoid the danger of gastro-intestinal diseases previously associated with the use of human excrement as manure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A process of composting should always come first, and this can happen in two ways. The first - slow composting - is a a-do-it-ourselves-guide technique that is explained in the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://humanurehandbook.com/contents.html&#34;&gt;Humanure Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, an online practical guide by Joseph Jenkins (who coined the term &amp;lsquo;humanure&amp;rsquo;). Slow composting happens at low temperatures and takes about one year in a moderate climate. To be secure, most say the resulting (odourless) compost should only be used for growing crops where there is no direct contact between food and fertilizer (like fruit trees) and for inedible plants (flowers, houseplants).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/pigstay_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: F.H. King and Joseph Needham praised the composting efforts of the early Chinese, who often combined their privy with the family pigsty.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: F.H. King and Joseph Needham praised the composting efforts of the early Chinese, who often combined their privy with the family pigsty. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second method is composting at high temperatures, which goes much faster and results in a fertilizer that can be applied to any kind of food crop. It is an industrial process, which is being applied successfully in several countries for a number of years. Interestingly, the first step of this process also generates electricity, further improving the sustainability of the whole system. Since 2005, a factory of the Dutch company &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orgaworld.nl/nl/index_gbnl.html&#34;&gt;Orgaworld&lt;/a&gt; composts diapers (from babies and elderly) together with many other kinds of organic waste. It is a high-tech process that takes about 6 weeks and results in a high-quality compost, free from pathogens, medicines and hormones. The company has also built two factories in Canada and is building plants in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-we-feed-the-world-using-humanure&#34;&gt;Can we feed the world using humanure?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we produce enough natural fertilizer to substitute for synthetic nitrogen and mined potassium and phosphates? According to the figures collected by F.H. King, an adult person produces on average 1,135 grams of dung and urine each day. How much nitrogen, potassium and phosphates does this contain? That all depends on the diet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the China of 100 years ago, King cites different research results, ranging from 2.9 to 6 kilogram (5.8 to 12 pounds) of nitrogen per person per year, 0.9 to 2 kilogram (1.8 to 4 pounds) of potassium per person per year, and 0.4 to 1.5 kilogram (0.8 to 3 pounds) of phosphates per person per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we recycle our own waste products, fertilizer production would automatically keep up with population growth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the world population is estimated at 6,800,000,000 people. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume they all have a similar diet as the early 20th century Chinese and that the highest figures given by King more closely resemble today&amp;rsquo;s diets (reliable present-day figures are hard to find). This would mean that the total world population could produce 40.8 million tonnes of nitrogen, 14 million tonnes of potassium and 10.4 million of phosphates. Is that enough to eliminate the need for artificial fertilizers? At first sight, no. Today&amp;rsquo;s artificial fertilizer production is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;99.9 million tonnes of nitrogen, or more than double the amount that all people could possibly produce (40.8 million tonnes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;37 million tonnes of phosphates, almost 4 times the amount that all people could produce (14 million tonnes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;25.8 million tonnes of potassium, or more than 1.8 times the amount that all people could produce (10.4 million tonnes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;livestock&#34;&gt;Livestock&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we humans have &amp;ldquo;outsourced&amp;rdquo; a considerable amount of dung production to farm animals. A large amount of artificial fertilizer is used to produce livestock feed. These animals produce much more manure than all the people on the planet. Livestock excreta in 2004 were estimated to contain 125 million tonnes of nitrogen and 58 million tonnes of phosphates (there are no figures for potassium, which we will further ignore). That&amp;rsquo;s 3 times more nitrogen and 6 times more phosphates than can be found in humanure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Animals played a minor role in the Chinese humanure-based agricultural economy, but the European farmers in the Middle Ages relied heavily upon livestock for manure, which was their main fertilizer. Animal manure was never wasted. Joseph Needham cites Fussell:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;European farmers of the 15th to 17th centuries, both high and low, had one main worry, manure. They dared not neglect any source of supply, however minute, for the success of every crop they grew depended largely on the amount they could accumulate for use. They were willing to undertake the labours of Hercules to build a sufficient dunghill&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many good reasons to cut back on meat consumption, both for our health and for the environment - livestock production is also the main driver of deforestation (in its turn a major driver of soil degradation). However, if we don&amp;rsquo;t want to give up our high meat consumption, the least we should do is &amp;ldquo;to undertake the labours of Hercules to build a sufficient dunghill&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/mechanical-manure-spreader_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A mechanical manure spreader.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A mechanical manure spreader. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not only save us the effort to produce an ever increasing amount of artificial fertilizers, but it would also stop the devastating ecological consequences of dumping 91 million tonnes of nitrogen and 49
million tonnes of phosphates into the environment every year. Most of this is discharged without any treatment, illegally, or legally by overdosing it on fields near cities as a cost-effective waste management practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;food-scraps--management-techniques&#34;&gt;Food scraps &amp;amp; management techniques&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another source of natural fertilizer material that is being wasted - food scraps. In this case, too, we turn a valuable resource into a waste product. Food scraps could be fed to animals like pigs, greatly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notechmagazine.com/2010/09/converting-waste-into-meat.html&#34;&gt;improving the sustainability of meat production&lt;/a&gt;. But, instead, we feed them grain. Of all the food scraps produced in the US, only 3 percent is currently being recycled. The rest ends up in landfills, producing large amounts of greenhouse gases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a large potential to lower demand - one of the main problems with today&amp;rsquo;s fertilizer use is overconsumption. Artificial fertilizers are cheap and as a result farmers prefer to dose their crops with too much fertilizer, instead of risking not using enough and lowering their yields. This means that more nutrients are lost through soil erosion, runoff and leaching - which also pollutes groundwater, rivers and seas, because these nutrients do not pass through sewage stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem is not that we produce inorganic fertilizers it&amp;rsquo;s that we don&amp;rsquo;t recycle them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things were very different in the early Chinese agricultural system and during the European Middle Ages. There was never a surplus of fertilizer, so farmers applied it thoughtfully. With more careful techniques, today&amp;rsquo;s farmers could get the same yields with the use of much less fertilizer. The use of crop rotation, intercropping and green manure, all historically important techniques which are still being applied in today&amp;rsquo;s organic agriculture, could further reduce the demand for fertilizers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nutrient-balance&#34;&gt;Nutrient balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s digest all this information for a second. On the one hand, we have livestock and people, who together produce 166 million tonnes of nitrogen and 72 million tonnes of phosphates. Almost all of this is wasted, wreaking ecological havoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, our factories produce 99.9 million tonnes of artificial nitrogen fertilizer and 37 million tonnes of phosphates. A completely superfluous operation that further increases pollution and consumes vast amounts of energy. With the expected human (and livestock) population growth, not to mention the rise of energy crops to make &lt;a href=&#34;/2008/04/leave-the-algae-alone/&#34;&gt;biofuels&lt;/a&gt;, both biological and artificial production will rise even further, making everything only worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/recycling-humanure-3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration by Diego Marmolejo.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration by Diego Marmolejo. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have more than likely already passed the stage where humanity could be sustained without inorganic fertilizers. It is, after all, artificial fertilizers that caused the population boom of the 20th century. However, this should not be a problem. The large amounts of human and animal dung include nutrients which originate from inorganic fertilizers, since we all eat food that is largely grown by means of inorganic fertilizers. It is estimated that humans have already doubled the amount of nutrients in the global ecosystem. Thus, the main problem is not that we produce inorganic fertilizers it&amp;rsquo;s that we don&amp;rsquo;t recycle them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;logistic-challenge&#34;&gt;Logistic challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if we only consider livestock manure, there is enough natural fertilizer available to sustain almost 7 billion people. There is also no taboo when it comes to utilising animal manure, so why don&amp;rsquo;t we use it? Nutrients recovered as animal manure and applied to agricultural lands were estimated globally at a mere 34 million tonnes of nitrogen (28 percent of total) and 8.8 million tonnes of phosphates (15 percent) in 1996. The amount wasted thus equals (for nitrogen) or surpasses (for phosphates) artificial fertilizer production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the consequence of an industrial and intensive meat and dairy production system that is operating on a global scale. In many countries cattle eats fodder that is produced on the other side of the world. So, in order to close the loop, we would have to ship the manure back to where the fodder comes from. The FAO &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.fao.org/docrep/fao/010/a0701e/a0701e00.pdf&#34;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; (pdf):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Even if livestock is raised on the same continent as where its feed is grown, the scale and geographical concentration of industrial  feedstock production causes gross imbalances that hamper manure recycling options. High labour and transport costs often limit the use of manure as organic fertilizer to the direct vicinity of the production facilities.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we recycle our own waste products, we have to ship them back from the place of food consumption to the place of food production&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the same can be said of human manure. Just like livstock, humans are geographically concentrated in large cities with no farmland in sight. Just like livestock, we eat food that is often produced far away from where we live. This means that if we choose to collect humanure, we have to ship it back from the place of food consumption to the place of food production. Consequently, recycling nutrient elements would bring along a massive logistic system consisting of trucks, trains and ships transporting dung (or pipelines transporting sewage) all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2010/09/recycling-animal-and-human-dung-is-the-key-to-sustainable-farming/images/dithers/recycling-humanure-4_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration by Diego Marmolejo.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration by Diego Marmolejo. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not saying that every ounce of dung should be sent back to the place where the food was grown—this is impossible and ridiculous. What counts is that there is a balance between import and export of nutrients. Countries that export food should also choose to import (other) food, instead of dung, yielding the same result and increasing the dietary variety. All we would essentially need is a sophisticated nutrient accounting system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;decentralisation-of-the-human-population&#34;&gt;Decentralisation of the human population&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental solution, of course, is to produce food more locally. This would not only do away with the shipping of manure, but also with the shipping of food. If livestock production would be geographically more diversified and mixed with cropland, all the animal manure could be used and artificial fertilizers would not be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If cities were smaller and distributed more uniformly throughout farming country, the logistics of returning humanure to farmland would be greatly simplified. Of course, this &amp;lsquo;decentralisation&amp;rsquo; of the human population goes against the notion that densely populated cities are more sustainable than a more uniformly distributed population. The challenge may not be to abandon Suburbia, but to make it more self-sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.de12ambachten.nl/&#34;&gt;Sietz Leeflang&lt;/a&gt;, inventor of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.de12ambachten.nl/engnonolet.html&#34;&gt;Nonolet&lt;/a&gt; (an urban composting toilet - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.de12ambachten.nl/eng-greentech/07-12%20diynonolet.html&#34;&gt;building plans&lt;/a&gt;), who spent two years convincing me to write this epos on shit, and referred me to most documents listed below. Sietz also inspired me to write about &lt;a href=&#34;/2008/12/sunbathing-in-the-living-room-oven-stoves-and-heat-walls/&#34;&gt;oven stoves&lt;/a&gt; (which took considerably less effort).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archive.org/details/cu31924073872685&#34;&gt;Farmers of Forty     Centuries&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, F.H.     King (1911)—dung recycling in china, korea and japan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nri.org.uk/science.html&#34;&gt;Science and civilization in     China&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Vol VI:2, Joseph     Needham (1984)—idem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dbnl.org/tekst/lint011gesc02_01/index.php&#34;&gt;De geschiedenis van de techniek in Nederland - de wording van een     moderne samenleving 1800 - 1890, deel     2&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, H.W.     Lindsen (1993)—the liernur system (in Dutch)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/905727048X?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=905727048X&#34;&gt;Feed or Feedback: Agriculture, Population Dynamics and the State     of the     Planet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;l=as2&amp;amp;o=1&amp;amp;a=905727048X&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Duncan Brown, 2003—the nutrient cycle and how to     restore it (great book!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sewerhistory.org/&#34;&gt;The history of sanitary sewers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;
(website)—the liernur system and other early sewer systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sewerhistory.org/articles/design/abp3/article.pdf&#34;&gt;Proposed plan for a sewerage system, and for the disposal of     sewage&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
PDF, Samuel M. Gray (1884)—the technical options at the end of     the 19th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://humanurehandbook.com/contents.html&#34;&gt;Humanure Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
Joseph Jenkins (2005 - third edition)—diy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grist.org/article/series/the-n2-dilemma-is-america-fertilizing-disaster&#34;&gt;The nitrogen dilemma: is America fertilizing     disaster?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
Tom Philpott, Grist (2010) - inorganic fertilizers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.fao.org/docrep/fao/010/a0701e/a0701e00.pdf&#34;&gt;Livestock&amp;rsquo;s long     shadow&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, PDF,     Food and Agriculture Organisation (2006) - figures of livestock dung     production&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ipni.net/ppiweb/bcrops.nsf/$webindex/02FB2A65B5DE395D852568F000674947/$file/98-3p06.pdf&#34;&gt;Production and use of     potassium&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
PDF (1998)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ipni.net/ppiweb/bcrops.nsf/$webindex/ADC8E71EF80F70D785256BDB004837F8/$file/02-2p06.pdf&#34;&gt;Inorganic phosphorus and potassium production and     reserves&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
PDF, T.L. Roberts and W.M. Stewart, in &amp;ldquo;Better Crops&amp;rdquo; (2002)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.elaw.org/system/files/PotashMining.pdf&#34;&gt;Environmental aspects of phosphate and potash     mining&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, PDF,     UNEP (2001)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2010/04/20/peak_phosphorus?hidecomments=yes&#34;&gt;Peak     Phosphorus&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
James Elser &amp;amp; Stuart White, Foreign Policy (2010)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodandwatersecurity.net/data/172.pdf&#34;&gt;Scientists warn of lack of vita phosphorus as biofuels raise     demand&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Times     Online, June 23, 2008&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archive.org/details/cu31924011271826&#34;&gt;The voyages and adventures of Ferdinand Mendez Pinto, a Portugal,     during his travels for the space of one and 20 years in the kingdom     of Ethiopia, China, Tartaria,     etcetera&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
Ferdinand Mendez Pinto (1583).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
