<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE Italiano</title>
    <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/about/</link>
    <description>Questo e un sito a energia solare, il che vuol dire che a volte va offline.</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>it</language><atom:link href="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is Low-tech Magazine?</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/about/what-is-low-tech-magazine/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/about/what-is-low-tech-magazine/images/dithers/low-tech-hearing-aid_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="59896" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/about/what-is-low-tech-magazine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Technology has become the idol of our society, but technological progress is—more often than not—aimed at solving problems caused by earlier technical inventions. There is a lot of potential in past and often forgotten knowledge and technologies when it comes to designing a sustainable society. Interesting possibilities arise when we combine old technology with new knowledge and new materials, or when we apply old concepts and traditional knowledge to modern technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine was founded in November 2007. Since 2018, the magazine also runs on a solar powered server. The website is also available in Spanish, French, Dutch, German, and Polish. Since 2019, LTM also appears in print. Low-tech Magazine publishes at most 12 well-researched stories per year. Sister blog No Tech Magazine brings more regular updates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Offline Reading</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/offline-reading/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/offline-reading/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="17252" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/offline-reading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/offline-reading/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Printed Website.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Printed Website. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The printed archives of Low-tech Magazine now amount to four volumes with a total of 2,398 pages and 709 images. Available as paperback and hardcover, they can be ordered &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/search?contributor=Kris+De+Decker&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;pageSize=10&amp;amp;adult_audience_rating=00&amp;amp;sortBy=PUBLICATION_DATE_ASC&#34;&gt;in our Lulu bookstore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-paper&#34;&gt;Why Paper?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The books are based on the same electronic documents that make up the solar powered website — all articles were converted to Markdown, a lightweight markup language based on plain text files. However, we partly rewrote some articles, updated the references, and added more images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The books can be read with no access to a computer, a power supply, or the internet. A printed website also serves to preserve the content of Low-tech Magazine in the longer run. Websites don’t live forever, and the internet should not be taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-volume-one-2007-2012&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume One (2007-2012)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume I contains 32 articles published between 2007 and 2012. The book has 618 pages and 268 images. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lulu.com/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2007-2012/paperback/product-24347567.html&#34;&gt;Find it in our Lulu bookstore&lt;/a&gt;. Contents table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to downsize a transport network: the Chinese wheelbarrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medieval smokestacks: fossil fuels in pre-industrial times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bright future of solar powered factories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pedal powered farms and factories: the forgotten future of the stationary bicycle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bike powered electricity generators are not sustainable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The short history of early pedal powered machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insulation: first the body, then the home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aerial ropeways: automatic cargo transport for a bargain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hand powered drilling tools and machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boat mills: water powered, floating factories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recycling animal and human dung is the key to sustainable farming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The status quo of electric cars: better batteries, same range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sky is the limit: human powered cranes and lifting devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wood gas vehicles: firewood in the fuel tank&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gas bag vehicles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trolley canal boats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How (not) to resolve the energy crisis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hoffmann kilns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wind powered factories: history (and future) of industrial windmills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water powered cable trains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get wired (again): Trolleybuses and Trolleytrucks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electric road trains in Germany, 1901 – 1950&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The monster footprint of digital technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cargo ships, then and now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moonlight towers: light pollution in the 1800s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tiles as a substitute for steel: the art of the timbrel vault&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A steam powered submarine: the Ictíneo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Citroen 2CV: cleantech from the 1940s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life without airplanes: from London to New York in 3 days and 12 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Satellite navigation in the 18th century&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email in the 18th century: the optical telegraph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-volume-two-2012-2018&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume Two (2012-2018)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume II contains 36 articles published between 2012 and 2018. It has 704 pages and 257 images. We published a second edition of this volume in 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;Find it in the Lulu bookstore&lt;/a&gt;. Contents table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Build a Low-tech Website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We Can’t Do It Ourselves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ditch the Batteries: Off-grid Compressed Air Energy Storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History and Future of the Compressed Air Economy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Much Energy Do We Need?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bedazzled by Energy Efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Run the Economy on the Weather&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How (Not) to Run a Modern Society on Solar and Wind Power Alone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could We Run Modern Society on Human Power Alone?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat Storage Hypocausts: Air Heating in the Middle Ages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why the Office Needs a Typewriter Revolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Curse of the Modern Office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Get Your Apartment Off the Grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slow Electricity: The Return of DC Power?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Water Networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit Walls: Urban Farming in the 1600s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinventing the Greenhouse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Build a Low-tech Internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 4G Mobile Internet that’s Already There&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why We Need a Speed Limit for the Internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is Stored Sunlight?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is PV Solar Power?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restoring the Old Way of Warming: Heating People, not Places&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Revenge of the Circulating Fan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If We Insulate Our Houses, Why Not Our Cooking Pots?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well-Tended Fires Outperform Modern Cooking Stoves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modular Cargo Cycles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Speed Trains are Killing the European Railway Network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power from the Tap: Water Motors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back to Basics: Direct Hydropower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mechanical Transmission of Power (3): Endless Rope Drives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mechanical Transmission of Power (2): Jerker Line Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mechanical Transmission of Power (1): Stangenkunst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make everything ourselves: open modular hardware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electric velomobiles: as fast and comfortable as automobiles, but 80 times more efficient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cargo cyclists replace truck drivers on European city streets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solar envelope: how to heat and cool cities without fossil fuel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-volume-three-2018-2021&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume Three (2018-2021)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III contains 18 articles published between 2018 and 2021. It has 368 pages and 183 images. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;Find it in the Lulu bookstore&lt;/a&gt;. This volume is &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/fr/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/&#34;&gt;also available in French&lt;/a&gt;. Contents table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Circular is the Circular Economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping Some of the Lights On: Redefining Energy Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat your House with a Mechanical Windmill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinventing the Small Wind Turbine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Wind Power Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mist Showers: Sustainable Decadence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too Much Combustion, Too Little Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is a Solar Powered Website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit Trenches: Cultivating Subtropical Plants in Freezing Temperatures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermoelectric Stoves: Ditch the Solar Panels?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Biomass Energy Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and Why I Stopped Buying New Laptops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical Farming Does not Save Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is High-tech Health Care?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Urban Fish Ponds: Low-tech Sewage Treatment for Towns and Cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Build a Low-tech Solar Panel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fascine Mattresses: Basketry Gone Wild&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments collects almost 3,000 comments on roughly 100 articles that we published between 2008 and 2021. The articles are in the three other books we have made so far. The book has 688 pages and no images. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;Find it in the Lulu bookstore&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, readers have often stated that the comments on the website are (at least) as interesting as the articles themselves. We agree. Low-tech Magazine would not have been even half what it is now without the comments. You can even take this literally, because the comments take more space than the articles. This is one of the thickest books we have published so far, despite the extra small font we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;print-on-demand&#34;&gt;Print on Demand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printing is done on demand, meaning that there are no unsold copies and no large upfront investment costs. Our book distributor Lulu.com works with printers all over the world, so that most copies are produced locally and travel relatively short distances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes a bit longer to receive the book, and because each copy goes straight from printer to client, there is no way for us to control the print quality. Quality is good is most cases, but if you receive a copy that is badly printed, you should notify Lulu to get a replacement. It’s a very smooth process and there’s no need to return the damaged copy. If things don&amp;rsquo;t work out, please contact us at solar [at] lowtechmagazine [dot] com.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Donate</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/donate/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/donate/images/dithers/begger_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="62890" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/donate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine was born out of idealism and has been an independent medium since 2007. We do not receive money from governments or companies, and we stopped running advertisements in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low-tech Magazine greatly appreciates financial support from its readers. We accept donations through &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.paypal.me/lowtechmagazine&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.patreon.com/lowtechmagazine&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://liberapay.com/lowtechmagazine/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; &gt;LiberaPay&lt;/a&gt;. You can also help us by &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/it/offline-reading/&#34; &gt;ordering the printed website&lt;/a&gt;. The more support we receive, the more articles we can publish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
