<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/tags/thermal-insulation/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mar-ver.github.io/tags/thermal-insulation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Direct Solar Power: Off-Grid Without Batteries</title>
      <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-solar-office_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="48549" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-solar-office_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: a laptop running on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: a laptop running on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional solar installations do not question our dependence on fossil fuels and the energy-guzzling lifestyle that results. Both rooftop solar panels and large-scale solar farms provide us with all the power we want, even when the sun is not shining. That is because these systems use the central power grid, which largely runs on fossil fuels, as a kind of battery to cope with power shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although grid-connected solar panels can reduce the fossil fuel consumption of thermal power plants, these savings are at least partly offset by the additional fossil fuels required to build and maintain what is essentially a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;dual energy infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;. Combining solar and wind power can further increase the share of renewable energy in the power grid, but this requires further infrastructure development. Apart from energy, this also demands a lot of money and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replacing fossil-fuel-fired power plants with energy storage, so that surplus electricity generated on sunny days can be stored for when there is no or insufficient sun, encounters the same problem. Energy storage, whether integrated into a power grid or located at individual households (off-grid systems), is very expensive and &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2015/05/how-sustainable-is-stored-sunlight/&#34;&gt;carbon-intensive to build and maintain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;autonomous-solar-installation&#34;&gt;Autonomous solar installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The production of solar panels obviously &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2015/04/how-sustainable-is-pv-solar-power/&#34;&gt;costs money and energy&lt;/a&gt;. However, the financial and energy costs of the associated back-up infrastructure are many times higher. For grid-connected solar installations, these costs are very difficult to calculate precisely, but for autonomous solar installations (without grid connection and with their own energy storage) it is a lot easier. As an example, I will therefore take the small autonomous solar installation that powers my living room in Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system consists of two 50W solar panels on the balcony, a 100 Ah lead-acid battery and a 10A charge controller. The energy generated is used for lighting, the music system, and charging laptops and other electronic devices, among other things. The initial financial investment was 340 euros: 120 euros for the solar panels, 170 euros for the battery and 50 euros for the charge controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while the solar panels should last 30 years and the charge controller about 10 years, I have to replace the lead battery on average every three to five years. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Over a 30-year lifespan, the costs then amount to €120 for the solar panels, €150 for the charge controllers and – in the best case scenario – €1,020 for the batteries. The batteries (and associated charge controllers) therefore account for about 90% of the total lifetime costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy storage also dominates the plant&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;embedded&amp;rdquo; energy (and resulting carbon emissions). Producing my lead-acid battery took 1,200 megajoules (MJ) of energy. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Over a 30-year lifetime (six batteries at best), that equates to 7,200 MJ. The three charge controllers add another 360 MJ over a 30-year lifetime, bringing the total energy consumption for the battery system to 7,560 MJ. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In contrast, the production of the solar panels costs only 2,275 MJ out of a total of 9,835 MJ. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Conclusion: more than 75% of total fossil energy consumption is due to energy storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/balcony-system-from-outside_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: To the right on the balcony are the two 50W solar panels that power my flat&amp;amp;rsquo;s living room. Next to it is the 30W solar panel that makes this website work. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: To the right on the balcony are the two 50W solar panels that power my flat&#39;s living room. Next to it is the 30W solar panel that makes this website work. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/structure-for-solar-panels-balcony_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The structure for the solar panels, built from waste wood. Photo: Kris De Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The structure for the solar panels, built from waste wood. Photo: Kris De Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/100ah-battery_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The 100 Ah lead-acid battery powering the living room after sunset. Photo: Kris De Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The 100 Ah lead-acid battery powering the living room after sunset. Photo: Kris De Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other types of batteries would not significantly change this conclusion. For a comparable off-grid system with lithium-ion batteries, energy storage would account for about 95% of the total lifetime cost (which is almost double that of a system with lead-acid batteries). Assuming an optimistic lifetime (10 years) and including charge controllers, lithium energy storage accounts for some 70% of the energy invested in a solar grid system. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For nickel-iron batteries, energy storage would account for 85% of the total lifetime cost (there are no energy cost data). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scale and location of the solar installation also make no difference. A larger system needs more solar panels, but also larger batteries and more expensive and powerful charge controllers. The ratios remain the same. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The only factor that may give the solar panels a slightly larger share of the total cost is the structures on which they are mounted. I don&amp;rsquo;t take this into account because I built them myself from waste wood. However, if the solar panels are mounted on a roof, a DIY solution is less obvious. But even in that case, the cost of energy storage remains by far the biggest consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;direct-solar-energy-much-cheaper-and-more-sustainable&#34;&gt;Direct solar energy: much cheaper and more sustainable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike fossil fuels, the sun and wind are not available on demand. The problem with our approach to renewable energy is that we &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/&#34;&gt;insist that power should always be infinitely available&lt;/a&gt;, regardless of the weather, seasons or time of day. Matching energy demand to supply – &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/&#34;&gt;as was done in the past&lt;/a&gt; – would lead to dramatic reductions in the cost and use of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if I omitted the battery storage of my solar installation, my system would become about 10 times cheaper: 120 euros instead of 1,290 euros over a 30-year lifetime. Alternatively, I could spend 1,290 euros on solar panels alone, which would give me a solar system of 1,075 watts. That&amp;rsquo;s ten times the capacity of the setup with batteries, more than what would fit on the balcony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the battery and charge controller, the energy cost of the installation also drops from 9,835 MJ to 2,275 MJ. In other words, I could generate at least four times as much solar energy with the same investment in fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-direct-solar-power-be-practical&#34;&gt;How can direct solar power be practical?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All well and good, but the sun does not shine after sunset and the amount of solar energy varies throughout the day and year. So how then can using solar panels without batteries (or other back-up infrastructure in the case of grid-connected installations) be practical?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, we look at a pioneer of &amp;ldquo;direct solar power&amp;rdquo;: the &lt;em&gt;Living Energy Farm&lt;/em&gt;. This environmental education community in the US state of Virginia is completely &amp;ldquo;off-the-grid&amp;rdquo; thanks to solar power, but only 10% of the solar power generated passes through a (nickel-iron) battery. However, the solar panels provide power for several homes, a communal kitchen, a metal workshop, and a farm. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/living-energy-farm-map_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: direct solar power at the Living Energy Farm.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: direct solar power at the Living Energy Farm. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar installation has been in operation since 2011 and consists of separate systems with a total peak power of 1,400 watts. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In comparison, the average peak power of a residential solar installation in the UK and the US – for one household – is 4,000 watts and 6,500 watts, respectively. As in my flat, the Living Energy Farm uses energy sparingly, but the fact that hardly any batteries are used has other reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-appliances-are-only-used-during-the-day&#34;&gt;Some appliances are only used during the day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first reason is obvious: some electrical appliances and machines are only used during the day. This is true, for example, of all machines in the metal workshop, including a band saw, compressor, grinder, circular saw, lathe, milling machine and drilling machine. It also applies to agricultural machinery such as a grain mill and a deep well pump. Linked directly to solar panels, these machines offer all the capabilities of modern grid-powered technology, with the exception that they can only be used during the day. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a much smaller scale, I have used direct solar power for a soldering iron, glue gun and irrigation pump (for the balcony) at home. Other examples of appliances and machines that could be used only during the day include hoovers, sewing machines, washing machines, game consoles, laser cutters and 3D printers. It is not so difficult to imagine a modern society where activities such as vacuuming and DIY chores only take place during the day. It is certainly not a return to the Middle Ages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/shop-tools-living-energy-farm_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: several workshop tools at the Living Energy Farm, most of them run on direct solar power. Image: Alexis Zeigler.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: several workshop tools at the Living Energy Farm, most of them run on direct solar power. Image: Alexis Zeigler. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/metal-lathe-living-energy-farm_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Metal lathe running on direct solar power, Living Energy Farm. Image: Alexis Zeigler.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Metal lathe running on direct solar power, Living Energy Farm. Image: Alexis Zeigler. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-soldering-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Soldering with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. Watch the video.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Soldering with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. [Watch the video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qozZCJU4IOc). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, not all electrical appliances require constant attention. Washing machines or dishwashers that trigger automatically when the sun shines are often cited example applications of a &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; power grid. But that approach relies on an extensive infrastructure of electricity transmission, communication networks, and electronics-packed appliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, in a decentralised direct solar approach, the intelligence is provided by the sun and the rotation of the planet. A direct solar-powered washing machine or dishwasher can be fully charged and switched on in the evening. The machine then starts up &amp;ldquo;automatically&amp;rdquo; in the morning. You can even use timers (electronic or mechanical) to run different appliances one after the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether clouds pose an additional limit to a direct solar installation, and to what extent, depends on the size of the solar panels. Doubling the area of solar panels guarantees sufficient solar power during moderate cloud cover, while the installation remains much cheaper and more sustainable than a system with batteries or other backup infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An even larger area of solar panels could provide sufficient energy even during heavy cloud cover, but increasing the size of the system tenfold brings the cost back to the level of an autonomous system with batteries. Quadrupling the area makes the system equally dependent on fossil fuels again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;many-appliances-already-have-batteries&#34;&gt;Many appliances already have batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Direct solar power does not rule out the use of electrical appliances after sunset either. As mentioned, the Living Energy Farm has a modest battery system, providing power for lights, fans, and electronic devices after sunset, among other things.  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In addition, many modern appliances already have built-in energy storage. This is the case for all kinds of electric vehicles, for most electronic gadgets, and for older electrical appliances with AA batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, these types of devices can be charged with direct solar energy during the day and then used for several hours after sunset thanks to the built-in battery. Combined with a lithium-ion power bank, a direct solar panel can also make it possible to charge USB devices after sunset. This strategy can even work for lighting, as there are many battery-powered lamps that you can use as modern torches, hung in different parts of rooms and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/solar-phone-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A mobile phone on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A mobile phone on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, outsourcing chemical energy storage to the device is not the most sustainable option. The production of lithium-ion batteries requires fossil fuels, and (unlike lead-acid batteries) they are not recycled. The best solution, of course, is to reduce the use of electrical devices. But charging them with direct solar energy is a lot more sustainable and efficient than via other batteries or a fossil-fueled electricity grid. If we use high-tech devices, then preferably in the smartest way possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;non-electric-energy-storage&#34;&gt;Non-electric energy storage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third reason why direct solar power is more practical than it initially seems is that some electrical appliances can be used after sunset thanks to thermal energy storage. This is much cheaper and more sustainable than electrical energy storage. Thermal energy storage is already fairly well established for space and water heating systems, which store solar-heated water in an insulated boiler or (for space heating only) in the building envelope. It is no surprise that the Living Energy Farm has such systems, and solar thermal energy also provides hot water in my flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the same approach also works for two important household appliances that need to work after sunset and also consume a lot of electricity: the fridge and the cooker. Instead of storing electricity from a solar panel in a battery to then power a fridge or cooker after sunset, these appliances on the Living Energy Farm use thermal insulation. This keeps the heat inside (in the case of the cooker) or outside (in the case of the fridge) when there is no power supply. The thermal insulation also ensures very high energy efficiency, which means that each of these appliances can already operate on a solar panel of just 100-200 watts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-direct-solar-powered-fridge&#34;&gt;A direct solar-powered fridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is perfectly possible to connect a conventional fridge or freezer directly to a solar panel, but such an appliance would heat up very quickly at night. Even refrigerators with the most energy-efficient labels have a relatively limited insulation thickness (usually 2.5 cm). However, if that insulation thickness is increased to about 12.5 cm, the energy consumption of a refrigerator drops by a factor of four. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The passive cooling capacity of a refrigerator can be further increased by adding thermal mass in the form of a water tank inside the appliance. During the day, the solar panel cools the water or converts it to ice. At night, this cold water or ice slows down the heating of the refrigerator. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A direct solar-powered fridge also opens at the top, not at the front. Cold air is heavy, and so much less energy is lost that way when someone opens the door. All these design choices add up to spectacular energy efficiency. A study of direct solar refrigerators in very sunny regions (Texas and New Mexico, USA) showed that they maintained their cooling capacity for 6 or 7 days without power supply. The units operated year-round with solar panels of only 80W to 120W. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Living Energy Farm powers its solar refrigerator with a 200W panel. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/sundanzer-direct-solar-fridge_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Sundanzer DDR165. A refrigerator designed specifically for direct solar power. Photo: Sundanzer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Sundanzer DDR165. A refrigerator designed specifically for direct solar power. Photo: Sundanzer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike solar heating, solar cooling is optimally tuned to seasonal variations in solar radiation. Cooling requires more energy in summer, when there is more solar energy. The aforementioned refrigerator in New Mexico recorded electricity consumption of 406 watt-hours per day in summer and only 230 watt-hours in winter. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Moreover, the technology can be used throughout the cold chain, of which the household refrigerator is only a small (but essential) part. Another application is air cooling, although this is less well researched and more challenging. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-direct-solar-electric-cooker&#34;&gt;A direct solar electric cooker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle, a conventional cooker can also be connected directly to a solar panel, but as with a conventional fridge, it is not very practical. You can only cook during the day, and you have to install a lot of solar panels. A single hot plate needs 1,000 watts of electrical power. A solar electric cooker solves these problems by packing the cooktop with thermal insulation. The technology is basically a combination of an electric cooktop and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/&#34;&gt;haybox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/test-isec-thermal-energy-storage_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Test of an electric solar cooker. Photo: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Test of an electric solar cooker. Photo: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to thermal insulation, an electric solar cooker slowly accumulates heat during the day, which can then be used for cooking after sunset. In this way, a much lower power supply can be sufficient to achieve high temperatures. Think of it as &amp;ldquo;charging&amp;rdquo; your cooker, not with electricity but with heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers at US California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly) built the first solar electric cooker in 2015. Their 12-volt device, which has since been further developed, needs only a 100W solar panel to work. It boils a litre of water in an hour. With a full day of sunlight, it can cook almost 5 kg of beans, rice, stew or potatoes. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooking after sunset is possible by using a cooking pot with a much thicker bottom (5-10 kg). Cal Poly&amp;rsquo;s research team managed to bring the temperature of that solid heat storage to 250°C in five hours with a 100W solar panel. They were then able to boil a litre of water in three seconds after sunset. In another test, they stir-fried 1 kg of vegetables in two minutes. The ideal configuration consists of two cooking pots: one with and one without heat storage. Thus, an electric solar cooker can cook both slowly and quickly, depending on the time of day and the dish. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/cal-poly-solar-electric-cooker-idea_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The principle of a solar electric cooker with solid heat storage. Drawing: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The principle of a solar electric cooker with solid heat storage. Drawing: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thermal-or-electric&#34;&gt;Thermal or electric?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like solar water and space heating systems, cooking and cooling can work both with and without electricity – with PV panels on the one hand and solar thermal collectors on the other. But while solar space and water heating are more cost- and energy-efficient without electricity, for solar cooling and solar cooking it is just the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space and water heating require relatively small temperature differences, which can be provided by low-cost solar thermal collectors made of glass plates and water pipes. In contrast, cooling and cooking require larger temperature differences, which require more sophisticated (vacuum tube or parabolic) solar collectors – and these are more expensive than PV panels. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only exception is a simple solar cooker – an insulated box with a glass top – but it cannot achieve such high temperatures. Moreover, an electric solar cooker has some additional advantages. With a non-electric appliance, you have to cook outside, which is less practical but also less efficient, especially in winter: a thermal solar cooker will lose more heat to the environment. An electric solar cooker is also more energy-efficient because it is insulated on all sides. It also works better in cloudy weather and can be used after sunset. At the Living Energy Farm, the parabolic solar cooker is only used in optimal conditions – at full sun and high outdoor temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-technical-challenges&#34;&gt;What are the technical challenges?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the Living Energy Farm is putting all these applications of direct solar energy into practice, there are some technical challenges for those who want to follow suit. Almost all our modern technology is designed to operate with a stable and uninterrupted power supply. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be that way, but for now, direct solar power usually requires some tinkering. A direct solar system is much easier to build than an autonomous system with batteries, but it often requires modifications on the appliance side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some devices can be connected directly to a solar panel: it is enough to connect the positive and negative contacts of the solar panel and the device. For example, machines with a DC motor tolerate large fluctuations in the power supply. The metal workshop and agricultural machinery at the Living Energy Farm work this way. If clouds block the sun, the combined electrical load can become greater than the power supply from the solar panels, but this does not stop the machines. All the engines will slow down because they share the available energy, but they all continue to do useful work. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same applies to all appliances that work on the basis of resistive heating elements, such as kettles, hotplates or electric heating systems. They work regardless of power or voltage, just slower or faster. A direct solar-powered fridge preferably operates on a variable DC compressor, which can adjust its speed according to the varying solar power production. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many other devices need a specific and stable voltage input, which usually does not match what the solar panel produces. This can be solved by placing a DC-DC converter (a &amp;ldquo;buck&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;boost&amp;rdquo; converter) between the solar panel and the device. This is a small electronic module that converts the fluctuating voltage of a solar panel into a constant output voltage for a low-voltage device (5V, 12V or higher). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/solar-behind-the-scenes-3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Experiments with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Experiments with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use an inverter in addition to this, even mains appliances can operate directly on a solar panel. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; DC-DC converters are essential for all appliances that contain electronic components. This is the case for many appliances today, including those, such as washing machines or coffee machines, that until recently operated without electronics. That often gives you two options to run such appliances on direct solar power. You can either fit a DC-DC converter or modify the appliance by bypassing the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;diy-manuals--commercial-devices&#34;&gt;DIY manuals &amp;amp; commercial devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most direct solar power applications &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&#34;&gt;operate at low voltage&lt;/a&gt;, so you can safely do it yourself. Low-tech Magazine will soon publish a manual on this. However, the Living Energy Farm uses direct current with higher voltages for a number of applications. Examples are the machine tools in the metal workshop (90V) and a number of powerful electric solar cookers (48V, 180V). It is not a good idea to build these systems yourself unless you have the help of a qualified electrician, as these voltages can lead to fatal accidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those wishing to build their own (low-voltage) electric solar cookers will find comprehensive manuals at both Living Energy Farm and Cal Poly. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The devices can be made with simple materials. The insulation material should be fireproof. Example materials are rock wool, fibreglass, natural wool or clay.goed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different technologies can be used for heating elements, but embedding nichrome wires in cement is the simplest option. These wires can be taken from a variety of appliances such as toasters, ovens and hotplates. In principle, the heating wires can be attached directly to the cooking pot, but it is more practical to make a heated &amp;ldquo;nest&amp;rdquo; in which a pot can be placed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/roxy-solar-oven_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Inspired by Cal Poly&amp;amp;rsquo;s work, Living Energy Farm also developed a number of electric solar cookers, one of which they offer for sale through their website. The Roxy Oven can be used as a hotplate or an oven, for example for baking bread. The door also remains closed when used as a hot plate. This solar cooker has no energy storage.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Inspired by Cal Poly&#39;s work, Living Energy Farm also developed a number of electric solar cookers, one of which they [offer for sale through their website](https://livingenergylights.com/product/roxy-solar-electric-oven/). The Roxy Oven can be used as a hotplate or an oven, for example for baking bread. The door also remains closed when used as a hot plate. This solar cooker has no energy storage. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/roxy-deluxe-without-door_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Roxy Oven without the door and with the glass wool insulation visible. The device - made in the metal workshop with direct solar power - runs on 48V and requires a solar panel of 200 to 500 watts. Living Energy Farm also offers Sunstar&amp;amp;rsquo;s solar refrigerator for sale online.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Roxy Oven without the door and with the glass wool insulation visible. The device - made in the metal workshop with direct solar power - runs on 48V and requires a solar panel of 200 to 500 watts. Living Energy Farm also offers Sunstar&#39;s solar refrigerator [for sale online](https://livingenergylights.com/product/sunstar-direct-drive-8-cuft-chest-style-refrigerator-freezer/). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;does-direct-solar-power-waste-energy&#34;&gt;Does direct solar power waste energy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sustainability of a solar installation depends not only on the energy required to produce and maintain the infrastructure, but also on the energy produced by the solar panels during their lifetime. Some people will argue that direct use of solar power is inferior to conventional grid-connected or battery-powered solar installations in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, the hoover, washing machine and power drill are not used every day, and if no electrical appliance is connected then a solar panel will not produce power either. Consequently, the amount of electricity produced by the panel will decrease over its lifetime, while the energy needed to manufacture the panel remains the same. This makes the power from a direct solar panel more carbon-intensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, because energy storage in batteries (or the grid-connected alternative) accounts for such a large proportion of the total energy invested, a standalone solar panel can waste quite a lot of energy before it becomes less sustainable than its counterpart with battery storage or grid connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, direct use of solar power avoids the charging and discharging losses caused by batteries, or the energy losses in the transmission infrastructure for grid-connected systems. Both have to be offset by additional solar panels. Furthermore, solar panels connected to batteries or the grid also waste power – a consequence of the large difference in energy production between summer and winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maximising-direct-solar-power-with-collective-services&#34;&gt;Maximising direct solar power with collective services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it is important to maximise the energy production of a direct solar panel. In that context, it is useful to return for a moment to the original example system located on my balcony. Direct solar power could be a nice addition to this system, especially for the fridge and cooker. It was because of these appliances that I &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/&#34;&gt;concluded in 2016 that it was impossible to completely disconnect my flat from the grid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the Living Energy Farm shows that it could be done: there is room for a further 200 watts of solar panels (4 x 50W) on the balcony, enough to power both a thermally insulated fridge and hob. Additional battery capacity would not be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other appliances, however, direct solar power is of little use in my case. It would not be very efficient to install an extra solar panel for the washing machine or the power drill, as they are only used occasionally. This seems to play into the hands of a &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; electricity grid, because that way many households can use the same solar power – there is always someone who needs to wash clothes or drill a hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, such a smart grid does require a lot of infrastructure, even if direct solar power were to be used at that scale. It may not require batteries or fossil fuels as backup, but it does require transmission and communication infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-solar-record-player_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A record player on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. Watch the video.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A record player on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. [Watch the video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_LjSigJv0-0). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Living Energy Farm demonstrates an alternative solution: the communal organisation of household tasks and work. Instead of a communal power grid distributing energy to many indidvidual households, we can set up collective services with decentralised energy production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Living Energy Farm communal workshop, direct solar power can be used much more efficiently than in an individual workshop that is only used occasionally. A collective laundry in each street would also use direct solar power much more efficiently. Moreover, we save a lot of energy on building appliances this way, and gain a lot of space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;direct-wind-power&#34;&gt;Direct wind power?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strategy becomes even more important if we choose not direct solar power but direct wind power – or a combination of both. The Living Energy Farm is located in a sunny region, but the same approach could also work in windy places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is an important difference between solar power and wind power. The efficiency of a solar panel does not depend on its size, which makes solar power ideal for decentralised energy production. In contrast, the efficiency of a wind turbine &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2009/04/small-windmills-put-to-the-test/&#34;&gt;increases more than proportionally as the rotor diameter increases&lt;/a&gt;. Much better than one wind turbine per household, therefore, is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2019/06/reinventing-the-small-wind-turbine/&#34;&gt;somewhat larger wind turbine&lt;/a&gt; for a community of households, e.g. for powering a collective laundry or workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service life of lead-acid batteries depends on many factors. If they are discharged too deeply or are not fully charged regularly, the service life can be shorter than three years. On the other hand, a lead-acid battery that is hardly used or not discharged at all can last much longer than five years. However, the academic literature states a life expectancy of three to five years and this has also been my experience with the batteries I have used since 2016. See, for example, &amp;ldquo;Optimal Sizing and Life Cycle Assessment of Residential Photovoltaic Energy Systems With Battery Storage&amp;rdquo;, A. Celik, in &amp;ldquo;Progress in Photovoltaics: Research and Applications&amp;rdquo;, 2008. &amp;amp; &amp;ldquo;Energy pay-back time of photovoltaic energy systems: present status and prospects&amp;rdquo;, E.A. Alsema, in &amp;ldquo;Proceedings of the 2nd World Conference and Exhibition on photovoltaics solar energy conversion&amp;rdquo;, July 1998.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing a lead-acid battery (based on largely recycled materials) takes about 1 MJ of energy per watt-hour of storage capacity. My 100 amp-hour battery equates to a storage capacity of 1,200 watt-hours, and so the embedded energy equals 1,200 MJ. Over a 30-year lifespan, I need six of these batteries at best, so 7,200 MJ in total. Source: &amp;ldquo;Energy Analysis of Batteries in Photovoltaic systems. Part one (Performance and energy requirements)&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Part two (Energy Return Factors and Overall Battery Efficiencies)&amp;rdquo; (PDF). Energy Conversion and Management 46, 2005.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much research has been done on the embedded energy of charge controllers. The most relevant data I found is a value of 1 MJ per watt maximum power: Kim, Bunthern, et al. &amp;ldquo;Life cycle assessment for a solar energy system based on reuse components for developing countries.&amp;rdquo; Journal of cleaner production 208 (2019): 1459-1468. For a capacity of 120W (my charge controller has a maximum capacity of 10A x 12V = 120W), this amounts to 120 MJ. For the estimated lifetime, I found values of 7 and 12.5 years: same reference as above, as well as: Kim, Bunthern, et al. &amp;ldquo;Second life of power supply unit as charge controller in PV system and environmental benefit assessment.&amp;rdquo; IECON 2016-42nd Annual Conference of the IEEE Industrial Electronics Society. IEEE, 2016. I therefore made the calculation on an estimated lifetime of 10 years.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nawaz, I., and G. N. Tiwari. &amp;ldquo;Embodied energy analysis of photovoltaic (PV) system based on macro-and micro-level.&amp;rdquo; Energy Policy 34.17 (2006): 3144-3152. According to this widely quoted source, it takes 3,500 MJ to produce 1 m2 of solar panel. My two solar panels together measure 0.65 m2, representing a total energy cost of 2,275 MJ. A more recent literature review puts the energy cost for producing different types of solar panels at between 1,034 and 5,150 MJ/m2. The most recent studies of silicon solar panels in this review put the energy cost at around 1,000 MJ/m2, much lower than the figure I am using. See: Ludin, Norasikin Ahmad, et al. &amp;ldquo;Prospects of life cycle assessment of renewable energy from solar photovoltaic technologies: A review.&amp;rdquo; Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 96 (2018): 11-28.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lithium-ion batteries are a lot more expensive than lead-acid batteries, but unlike lead-acid batteries, they can be discharged deeper (up to 15% of their total capacity) and have a longer lifespan (7 to 10 years). Consequently, fewer and smaller batteries are needed. Taking these factors into account, the lifetime cost of the battery is €750, compared with €1,020 for lead-acid batteries. On the other hand, lithium-ion batteries require a more sophisticated and more expensive charge controller: a 10A charge controller costs between 200 and 600 euros, depending on the quality. Assuming a price of 400 euros for the charge controller and a 10-year lifetime for both the battery and the charge controller, battery storage accounts for 95% of the total lifetime cost (a total of 2,070 euros, much more than the total cost for the system with lead-acid batteries). Sources: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/product/12v-50ah-lithium-ion-battery&#34;&gt;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/product/12v-50ah-lithium-ion-battery&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/12v-lithium-ion-battery-chargers/&#34;&gt;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/12v-lithium-ion-battery-chargers/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the production of a lithium-ion battery costs more energy than the production of a lead-acid battery (1.4-1.9 MJ/Wh versus 1 MJ/Wh), this is offset by a longer lifespan and greater discharge capacity. The energy cost of lithium-ion batteries over a 30-year lifetime is then about 3,000 MJ, significantly less than a comparable lead-acid battery system. In contrast, the charge controller contains more complex electronics. Unfortunately, no data is available for the energy cost of such a charge controller. So there is no alternative but to estimate the energy cost based on the financial cost, which is four to twelve times more expensive than a charge controller for a lead-acid battery. Assuming a four times higher cost, the embedded energy of the charge controller increases to 480 MJ, or 1,440 MJ over a 30-year period. The total energy cost for the system is then 6,685 MJ, less than a comparable system with lead-acid batteries. Of this, almost 70% is attributable to battery storage.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nickel-iron batteries are even bigger and heavier than lead-acid batteries and they need regular maintenance. But they can be fully discharged and have a very long service life (20 years). Moreover, they can be used with the same charge controllers as lead-acid batteries. The lifetime cost over 30 years for the battery is €750, cheaper than the six lead-acid batteries of similar capacity. The total lifetime cost for a nickel-iron battery system with 100W solar panels is €1,020, of which 85% goes to energy storage. Unfortunately, nickel-iron batteries are hard to find, especially the smaller models. Sources: &lt;a href=&#34;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product/nickel-iron-battery-industrial-series/&#34;&gt;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product/nickel-iron-battery-industrial-series/&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product-category/batteries/nickel-iron/&#34;&gt;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product-category/batteries/nickel-iron/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the price of solar panels in a somewhat larger solar installation would be proportionally even smaller. This is because solar panels with small sizes (such as 50W) are proportionally more expensive per watt of peak capacity than solar panels with more conventional sizes (from 250W onwards). More or less the same applies to the energy cost.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://livingenergyfarm.org&#34;&gt;https://livingenergyfarm.org&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexis Zeigler, founder of the Living Energy Farm, wrote a book about the project, which is available in full online: &lt;a href=&#34;https://conev.org/empoweringcommunities14.pdf&#34;&gt;Empowering Communities. A Practical Guide to Energy Self Sufficiency and Stopping Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. It can also be &lt;a href=&#34;https://conev.org/&#34;&gt;ordered in hard copy&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since direct solar power does not require a charge controller for each separate system, splitting up a solar system does not involve any additional costs or energy consumption.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research shows that doubling the insulation thickness from 2.5 cm (standard insulation) to 5 cm reduces the annual electricity consumption of a refrigerator (50 litre capacity) from 250 to 125 kilowatt hours. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; With an insulation thickness of 10 to 12.5 cm, electricity consumption halves again to around 60 kilowatt hours per year. Even thicker insulation brings a smaller reduction in electricity consumption and is no longer attractive because thicker insulation also increases the cost and size of the refrigerator. The study concerns a solar-powered AC fridge that operates thanks to an inverter and a battery, which is less energy-efficient than a direct solar-powered fridge.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gupta, B. L., Mayank Bhatnagar, and Jyotirmay Mathur. &amp;ldquo;Optimum sizing of PV panel, battery capacity and insulation thickness for a photovoltaic operated domestic refrigerator.&amp;rdquo; Sustainable Energy Technologies and Assessments 7 (2014): 55-67.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thermal mass can literally be a container of water placed inside the fridge. or some water bottles for drinking. But the water can also be stored in reservoirs along the side of the appliance, behind an inner lining that keeps them in place and hides them from view. Water has a higher heat storage density than air, keeping the temperature stable for longer.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ewert, M., et al. &amp;ldquo;Photovoltaic direct drive, battery-free solar refrigerator field test results.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings of the solar conference. American solar energy society; American institute of architects, 2002.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This advantage only applies if the fridge is set up in an unheated room. The modern habit of placing a fridge in a heated kitchen when the outside temperature in winter is equal or lower than that in the fridge is obviously absurdly wasteful. But neither is this advantage valid in tropical countries, where temperatures are high all year round.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of direct solar power for space cooling has not been analysed as thoroughly as for domestic refrigerators. See: Luerssen, Christoph, et al. &amp;ldquo;Life cycle cost analysis (LCCA) of PV-powered cooling systems with thermal energy and battery storage for off-grid applications.&amp;rdquo; Applied energy 273 (2020): 115145. Moreover, it is unlikely to achieve equally large energy savings. A refrigerator is always insulated, but in the case of an air-cooled room or building, this is not necessarily the case. Moreover, a refrigerator is set up in a room where there is a stable temperature. A building is subject to greater temperature fluctuations and can also be heated by direct solar radiation. So direct solar air cooling is a lot more complicated. See: Qi, Ronghui, Lin Lu, and Yu Huang. &amp;ldquo;Parameter analysis and optimisation of the energy and economic performance of solar-assisted liquid desiccant cooling system under different climate conditions.&amp;rdquo; Energy conversion and management 106 (2015): 1387-1395.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sharedcurriculum.peteschwartz.net/solar-electric-cooking/&#34;&gt;Solar Electric Cooking&lt;/a&gt;, Pete Schwartz, Cal Poly Physics. See also &lt;a href=&#34;http://sharedcurriculum.peteschwartz.net/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2022/11/New-ISEC-Design-Ideas.pdf&#34;&gt;this PowerPoint&lt;/a&gt; by the same author.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1747&amp;amp;context=mesp&#34;&gt;Insulated Solar Electric Cooker with Solid Thermal Storage&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew McCombs et al., 2022. See also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FKIH7HDK6Dw&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See: Ferreira, Carlos Infante, and Dong-Seon Kim. &amp;ldquo;Techno-economic review of solar cooling technologies based on location-specific data.&amp;rdquo; International Journal of Refrigeration 39 (2014): 23-37. ///// Riffat, James, et al. &amp;ldquo;Development and testing of a PCM enhanced domestic refrigerator with use of miniature DC compressor for weak/off grid locations.&amp;rdquo; International Journal of Green Energy 19.10 (2022): 1118-1131. ///// Du, Wenping, et al. &amp;ldquo;Dynamic energy efficiency characteristics analysis of a distributed solar photovoltaic direct-drive solar cold storage.&amp;rdquo; Building and Environment 206 (2021): 108324. ///// Alsagri, Ali Sulaiman. &amp;ldquo;Photovoltaic and photovoltaic thermal technologies for refrigeration purposes: an overview.&amp;rdquo; Arabian journal for science and engineering 47.7 (2022): 7911-7944.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lack of research, whether the same applies to embedded energy consumption is not clear.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, however, it is necessary to bypass the device&amp;rsquo;s switch, because DC electricity produces more heat than AC electricity. Instead, a suitable external switch can help, but in doing so you bypass the device&amp;rsquo;s safety mechanism, which is obviously a risk. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref6:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Again, this does not have to be the case: it is technically possible to make devices suitable for direct solar power.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fixed-speed compressor can only use 50% of the solar power produced in a useful way, while a variable-speed compressor uses about 75% in a useful way. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A capacitor is needed to provide the compressor with an energy boost during the start-up phase.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a DC-DC converter, you can also install a small &amp;ldquo;buffer battery&amp;rdquo; and a charge controller. Like a DC-DC converter, the charge controller will ensure a stable output voltage. In addition, the small battery can provide limited energy storage that can be useful to handle short spikes in power consumption. For example, some devices have a current spike when charging. The disadvantage of a buffer battery is that the cost and embedded energy increase, and additional components can fail. A capacitor is an alternative technology to absorb power peaks.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, using low-voltage direct current devices is a lot more energy-efficient because solar panels also produce low-voltage direct current: &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&#34;&gt;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://conev.org/ISECmanual14.pdf&#34;&gt;Insulated Solar Cooker Construction Manual&lt;/a&gt;, Living Energy Farm. &lt;a href=&#34;http://sharedcurriculum.peteschwartz.net/isecooker-construction/&#34;&gt;Insulated solar electric cooker manual&lt;/a&gt;, Pete Schwartz, Cal Poly Physics. &lt;a href=&#34;https://livingenergylights.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/roxy-installation-instructions.pdf&#34;&gt;Roxy Oven Manual&lt;/a&gt;, Living Energy Farm. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SIDG8fTvf-I&#34;&gt;Video presentation manual solar electric cookers&lt;/a&gt;, Alexis Zeigler, Living Energy Farm. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uzZPstX1CbQ&#34;&gt;Video manual for making heating wires&lt;/a&gt;. Thermal heat storage: &lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1747&amp;amp;context=mesp&#34;&gt;Insulated Solar Electric Cooker with Solid Thermal Storage&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew McCombs et al., 2022. Also see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FKIH7HDK6Dw&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If We Insulate Our Houses, Why Not Our Cooking Pots?</title>
      <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/fireless-cooker-in-kitchen_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="39897" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/fireless-cooker-in-kitchen_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A fireless/gas cookstove from the 1920s.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A fireless/gas cookstove from the 1920s. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While modern cooking stoves are convenient, when it comes to energy use they leave a lot to be desired. As we &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/06/well-tended-fires-outperform-modern-cooking-stoves/&#34;&gt;have seen in the previous article&lt;/a&gt;, the thermal efficiency of an electric hob does not exceed that of a conventional open fire. In both cases almost 90% of the primary energy is lost during the cooking process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooking food could be achieved in a far more energy efficient way, especially if the cooking pot itself is insulated. This is the principle behind the fireless cooker, a well-insulated box that keeps food simmering with only the heat of the cooking pot itself. A fireless cooker doubles the efficiency of any type of cooking device because it shortens the time on the fire and limits heat transfer losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early twentieth century, fireless cookers were common additions to western kitchens, similar to the refrigerator or cooking stove. Some models even integrated fireless cookers with gas or electric hobs. These functioned by lowering an insulated hood over the cooking pot once the heat had been switched off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/thermal-efficiencies-cooking-appliances-rich-and-poor-countries_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Graph: Thermal efficiencies of cooking appliances in rich and poor countries.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Graph: Thermal efficiencies of cooking appliances in rich and poor countries. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous article, we found that &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/06/well-tended-fires-outperform-modern-cooking-stoves/&#34;&gt;cooking food is an incredibly inefficient process&lt;/a&gt;. The thermal efficiency varies from 13% for electric hobs to 23% for gas hobs, and from 5 to 25% for open fires and crude biomass stoves. Cooking stoves also produce considerable levels of indoor air pollution  —  especially in developing countries but also in the modern kitchens of wealthy households. These results show that in both developed and developing nations, energy efficiency and pollution levels in the cooking process can stand to be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed strategies to tackle these issues differ for poor and rich countries. In poorer countries, most efforts concentrate on improving energy efficiency and lowering the indoor pollution caused by biomass stoves. Rocket stoves, for example, can achieve thermal efficiencies of 45% or more, with only about half of the emissions. However, any type of improved biomass stove still requires wood for fuel, and continues to produce air pollution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the western world, the proposed solution is a more widespread use of the best available technology, such as electric induction stoves. However, these devices obtain a thermal efficiency of only 15%, which means that 85% of the energy generated for cooking is wasted. In summary, the present-day approach to improving the sustainability of cooking stoves is not very ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-is-cooking-so-inefficient&#34;&gt;Why is cooking so inefficient?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further improve upon the efficiency of cooking, we have to take a closer look at where the greatest energy losses are incurred. For electric hobs and microwaves, the most significant waste of energy can be attributed to power conversion losses. Converting fossil fuels or biomass into electricity produces an energy efficiency level of 20-45% depending on the power plant, which explains why electric stoves are among the least efficient cooking devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/gas-stove_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Gas stoves have the largest heat transfer losses of all modern cooking stoves. Image: Ashley Bischoff @ Flickr.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Gas stoves have the largest heat transfer losses of all modern cooking stoves. Image: [Ashley Bischoff @ Flickr](https://www.flickr.com/photos/handcoding/2306148621/sizes/l/in/photolist-9fwxsE-ceme3-6fsdHT-baqyQD-4vMBD8-7qKtbt-7wgwmh-5mxmYh-7t5MRY-32Zkcr-334VPJ-32ZneV-6WNUnd-4otRwY-9YKx7X-eNvbyf-5K212X-6oy431-3i4xq-5dhzoB-6aXzBk-bcpTDp-3LarEn-5Ru5J2-3i4xp-4sXcWB-4tNCfP-7teghU-8XjEGz-4KFDC7-4nXEtC-CgUdE-4hWhcF-4jFwAw-7estzW-49Ti1-9n5zm5-5vGLzJ-5LULtt-6v5ReY-67t5UC-5FrWB8-5vCsSD-6psLwc-a2JTdv-SBfWT-8shCrM-52ndMn-4RfqYF-7jkgdz/). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second most significant energy loss for electric stoves, and the most important one for all other cooking stoves, occurs during the transferral of heat from the cooking hob to the food in the cooking vessel. Not all heat produced by the fire reaches the cooking pot, and heat is lost through the walls and lid of the pot, as well as through escaping steam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cooking process is similar to heating an uninsulated building with all the doors and windows open&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to bring water to a boil and to keep a dish simmering, the cooking stove has to continuously compensate for these heat transfer losses. This is similar to heating an uninsulated building with all the doors and windows open. Even the most performable stoves now available  —  rocket stoves and wood gas stoves — only achieve a maximal thermal efficiency of 40-50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, we could do better. With regards to potential improvements in cooking sustainability, four technologies deserve further attention: pot skirts, fireless cookers, pressure cookers, and solar cookers. While each of these is a solution in themselves, they are especially advantageous when used together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pot-skirts&#34;&gt;Pot Skirts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple way to start improving cooking efficiency is by using a pot skirt. This device increases heat transfer efficiency between cooking stove and cooking pot. They work with all but the electric stove. A pot skirt is a vertical sleeve, usually of metal, that forces the hot gases from the fire to flow closely around the sides of the pot. Skirts can be insulated on the outside, which brings the additional benefit of decreasing heat losses from the sides of the pot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/pot-skirt_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A pot skirt. Picture: Ecozoomstove.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A pot skirt. Picture: [Ecozoomstove](http://ecozoomstove.com/blogs/ecozoom/13498333-maximum-rocket-stove-efficiency-use-a-pot-skirt). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pot skirt also reduces the effects of fire assymetry, which can be a problem for both outdoor and indoor cooking. Experiments in rooms with virtually no crossflow of air can show highly assymetric flame patterns, which decrease heat transfer efficiency. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vrac.iastate.edu/ethos/files/ethos2010/Saturday/Stoves,%20Electricity,%20and%20Heat%20Transfer/Skirts%20Paper_Andreatta.pdf&#34;&gt;Tests on three types of stoves&lt;/a&gt; — an open fire, a biomass rocket stove and a gas rocket stove — showed that pot skirts can improve heat transfer efficiency by about 10-20% for a rocket stove, and by about 30% for an open fire. Since heat transfer losses are the main inefficiency for these types of cooking stoves, this is not a bad start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pressure-cookers&#34;&gt;Pressure Cookers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rather well-known pressure cooker takes a different approach. A pressure cooker is a sealed vessel which reaches higher water temperatures because of added steam pressure, making it more energy efficient and able to cook food faster. It is either operated electrically (as a standalone device or on an electric stove), or used in combination with a gas, biomass, coal or solar stove. The pressure cooker lowers both power conversion losses (because of shorter cooking times) and heat transfer losses (because it completely eliminates heat loss through evaporation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/pressure-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A pressure cooker. Image: Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A pressure cooker. Image: Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific studies on the energy efficiency of a pressure cooker could not be found. Manufacturers usually advertise energy and time savings of up to 70% when compared to cooking in a normal pot. If we assume these figures to be correct averages (which is probably overly optimistic), then the thermal efficiencies of cooking stoves start to look more promising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a pressure cooker is used on an electric stove, the cooking process would reach a thermal efficiency of 22%, which brings it on par with a well-tended three-stone fire. The combination of a gas stove with a pressure cooker would achieve a thermal efficiency of 39%, while the combination of a well-tended three-stone fire with a pressure cooker would obtain 40% thermal efficiency. The best result is achieved via the combination of pressure cooker and rocket stove, which is 62% effective. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fireless-cookers&#34;&gt;Fireless Cookers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we can see marked improvements with the pressure cooker, these vessels still lose heat through the walls and lid, and these losses are considerable. There are also heat transfer losses between the stove and the pot if the device is placed on a hob. However, if we bring food to a boil and then quickly put the pot in a well-insulated box, the heat transfer energy losses can be minimized to such an extent that the cooking process continues, without any further energy input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/fireless-cooker-in-basket_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Fireless cooker in a basket. Picture: Solar Cookers International.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Fireless cooker in a basket. Picture: [Solar Cookers International](http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/Heat-retention_cooking). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the principle of the &amp;ldquo;fireless cooker&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;heat retention cooker&amp;rdquo;, which is best described as the passive house concept applied to cooking. A passive house is a well-insulated building that requires little energy for space heating of cooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fireless cooker is the passive house concept applied to cooking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fireless cooker is the key to efficient cooking in poor and rich countries alike. It almost completely eliminates heat transfer loss and reduces cooking time on the fire or hob substantially, thus addressing the two largest energy losses in the cooking process. Fireless cookers can lower energy use by more than 80%, but the precise savings potential depends on many factors. Such factors include the insulation material, the design of the fireless cooker, the required cooking time of the dish, the food itself, and the swiftness with which the cooking pot is moved from the stove to the fireless cooker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/classical-fireless-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A classical fireless cooker. Image: Natuurlijk Bewaren.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A classical fireless cooker. Image: [Natuurlijk Bewaren](http://www.natuurlijkbewaren.nl/website/). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Partnership for Clean Indoor Air (PCIA) has measured the energy savings of fireless cookers. In their &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/06/well-tended-fires-outperform-modern-cooking-stoves/&#34;&gt;test of 18 types of solid fuel cooking stoves&lt;/a&gt;, the energy savings of the fireless cooker amount to an average fuel reduction of 50%, which is the number we will use in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we combine an electric stove with a fireless cooker, we can double its thermal efficiency. Combined they reach 26%, which is still not very impressive, but at least achieves a higher energy efficiency than a gas stove alone. A gas stove used in conjunction with a fireless cooker obtains 46% thermal efficiency, while a well-tended fire with a fireless cooker attains 50%. A combination of a rocket stove with a fireless cooker is more than 80% efficient. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/thermal-efficiency-fireless-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Graph: Thermal efficiency of a fireless cooker&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Graph: Thermal efficiency of a fireless cooker 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These numbers could be further improved if we combine the fireless cooker with the pressure cooker. If we use a pressure cooker to bring food to a boil and then put the pressure cooker into a fireless cooker, we can cook at 40%-90% efficiency, depending on the cooking stove used. This compares to a maximum of 23% for our western cooking stoves, and 40% — or at most 50% — for improved biomass stoves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, the fireless cooker is a wooden, metal or plastic container filled with straw, old clothes, styrofoam, paper or any other insulation material. It can even be a cooking pot wrapped into a sleeping bag. Usually 5 to 10 cm of insulation is applied on all sides, the upper layer often in the form of an easy-to-handle, scaled-down mattress or pillow. A more cost-effective technique to lower energy use is hardly imaginable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fireless-cookers-in-history&#34;&gt;Fireless Cookers in History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some parts of the world, the concept of the fireless cooker has been known about for centuries. During the middle ages, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peoplescollectionwales.co.uk/items/7915&#34;&gt;Europeans used&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;hayboxes&amp;rdquo; and holes in the ground filled with straw. American Indians took a slightly different approach to limiting heat transfer losses by enclosing the heat source (fire-heated stones or clay balls) within the cookware. Some American Indian groups used &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brighthubeducation.com/social-studies-help/96105-traditional-native-american-cooking/&#34;&gt;cooking baskets&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;
for this purpose; tightly woven &lt;a href=&#34;http://books.google.es/books?id=OsJZahLLUxoC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;hl=nl&amp;amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;watertight baskets&lt;/a&gt;, which could be coated with clay for insulation. Others stone-boiled soups and stews in a hole that they dug in the ground, lined with animal hide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fireless cooker became popular in the western world in the years between the 1890s and the 1930s. A Norwegian &amp;ldquo;self-cooking apparatus&amp;rdquo;
received an award at the 1867 World Exhibition in Paris. It was a simple yet elegant container with four layers of felt for insulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/fireless-cooker-with-associated-cooking-pots_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A fireless cooker with associated cooking pots. Image: Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A fireless cooker with associated cooking pots. Image: Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first decades of the twentieth century, the fireless cooker became a permanent fixture of many American and European households&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the heat retention cooker was mainly used to make food more portable for use by people on the move such as fishermen, hunters and soldiers. Amsterdam trams (streetcars) had them onboard for the driver. However, during the first decades of the twentieth century, the fireless cooker also became a permanent fixture of many American and European households, an appliance often found next to the cooking stove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best models were made entirely out of metal lined with mineral wool insulation, and kept the cooking pot and insulating material separated for easy cleaning and durable construction. These devices were also used for cooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/fireless-cooker-integrated-in-gas-hub_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A fireless cooker integrated into a gas hob.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A fireless cooker integrated into a gas hob. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/fireless-cooking-gas-range_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Chambers Fireless Cooking Gas Range from the 1910s. The insulated hoods were lowered over the burners.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Chambers Fireless Cooking Gas Range from the 1910s. The insulated hoods were lowered over the burners. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another innovation from the early twentieth century was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vintagechambers.com/indexe042.html?module=pagemaster&amp;amp;PAGE_user_op=view_page&amp;amp;PAGE_id=2&amp;amp;MMN_position=8:8&#34;&gt;fireless cooking gas range;&lt;/a&gt;
a combination of gas stove, gas oven and fireless cooker. The device obviated the need to move cooking utensils from the hob to the fireless cooker by making use of insulated hoods — &amp;ldquo;thermodomes&amp;rdquo; — that could be lowered over the burners. The food was brought to a boil, the gas was shut off, and then the pot would be covered up by the thermodome. The inverted receptacle was raised and lowered with the assistance of a counterbalance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/integrated-fireless-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: How to operate the thermodome.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: How to operate the thermodome. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the hood was partially lowered while the gas was burning. The interior thus became hot from the heat which would otherwise escape, ensuring that plenty of retained heat would be available for cooking after the gas was turned off. Later versions worked completely automatically, shutting off the gas and lowering the hood at a preset time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another attempt to merge fireless cookers with cookstoves was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.automaticwasher.org/cgi-bin/TD/TD-VIEWTHREAD.cgi?51147_3&#34;&gt;deep well cooker&lt;/a&gt; (also known as the &amp;ldquo;thrift cooker&amp;rdquo;). Old ranges, both gas and electric, sometimes had one of their burners sunk into a hole in the cooktop. This &amp;ldquo;well&amp;rdquo; had heavily insulated sides and enclosed a specifically designed pot with an insulated lid and no handles on the sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/deep-well-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A deep well cooker from the 1950s. Source.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A deep well cooker from the 1950s. [Source](http://www.automaticwasher.org/cgi-bin/TD/TD-VIEWTHREAD.cgi?51147_3). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some models, the burners could double as a surface unit. Although they were not really fireless cookers — the pot was on a low fire — deep well cookers reduced heat transfer losses considerably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;improved-fireless-cookers&#34;&gt;Improved Fireless Cookers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of heat retention cookers declined in the 1930s, and then resurfaced during World War Two and the oil crises of the 1970s. Today the fireless cooker is mainly promoted for use in developing countries. NGO&amp;rsquo;s that have introduced the technology are — among others — &lt;a href=&#34;http://practicalaction.org/fireless-cooker-1&#34;&gt;Practical Action&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://helpsintl.org/&#34;&gt;HELPS International&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/Heat-retention_cooking&#34;&gt;Solar Cookers International&lt;/a&gt;. The designs made for developing countries differ, from the insulated baskets of Solar Cookers International to the styrofoam insulated &lt;a href=&#34;http://nb-wonderbag.com/Pages/Default&#34;&gt;Wonderbag&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://pciaonline.org/files/RHC%20Guide%20English.pdf&#34;&gt;ONIL&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although heat retention cookers can be made cheaply with natural and locally available resources, they could just as well be mass-produced using more sophisticated materials. While it makes the devices less sustainable in production, plastic has made fireless cookers more practical, and superior insulation materials have improved their performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thermal cooker is a compact, high-tech version of a fireless cooker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important innovation in the western market is the so-called thermal cooker which appeared in the 1990s. The device is based on vacuum technology: the principle behind the thermos flask. The thermal cooker is comprised of a removable cooking pot, with handle and lid, that fits inside a vacuum flask which has a diameter ranging from 20 to 50 cm. The cooking pot is heated on the cooking stove (regardless of type) and then moved to and sealed in the flask. Find an exampe &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zojirushi.com/products/snxae&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/thermal-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A thermal cooker. The high-tech version of the fireless cooker. The cooking pot (left) is put on the fire and transferred to the vacuum flask (right) once to food has been brought to a boil. Picture: Thermal Cookware&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A thermal cooker. The high-tech version of the fireless cooker. The cooking pot (left) is put on the fire and transferred to the vacuum flask (right) once to food has been brought to a boil. Picture: [Thermal Cookware](https://www.thermalcookware.com/main.php?mod=Shop&amp;file=Cats) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a thermos flask or thermal vacuum cooker the space between the dual walls of a cylinder is completely evacuated. With virtually no molecules of gas available, heat transfer by conduction and convection are almost eliminated and therefore thermal conductivities are extremely low. Insulation thickness is about one-seventh of that of rockwool and one-third that of petrochemical insulation foams for similar thermal resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a much more compact fireless cooker, which could easily become part of any western kitchen as a standard, built-in device next to the cookstove. Smaller thermal cookers could be used to make hot food portable. Vacuum insulation is also available in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.porextherm.com/en/products/vacupor.html&#34;&gt;insulation panels&lt;/a&gt;, which you could use to build a compact yet superinsulated fireless cooker yourself. (But although home production is possible, one would have to adapt to available sizes — it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to cut the panels as this would destroy the vacuum).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All too often, fireless cookers are pictured as an emergency device aimed at campers, refugees or survivalists. However, a relatively simple device that can double the efficiency of whatever cooking technology you have at your diposal deserves more credence than that. The fireless cooker should be a commonplace item in every kitchen. Aside from its energy saving potential, its use in the western world would also encourage its acceptance in the developing world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-saving&#34;&gt;Time Saving&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of the twentieth century, time savings were the main sales argument for fireless cookers. This seems odd, because the average cooking time doubles compared to the traditional cooking process. Fireless cookers do afford the cook more time, however, by reducing the amount he or she spends in front of the stove or fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/photograph-woman-cooking-dinner-for-six-fireless-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Early twentieth century advertisement for fireless cooking.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Early twentieth century advertisement for fireless cooking. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the cooking pot has been transferred to the fireless cooker, it requires no further attention and the cook is free to do something else, even if it&amp;rsquo;s outside the house. It&amp;rsquo;s impossible for the food to boil over, and there is no fire hazard to keep an eye on. Furthermore, a dish can stay hot for up to 6 hours or more, so the timing of the cooking process becomes more flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fireless cooker also increases the capacity of a cooking stove, whether it runs on electricity, gas, coal, wood or solar energy. You can put a new dish on the fire while the other one is simmering in the fireless cooker. With every fireless cooker you add, the capacity of the cooking stove increases further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solar-cookers--fireless-cookers&#34;&gt;Solar Cookers + Fireless Cookers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature is especially interesting in combination with a solar cooker. A fireless cooker increases the capacity of a solar cooker, but it also allows you to cook if there is not much sun available. When a fireless cooker is used to complete the cooking process, a solar cooker requires as little as half an hour of sunshine to cook dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fireless cookers essentially act as batteries, storing energy in hot food. They greatly increase the usefulness of solar cookers, making them appropriate even on cloudy days and in countries where there is less sunshine. Furthermore, the combination of solar cooker and fireless cooker allows you to prepare a meal that can be served hours after sunset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/solar-box-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A low-tech solar box cooker. Image: Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A low-tech solar box cooker. Image: Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When viewed alongside all other cooking appliances, the solar cooker is the ultimately sustainable stove. It requires zero fuel and produces zero air pollution. Even if gas or solid fuel stoves could reach a thermal efficiency of 100%, they would still require resources like wood or coal, and they would continue to produce air pollution. The solar cooker is the only cooking device that doesn&amp;rsquo;t face these issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fireless cooker greatly increases the usefulness of a solar cooker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exist &lt;a href=&#34;http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/Category:Solar_cooker_plans&#34;&gt;many designs for solar cookers&lt;/a&gt;. The simplest type is the solar box cooker, which is not much more than an insulated box with a glass plate on top. The glass allows solar radiation to enter, heating up the interior, while the insulated walls decrease heat loss. There is not much difference between a solar box cooker and a fireless cooker, and both appliances could be merged into one design. Solar box cookers can also work under cloudy conditions because they are able to exploit diffuse radiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parabolic solar cookers incorporate a more complex design, and use curved mirrors to focus solar radiation on a focal point. They work faster, produce higher temperatures, and have the ability to fry, roast and barbeque food. They are, however, more challenging to build, they require frequent orientation to the sun, they can be dangerous, and they only work in clear weather conditions. Panel cookers — such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/CooKit&#34;&gt;CooKit&lt;/a&gt; — incorporate elements of both box and parabolic cookers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/parabolic-solar-cooker_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A parabolic solar cooker. Picture: Solar Cookers International.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A parabolic solar cooker. Picture: [Solar Cookers International](http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/Heat-retention_cooking). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar cooker is not the only way to take advantage of solar energy for cooking. Electric cookstoves or microwaves run by electricity from PV solar panels can also be considered solar powered cookstoves. However, converting solar energy into electricity to convert it to heat in order to boil water is needlessly complex, energy inefficient, and very expensive compared to taking advantage of solar heat in a direct way by using a solar cooker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;indoor-solar-cooking&#34;&gt;Indoor Solar Cooking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like improved biomass stoves and fireless cookers, solar cookers are mainly promoted in developing countries as an alternative to the use of open fires. The technology is distributed by some 500 organisations, companies, and individuals, united in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/Solar_Cookers_International_Network&#34;&gt;Solar Cookers World Network&lt;/a&gt;. The promotion of panel and box cookers is mostly aimed at households and refugees, while the more sophisticated parabolic cookers are generally reserved for large-scale cooking in institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The promotion of solar cookers in developing countries has produced improved technology that can be useful all over the world. For example, it is now possible to cook indoors using solar energy. This can happen in two ways: either by focusing a parabolic cooker through a wall aperture and then reflecting the sunlight onto a cooking pot, or by using concentrated sunlight to generate steam which is then transported through pipes to a nearby indoor kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/indoor-solar-cooking_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Indoor solar cooking. Image: Solare Brücke.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Indoor solar cooking. Image: [Solare Brücke](http://www.solare-bruecke.org/index.php?lang=en). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both approaches were demonstrated in the Scheffler Community Kitchens in India. These cooking installations are applied on a very large scale, for example at the Shirdi Temple where a solar cooked lunch is served to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.renewindians.com/2012/07/indian-temples-set-high-standards-in.html&#34;&gt;over 50,000 people per day&lt;/a&gt;. However, using solar energy indoors can also happen on a much smaller scale, as is demonstrated by the system pictured above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar cookers used in developing countries are usually not the most efficient devices. Improving them with more sophisticated materials greatly increases their usability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a remarkable and highly sustainable piece of equipment, most solar cookers used in developing countries are not the most efficient. As Appropedia &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appropedia.org/Solar_cooking&#34;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;, solar cookers are &amp;ldquo;solar concentrators where precision and efficiency have been sacrificed for ease of construction and use of readily available materials&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of these cookers could be enhanced if we built them in a more sophisticated way. For example, low-E window glass makes a solar box cooker much more efficient, as most heat that escapes from the box is through the glass. Solar Cookers International &lt;a href=&#34;http://solarcooking.wikia.com/wiki/Where_is_solar_cooking_possible%3F&#34;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt; that the ongoing development of more efficient models continues to push the practicality of solar cookers into higher latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-cooking-sustainable-integrated-cooking&#34;&gt;Making Cooking Sustainable: &amp;ldquo;Integrated Cooking&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining cooking stoves with solar cookers, fireless cookers, and pressure cookers turns an inefficient process into a year-round sustainable system that dramatically cuts greenhouse gas emissions, fuel use, and air pollution. This holds true for poor and rich countries alike, regardless of which type of cooking stove is used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, NGO&amp;rsquo;s are betting on a combination of solar cookers, fireless cookers and improved biomass stoves, an approach that is known as &amp;ldquo;integrated cooking&amp;rdquo;. [2] In &amp;ldquo;integrated cooking&amp;rdquo;, solar cookers are used whenever possible, while the improved biomass stove offers a solution when solar energy is not available. The fireless cooker is used in combination with both, increasing the capacity of the cooking system and maximizing energy efficiency. For an example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I1U2ILREJqk&#34;&gt;see this video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar system in the western world could even utilise electric or gas stoves instead of improved biomass stoves. Because the use of fireless cookers, pressure cookers and solar cookers shortens the use of electric or gas stoves considerably, their low efficiency becomes less of a concern. If the energy use of gas and electric stoves is substantially reduced, it also becomes more realistic to supply this smaller amount of energy by renewable sources, such as wind power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/images/dithers/integrated-cooking_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Integrated cooking: combining solar cookers, fireless cookers and improved biomass stoves.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Integrated cooking: combining solar cookers, fireless cookers and improved biomass stoves. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, NGO&amp;rsquo;s are betting on a combination of solar cookers, fireless cookers and improved biomass stoves&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar cookers and fireless cookers are good examples of the kind of technology that we aim for here at Low-tech Magazine. They can be cheap and easy to make, they are truly sustainable, and yet they are superior to any cooking technology available in pre-industrial times. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2010/11/boat-mills-water-powered-floating-factories/&#34;&gt;extensive use of water power&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;wind power in history&lt;/a&gt;
seems to suggest that solar cooking goes back many centuries, but that is not the case. The first experimental solar box cookers only appeared in the 18th century, and parabolic cookers only showed up in the late 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar cookers and fireless cookers might have a very low-tech image, but they integrate well with high-tech materials. Before the Industrial Revolution, we had no tin or aluminium foil, no vacuum technology, no plastic containers, and no thermally insulated glass. Cooking with fireless cookers, pressure cookers and solar cookers is not a return to the now impractical or defunct gadgets of the past. Rather, it is an innovative approach that optimizes existing knowledge and technology with the aim of radical energy efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all readers who have urged me to write about fireless cookers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a rough calculation as I have assumed that the cooking time is equally divided between the cooking stove and fireless cooker, and that the energy use of a cookstove is the same whether it brings water to a boil or merely simmers it. This leads to either an overestimation or an underestimation of the combined thermal efficiency, depending on the technology used. For example, a rocket stove is especially efficient at high power output and much less so while simmering water, so that the combined efficiency of rocket stove and fireless cooker is higher than mentioned.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Solar Envelope: How to Heat and Cool Cities without Fossil Fuels</title>
      <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Sun-S_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="46052" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Sun-S_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration by Diego Marmolejo for Low-tech Magazine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration by [Diego Marmolejo](http://ddidak.blogspot.com.es/) for Low-tech Magazine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 / &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-2/&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-3/&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architects all over the world have demonstrated the usefulness of buildings which are heated and cooled by design rather than by fossil fuel energy. What has received much less attention, however, is the possibility of applying this approach to entire urban neighbourhoods and cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing a single, often free-standing, passive solar house is quite different from planning a densely populated city where each building is heated and cooled using only natural energy sources. And yet, if we want passive solar design to be more than just a curiosity, this is exactly what we need. Modern research, which combines ancient knowledge with fast computing techniques, shows that passive solar cities are a realistic option, allowing for surprisingly high population densities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passive solar design has been around for thousands of years, and even predates the use of glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passive solar design requires the knowledge to design and orientate buildings so that they can be heated by the sun. Coupled with other low-tech solutions such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2011/02/insulation-first-the-body-then-the-home/&#34;&gt;thermal underwear&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;ndash;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/&#34;&gt;heated clothing&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;ndash; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/&#34;&gt;creation of microclimates&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash;, passive solar design could all but eliminate the use of fossil fuels and biomass for heating buildings throughout large parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indirectly, a passive solar house can also cancel the energy requirements for cooling and ventilation (passive cooling), and for lighting during the day. Of course, passive solar buildings can be outfitted with solar water heaters and PV solar panels, further reducing the use of unsustainable energy resources. Passive solar design does not involve any new technology. In fact, it has been around for thousands of years, and even predates the use of glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of human history, buildings were adapted to the local climate through a consideration of their location, orientation and shape, as well as the appropriate building materials. This resulted in many vernacular building styles in different parts of the world. In contrast, most modern buildings look the same wherever they stand. They are made from the same materials, they follow forms that are driven by fashion rather than by climate, and are most often randomly located and oriented, indifferent to the path of the sun and the prevailing wind conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Casas-solar-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration by Diego Marmolejo for Low-tech Magazine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration by [Diego Marmolejo](http://ddidak.blogspot.com.es/) for Low-tech Magazine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern buildings rely on a massive supply of cheap fossil fuels for heating, cooling, and lighting. Take the supply of cheap fossil fuels away, and they become completely uninhabitable for most of the year: they are too cold, too hot or too dark. This radical change in architectural design was caused by both the arrival of cheap and abundant energy sources and the resultant urbanisation (See &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-2/&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;mdash;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Industrial Revolution relocated millions of people from the countryside to the cities. When most of us lived and worked on farms or in hamlets, it was fairly easy to orientate one&amp;rsquo;s house towards the sun. In an urban environment, however, building orientation is generally determined by street layout, and one building can easily overshadow another. High-rise buildings further complicate solar access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-solar-oriented-buildings-to-solar-oriented-cities&#34;&gt;From solar oriented buildings to solar oriented cities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that passive solar design could not be applied to entire cities. It just takes more sophisticated planning. Solar access to an individual building is determined by only four factors: latitude (the distance north or south from the equator), slope, building shape and orientation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar access to a city (or any other built-up environment) is determined by &lt;em&gt;seven&lt;/em&gt; factors: the four just mentioned, plus the height of the buildings, the width of the streets, and the orientation of the streets (See &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-2/&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;mdash;). Providing ventilation in an urban environment is determined by the same factors, with the exception that latitude is replaced by prevailing wind conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/General-principle-solar-envelope_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Ralph Knowles developed and refined a method that strikes an optimal balance between population density and solar access: the &amp;amp;quot;Solar Envelope&amp;amp;quot;.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Ralph Knowles developed and refined a method that strikes an optimal balance between population density and solar access: the \&#34;Solar Envelope\&#34;. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most research in passive solar design during the 1970s was directed at individual buildings, one man began forty years of research into solar oriented cities: Ralph Knowles, professor emeritus at the USC&amp;rsquo;s School of Architecture and author of three fascinating books on the topic (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0262610256/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;1974&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/026261040X/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;1981&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/1597260509/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowles developed and refined a method that strikes an optimal balance between population density and solar access: the &amp;ldquo;Solar Envelope&amp;rdquo;. It is a set of imaginary boundaries, enclosing a building site, that regulate development in relation to the sun&amp;rsquo;s motion—which is predictable throughout the seasons for any place on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buildings within the solar envelope do not overshadow neighbouring buildings during critical energy-receiving periods of the day and the year&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buildings within this imaginary container do not overshadow neighbouring buildings during critical energy-receiving periods of the day and the season, and assure solar access for both passive and active solar systems. On the one hand, the solar envelope allows architects to design with sunlight without fear that their ideas will be cancelled out by future buildings. On the other hand, the solar envelope recognizes the need for development and high population densities, by defining the largest container of space that would not cast shadows off-site at specified times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Floor-to-area-ratio-and-solar-access_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Floor-to-area ratio and solar access. Ralph Knowles.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Floor-to-area ratio and solar access. Ralph Knowles. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowles and his students have reached densities that are far above the average in European and American cities (See &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-3/&#34;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&amp;mdash;), with the exception of high-rise centers such as Manhattan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;modification-of-traditional-zoning-practices&#34;&gt;Modification of traditional zoning practices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar envelope is actually a relatively simple modification of existing zoning practices, which also set imaginary boundaries that enclose a building site—determining the maximum height, width and depth of future buildings. The most rigid approach in conventional zoning prescribes maximum building heights, set in feet or metres, number of floors, or both. A second, more flexible approach, sets limits based on a ratio between developeable land and floor area within the building on that site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a floor-to-area ratio (FAR) of 6 means that architects can develop 6 times the developeable square footage of land within the setbacks. They could cover the entire site with 6 stories, or cover only half of the site with 12 stories, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both zoning methods offer a certain degree of solar access in a city, they are far from optimal. The main problem is that they do not design building orientation with its solar impact in mind, which can be as critical as building height. For example, a skyscraper with its broad flat sides facing east and west will cast a relatively small midday winter shadow, while one oriented with its broad flat sides facing north and south will shade a much larger area during the sunniest periods of the day (illustration above). Taking orientation into account would greatly improve solar access for surrounding buildings, without sacrificing housing density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-geometry-of-the-solar-envelope&#34;&gt;The geometry of the solar envelope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to conventional zoning practices, the solar envelope produces a different geometry—the limits of the envelope derive their vertical dimensions from the sun&amp;rsquo;s daily and seasonal movements. Thus, while conventional zoning envelopes are shaped like a box, the solar envelope has both vertical and sloping spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, the buildings and city blocks that fill these imaginary solar envelopes are more likely to have unique shapes. One side of a building would not look like the other, nor would each side of the street. In the northern hemisphere, development would tend to be lower on the south side of a street than on the north where a major southern exposure would be preserved. Streets take on a directional character where solar orientation is clearly recognised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjacent buildings can meet each other gently, rather than abruptly, across property sidelines. Tall buildings would group together at the site&amp;rsquo;s southwestern end, and those of moderate height at the northeastern end, with the shortest buildings taking up the site&amp;rsquo;s midsection. Buildings on corner lots will be taller because their shadows can extend accross the street in two directions instead of one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Solar-Envelopes-Ralph-Knowles_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Solar envelopes on the Spanish street grid system in Los Angeles. Ralph Knowles.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Solar envelopes on the Spanish street grid system in Los Angeles. Ralph Knowles. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Buildings-within-solar-envelopes-ralph-knowles_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Buildings within the solar envelopes shown above. Ralph Knowles.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Buildings within the solar envelopes shown above. Ralph Knowles. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Solar-Envelopes-High-Density-Housing-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Building designs under the solar envelope are characterised by roof terraces, courtyards and clerestories. Ralph Knowles.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Building designs under the solar envelope are characterised by roof terraces, courtyards and clerestories. Ralph Knowles. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the solar envelope, certain architectural characteristics have great consistency. For instance, roof terraces appear where the sloping sides of the envelope intersect the rectilineair geometry of buildings. Courtyards are another crucial element, as they introduce sunlight and heat to deep interiors. Clerestories allow for the penetration of winter sun down stairways to enliven otherwise darker, lower floors. Sunscreens and porches are everywhere, keeping the sun out in summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;defining-solar-access&#34;&gt;Defining solar access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar envelope is not only defined by the path of the sun, but also by fixed parameters set by the designer. Choosing these will determine the balance between solar access and development potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important choice is the definition of the hours during which we want to avoid casting shadows on adjacent land—the &amp;lsquo;cut-off times&amp;rsquo;. The longer the period of daily solar access, the smaller the developeable volume under the envelope. Obviously, setting the cut-off times as equal to the period between sunrise and sunset would not work, because in that case few or any buildings could be constructed. For passive solar design, a minimum of 4 to 6 hours per day in winter is considered practical, depending on the climate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Generation-of-solar-envelope-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Generation-of-solar-envelope-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Generating a solar envelope.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Generating a solar envelope. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duration of solar access could also be set by a minimum percentage of available energy instead of determining a minimum hours of sunshine. In that case, cut-off times would change over the course of the year. Another parameter to be set is the &amp;lsquo;shadow fence&amp;rsquo;. It determines the minimum height to which solar access has to be assured; for instance zero, 3 or 6 metres above street level. For example, one can choose to allow shadowing of garages and shops in order to improve the density under the solar envelope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-existing-buildings&#34;&gt;What about existing buildings?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar envelopes can be designed for individual buildings or as a single envelope for a group of houses, a neighbourhood, a district or even an entire city. This is a rather straightforward process when a site is being designed from scratch, but often current buildings will complicate the generation of a solar envelope. When the solar envelope is applied in line with existing buildings, new construction would always be shaped and proportioned with reference to the old. Each new phase of development changes the surroundings and thus the context within which the next envelope is generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Knowles-Wilshire-Housing-Project_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A solar envelope casting its maximum shadow in winter. The smaller, previously built houses retain their solar access. Ralph Knowles.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A solar envelope casting its maximum shadow in winter. The smaller, previously built houses retain their solar access. Ralph Knowles. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Wilshire-project-buildings-within-solar-envelope_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: One of the building designs within the solar envelope shown above. Ralph Knowles.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: One of the building designs within the solar envelope shown above. Ralph Knowles. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that the solar envelope only protects neighbouring properties. It is the architect who must ensure solar access to the buildings within the envelope, tackling problems of overshadowing within the envelope itself. For larger sites, the volume of a solar envelope is therefore larger than the volume of the buildings that actually fill it, at least when solar access is assured to all dwellings on site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solar-oriented-cities-in-antiquity&#34;&gt;Solar oriented cities in Antiquity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowles&amp;rsquo; research draws on ancient knowledge, most notably the solar planned cities in Ancient Greece and the solar communities of the Ancient Pueblo People in what is today the Southwestern United States. The Ancient Greeks built entire cities which were optimal for solar exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fifth century BC, for example, a neighbourhood for about 2500 people was built in the city of Olynthus. The streets were built perpendicular to each other, running long in the east-west direction (the horizontal streets shown in the plan below), so that all houses (five on each side of the street) could be built with southern exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Passive-solar-house-in-priene-greece_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Passive solar house in Ancient Greece.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Passive solar house in Ancient Greece. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Olynthus-street-plan_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Street plan of the Ancient Greek City Olynthus.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Street plan of the Ancient Greek City Olynthus. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A gridirion street plan oriented at the cardinal points was not new at the time, and neither is it proof of a design aimed at maximum solar exposure. But the Greeks did more. In &amp;ldquo;*&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0442240058/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;A Golden Thread: 2500 Years of Solar Architecture and Technology&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Ken Butti and John Perlin note that all houses were consistently built around a south-facing courtyard:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;The houses that faced south on the street and south to the sun were entered through the court, straight from the street. The houses that faced north to the street and south to the sun were entered through a passageway that led from the street through the main body of the house and into the court, from which access was gained to all other spaces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the democratic ethos of the period, the height of buildings was strictly limited so that each courtyard received an equal amount of sunshine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;In winter, rays from the sun traveling low across the southern sky streamed across the south-facing courts, throgh the portico, and into the house - heating the main rooms. The north walls were made of adobe bricks one and a half feet thick, which kept out the cold north winds of winter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Priene-Solar-Oriented-City_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Ancient Greek city of Priene.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Ancient Greek city of Priene. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another obvious example of Ancient Greek solar planning was Priene (illustration above), rebuilt in 350 BC and located in present-day Turkey. The city had about 4000 inhabitants living in 400 houses. Its buildings and street plan were similar to those in Olynthus, but because the city was built on the slope of a steep mountain, many of the fifteen secondary streets (running north-south) were actually stairways. The seven main avenues were terraced on an east-west axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;native-americans&#34;&gt;Native Americans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ancient Pueblo People or &amp;ldquo;Anasazi&amp;rdquo; built a number of sophisticated solar oriented communities during the 11th and 12th centuries AD in what is now the Southwestern United States: Long House at Mesa Verde, Pueblo Bonito in Northern Mexico and the &amp;ldquo;sky city&amp;rdquo; of Acoma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These communities followed a different building style than that of the Greeks. The Ancient Pueblo People constructed terraced buildings of up to three floors high. These were buildings that would fit perfectly in a solar envelope with slanting lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Drawing-by-Gary-Shigemura-in-from-Energy-and-form-ralph-knowls_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Illustration of Acoma Pueblo, by Gary S. Shigemura (from &amp;amp;quot;Energy and Form&amp;amp;quot;, Ralph Knowles).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Illustration of Acoma Pueblo, by Gary S. Shigemura (from \&#34;Energy and Form\&#34;, Ralph Knowles). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acoma pueblo (illustration above) is one example of these orderly, solar planned communities. It consists of three rows of houses built along streets running east and west, so that each building faces south. The streets that separate the houses have a width that allows winter shadows to cover the whole of the adjoining street, stopping  just before the following row of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;heliodon&#34;&gt;Heliodon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowles&amp;rsquo; research combines the best elements of these historical designs and incorporates modern technology that greatly facilitates the generation of a solar envelope. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hpd-online.com/heliodons.php&#34;&gt;heliodon&lt;/a&gt;, invented in the 1930s, is a contraption that creates a geometrical relationship between an architectural scale model and (a representation of) the sun.  More recently, software versions of the heliodon have made the technology much more affordable, while allowing for the fast generation of even very complex solar envelopes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Solar-houses-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration by Diego Marmolejo for Low-tech Magazine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration by [Diego Marmolejo](http://ddidak.blogspot.com.es/) for Low-tech Magazine. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On larger sites in particular, and when already existing buildings complicate the generation of a solar envelope, the available computer software saves time and can result in more building volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continue reading: 1 / &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-2/&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;/ &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels-part-3/&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/1597260509/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;Ritual House: Drawing on Nature&amp;rsquo;s Rhythms for Architecture and     Urban     Design&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Ralph L. Knowles, 2006.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/026261040X/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;Sun Rhythm     Form&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Ralph L. Knowles, 1981&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0262610256/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;Energy and Form: An Ecological Approach to Urban     Growth&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Ralph L. Knowles, 1974&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0442240058/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;A Golden Thread: 2500 Years of Solar Architecture and     Technology&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Ken Butti and John Perlin, 1981, reprinted in 2009&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.archive.org/details/orientationofbui00atki&#34;&gt;The orientation of buildings, or planning for     sunlight&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
William Atkinson, 1912&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.anycerda.org/web/arxiu-cerda&#34;&gt;Teoría general de la urbanización y aplicación de sus principios y     doctrinas a la reforma y ensanche de     Barcelona&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Ildefons Cerdà
i Sunyer, 1867&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ildefonso_Cerd%C3%A1&#34;&gt;Ildefonso     Cerdá&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distrito_del_Ensanche&#34;&gt;Distrito del     Ensanche&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; &amp;amp;
&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plan_Cerd%C3%A1&#34;&gt;Plan Cerdá&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
Wikipedia Spanish -   &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.comd/dp/1593761031/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;Walks Through Lost Paris: A Journey Into the Heart of Historic     Paris&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Leonard Pitt, 2006&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inive.org/members_area/medias/pdf/Inive%5Cpalenc%5C2005%5CMofidi.pdf&#34;&gt;Responsive and sustainable architectural strategies for temperate     regions&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;,
S.M. Mofidi, 2005 (PDF) -   &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0300042124/?tag=lowtemagaz-20&#34;&gt;The City as a Work of Art: London, Paris,     Vienna&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Donald J. Olsen, 1986&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Spanish city planning in North America&amp;rdquo;, Dora Crouch, Daniel Garr,     Axel Mundigo, 1982&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.densityatlas.org/&#34;&gt;The Density Atlas&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, MIT (website) -   &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=9&amp;amp;cts=1331076526613&amp;amp;ved=0CHIQFjAI&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.pbcgov.com%2Fcountycommissioners%2Fdistrict4%2Fbrinybreezes%2Fpdf%2FVisualizing_Density.pdf&amp;amp;ei=e51WT5HGF8LG0QWgia3jCQ&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNESNlbyNiqJIQ5_wQQPNQVDhWKsMA&amp;amp;sig2=lA1jmFqhKNDt8tGToELhZw&#34;&gt;Visualizing     density&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;
(PDF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
