<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>/tags/solar-power/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline </description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/solar-power/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Direct Solar Power: Off-Grid Without Batteries</title>
      <link>/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-solar-office_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="48549" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-solar-office_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: a laptop running on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: a laptop running on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional solar installations do not question our dependence on fossil fuels and the energy-guzzling lifestyle that results. Both rooftop solar panels and large-scale solar farms provide us with all the power we want, even when the sun is not shining. That is because these systems use the central power grid, which largely runs on fossil fuels, as a kind of battery to cope with power shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although grid-connected solar panels can reduce the fossil fuel consumption of thermal power plants, these savings are at least partly offset by the additional fossil fuels required to build and maintain what is essentially a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;dual energy infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;. Combining solar and wind power can further increase the share of renewable energy in the power grid, but this requires further infrastructure development. Apart from energy, this also demands a lot of money and time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replacing fossil-fuel-fired power plants with energy storage, so that surplus electricity generated on sunny days can be stored for when there is no or insufficient sun, encounters the same problem. Energy storage, whether integrated into a power grid or located at individual households (off-grid systems), is very expensive and &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2015/05/how-sustainable-is-stored-sunlight/&#34;&gt;carbon-intensive to build and maintain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;autonomous-solar-installation&#34;&gt;Autonomous solar installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The production of solar panels obviously &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2015/04/how-sustainable-is-pv-solar-power/&#34;&gt;costs money and energy&lt;/a&gt;. However, the financial and energy costs of the associated back-up infrastructure are many times higher. For grid-connected solar installations, these costs are very difficult to calculate precisely, but for autonomous solar installations (without grid connection and with their own energy storage) it is a lot easier. As an example, I will therefore take the small autonomous solar installation that powers my living room in Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system consists of two 50W solar panels on the balcony, a 100 Ah lead-acid battery and a 10A charge controller. The energy generated is used for lighting, the music system, and charging laptops and other electronic devices, among other things. The initial financial investment was 340 euros: 120 euros for the solar panels, 170 euros for the battery and 50 euros for the charge controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while the solar panels should last 30 years and the charge controller about 10 years, I have to replace the lead battery on average every three to five years. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Over a 30-year lifespan, the costs then amount to €120 for the solar panels, €150 for the charge controllers and – in the best case scenario – €1,020 for the batteries. The batteries (and associated charge controllers) therefore account for about 90% of the total lifetime costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy storage also dominates the plant&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;embedded&amp;rdquo; energy (and resulting carbon emissions). Producing my lead-acid battery took 1,200 megajoules (MJ) of energy. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Over a 30-year lifetime (six batteries at best), that equates to 7,200 MJ. The three charge controllers add another 360 MJ over a 30-year lifetime, bringing the total energy consumption for the battery system to 7,560 MJ. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In contrast, the production of the solar panels costs only 2,275 MJ out of a total of 9,835 MJ. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Conclusion: more than 75% of total fossil energy consumption is due to energy storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/balcony-system-from-outside_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: To the right on the balcony are the two 50W solar panels that power my flat&amp;amp;rsquo;s living room. Next to it is the 30W solar panel that makes this website work. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: To the right on the balcony are the two 50W solar panels that power my flat&#39;s living room. Next to it is the 30W solar panel that makes this website work. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/structure-for-solar-panels-balcony_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The structure for the solar panels, built from waste wood. Photo: Kris De Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The structure for the solar panels, built from waste wood. Photo: Kris De Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/100ah-battery_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The 100 Ah lead-acid battery powering the living room after sunset. Photo: Kris De Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The 100 Ah lead-acid battery powering the living room after sunset. Photo: Kris De Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other types of batteries would not significantly change this conclusion. For a comparable off-grid system with lithium-ion batteries, energy storage would account for about 95% of the total lifetime cost (which is almost double that of a system with lead-acid batteries). Assuming an optimistic lifetime (10 years) and including charge controllers, lithium energy storage accounts for some 70% of the energy invested in a solar grid system. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For nickel-iron batteries, energy storage would account for 85% of the total lifetime cost (there are no energy cost data). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scale and location of the solar installation also make no difference. A larger system needs more solar panels, but also larger batteries and more expensive and powerful charge controllers. The ratios remain the same. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The only factor that may give the solar panels a slightly larger share of the total cost is the structures on which they are mounted. I don&amp;rsquo;t take this into account because I built them myself from waste wood. However, if the solar panels are mounted on a roof, a DIY solution is less obvious. But even in that case, the cost of energy storage remains by far the biggest consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;direct-solar-energy-much-cheaper-and-more-sustainable&#34;&gt;Direct solar energy: much cheaper and more sustainable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike fossil fuels, the sun and wind are not available on demand. The problem with our approach to renewable energy is that we &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/&#34;&gt;insist that power should always be infinitely available&lt;/a&gt;, regardless of the weather, seasons or time of day. Matching energy demand to supply – &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/&#34;&gt;as was done in the past&lt;/a&gt; – would lead to dramatic reductions in the cost and use of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if I omitted the battery storage of my solar installation, my system would become about 10 times cheaper: 120 euros instead of 1,290 euros over a 30-year lifetime. Alternatively, I could spend 1,290 euros on solar panels alone, which would give me a solar system of 1,075 watts. That&amp;rsquo;s ten times the capacity of the setup with batteries, more than what would fit on the balcony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the battery and charge controller, the energy cost of the installation also drops from 9,835 MJ to 2,275 MJ. In other words, I could generate at least four times as much solar energy with the same investment in fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-direct-solar-power-be-practical&#34;&gt;How can direct solar power be practical?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All well and good, but the sun does not shine after sunset and the amount of solar energy varies throughout the day and year. So how then can using solar panels without batteries (or other back-up infrastructure in the case of grid-connected installations) be practical?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, we look at a pioneer of &amp;ldquo;direct solar power&amp;rdquo;: the &lt;em&gt;Living Energy Farm&lt;/em&gt;. This environmental education community in the US state of Virginia is completely &amp;ldquo;off-the-grid&amp;rdquo; thanks to solar power, but only 10% of the solar power generated passes through a (nickel-iron) battery. However, the solar panels provide power for several homes, a communal kitchen, a metal workshop, and a farm. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/living-energy-farm-map_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: direct solar power at the Living Energy Farm.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: direct solar power at the Living Energy Farm. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar installation has been in operation since 2011 and consists of separate systems with a total peak power of 1,400 watts. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In comparison, the average peak power of a residential solar installation in the UK and the US – for one household – is 4,000 watts and 6,500 watts, respectively. As in my flat, the Living Energy Farm uses energy sparingly, but the fact that hardly any batteries are used has other reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-appliances-are-only-used-during-the-day&#34;&gt;Some appliances are only used during the day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first reason is obvious: some electrical appliances and machines are only used during the day. This is true, for example, of all machines in the metal workshop, including a band saw, compressor, grinder, circular saw, lathe, milling machine and drilling machine. It also applies to agricultural machinery such as a grain mill and a deep well pump. Linked directly to solar panels, these machines offer all the capabilities of modern grid-powered technology, with the exception that they can only be used during the day. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a much smaller scale, I have used direct solar power for a soldering iron, glue gun and irrigation pump (for the balcony) at home. Other examples of appliances and machines that could be used only during the day include hoovers, sewing machines, washing machines, game consoles, laser cutters and 3D printers. It is not so difficult to imagine a modern society where activities such as vacuuming and DIY chores only take place during the day. It is certainly not a return to the Middle Ages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/shop-tools-living-energy-farm_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: several workshop tools at the Living Energy Farm, most of them run on direct solar power. Image: Alexis Zeigler.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: several workshop tools at the Living Energy Farm, most of them run on direct solar power. Image: Alexis Zeigler. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/metal-lathe-living-energy-farm_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Metal lathe running on direct solar power, Living Energy Farm. Image: Alexis Zeigler.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Metal lathe running on direct solar power, Living Energy Farm. Image: Alexis Zeigler. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-soldering-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Soldering with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. Watch the video.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Soldering with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. [Watch the video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qozZCJU4IOc). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, not all electrical appliances require constant attention. Washing machines or dishwashers that trigger automatically when the sun shines are often cited example applications of a &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; power grid. But that approach relies on an extensive infrastructure of electricity transmission, communication networks, and electronics-packed appliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, in a decentralised direct solar approach, the intelligence is provided by the sun and the rotation of the planet. A direct solar-powered washing machine or dishwasher can be fully charged and switched on in the evening. The machine then starts up &amp;ldquo;automatically&amp;rdquo; in the morning. You can even use timers (electronic or mechanical) to run different appliances one after the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether clouds pose an additional limit to a direct solar installation, and to what extent, depends on the size of the solar panels. Doubling the area of solar panels guarantees sufficient solar power during moderate cloud cover, while the installation remains much cheaper and more sustainable than a system with batteries or other backup infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An even larger area of solar panels could provide sufficient energy even during heavy cloud cover, but increasing the size of the system tenfold brings the cost back to the level of an autonomous system with batteries. Quadrupling the area makes the system equally dependent on fossil fuels again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;many-appliances-already-have-batteries&#34;&gt;Many appliances already have batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Direct solar power does not rule out the use of electrical appliances after sunset either. As mentioned, the Living Energy Farm has a modest battery system, providing power for lights, fans, and electronic devices after sunset, among other things.  &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In addition, many modern appliances already have built-in energy storage. This is the case for all kinds of electric vehicles, for most electronic gadgets, and for older electrical appliances with AA batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, these types of devices can be charged with direct solar energy during the day and then used for several hours after sunset thanks to the built-in battery. Combined with a lithium-ion power bank, a direct solar panel can also make it possible to charge USB devices after sunset. This strategy can even work for lighting, as there are many battery-powered lamps that you can use as modern torches, hung in different parts of rooms and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/solar-phone-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A mobile phone on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A mobile phone on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, outsourcing chemical energy storage to the device is not the most sustainable option. The production of lithium-ion batteries requires fossil fuels, and (unlike lead-acid batteries) they are not recycled. The best solution, of course, is to reduce the use of electrical devices. But charging them with direct solar energy is a lot more sustainable and efficient than via other batteries or a fossil-fueled electricity grid. If we use high-tech devices, then preferably in the smartest way possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;non-electric-energy-storage&#34;&gt;Non-electric energy storage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third reason why direct solar power is more practical than it initially seems is that some electrical appliances can be used after sunset thanks to thermal energy storage. This is much cheaper and more sustainable than electrical energy storage. Thermal energy storage is already fairly well established for space and water heating systems, which store solar-heated water in an insulated boiler or (for space heating only) in the building envelope. It is no surprise that the Living Energy Farm has such systems, and solar thermal energy also provides hot water in my flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the same approach also works for two important household appliances that need to work after sunset and also consume a lot of electricity: the fridge and the cooker. Instead of storing electricity from a solar panel in a battery to then power a fridge or cooker after sunset, these appliances on the Living Energy Farm use thermal insulation. This keeps the heat inside (in the case of the cooker) or outside (in the case of the fridge) when there is no power supply. The thermal insulation also ensures very high energy efficiency, which means that each of these appliances can already operate on a solar panel of just 100-200 watts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-direct-solar-powered-fridge&#34;&gt;A direct solar-powered fridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is perfectly possible to connect a conventional fridge or freezer directly to a solar panel, but such an appliance would heat up very quickly at night. Even refrigerators with the most energy-efficient labels have a relatively limited insulation thickness (usually 2.5 cm). However, if that insulation thickness is increased to about 12.5 cm, the energy consumption of a refrigerator drops by a factor of four. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The passive cooling capacity of a refrigerator can be further increased by adding thermal mass in the form of a water tank inside the appliance. During the day, the solar panel cools the water or converts it to ice. At night, this cold water or ice slows down the heating of the refrigerator. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A direct solar-powered fridge also opens at the top, not at the front. Cold air is heavy, and so much less energy is lost that way when someone opens the door. All these design choices add up to spectacular energy efficiency. A study of direct solar refrigerators in very sunny regions (Texas and New Mexico, USA) showed that they maintained their cooling capacity for 6 or 7 days without power supply. The units operated year-round with solar panels of only 80W to 120W. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Living Energy Farm powers its solar refrigerator with a 200W panel. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/sundanzer-direct-solar-fridge_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Sundanzer DDR165. A refrigerator designed specifically for direct solar power. Photo: Sundanzer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Sundanzer DDR165. A refrigerator designed specifically for direct solar power. Photo: Sundanzer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike solar heating, solar cooling is optimally tuned to seasonal variations in solar radiation. Cooling requires more energy in summer, when there is more solar energy. The aforementioned refrigerator in New Mexico recorded electricity consumption of 406 watt-hours per day in summer and only 230 watt-hours in winter. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Moreover, the technology can be used throughout the cold chain, of which the household refrigerator is only a small (but essential) part. Another application is air cooling, although this is less well researched and more challenging. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-direct-solar-electric-cooker&#34;&gt;A direct solar electric cooker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle, a conventional cooker can also be connected directly to a solar panel, but as with a conventional fridge, it is not very practical. You can only cook during the day, and you have to install a lot of solar panels. A single hot plate needs 1,000 watts of electrical power. A solar electric cooker solves these problems by packing the cooktop with thermal insulation. The technology is basically a combination of an electric cooktop and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/&#34;&gt;haybox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/test-isec-thermal-energy-storage_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Test of an electric solar cooker. Photo: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Test of an electric solar cooker. Photo: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to thermal insulation, an electric solar cooker slowly accumulates heat during the day, which can then be used for cooking after sunset. In this way, a much lower power supply can be sufficient to achieve high temperatures. Think of it as &amp;ldquo;charging&amp;rdquo; your cooker, not with electricity but with heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers at US California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly) built the first solar electric cooker in 2015. Their 12-volt device, which has since been further developed, needs only a 100W solar panel to work. It boils a litre of water in an hour. With a full day of sunlight, it can cook almost 5 kg of beans, rice, stew or potatoes. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooking after sunset is possible by using a cooking pot with a much thicker bottom (5-10 kg). Cal Poly&amp;rsquo;s research team managed to bring the temperature of that solid heat storage to 250°C in five hours with a 100W solar panel. They were then able to boil a litre of water in three seconds after sunset. In another test, they stir-fried 1 kg of vegetables in two minutes. The ideal configuration consists of two cooking pots: one with and one without heat storage. Thus, an electric solar cooker can cook both slowly and quickly, depending on the time of day and the dish. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/cal-poly-solar-electric-cooker-idea_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The principle of a solar electric cooker with solid heat storage. Drawing: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The principle of a solar electric cooker with solid heat storage. Drawing: California Polytechnic State University (Cal Poly). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thermal-or-electric&#34;&gt;Thermal or electric?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like solar water and space heating systems, cooking and cooling can work both with and without electricity – with PV panels on the one hand and solar thermal collectors on the other. But while solar space and water heating are more cost- and energy-efficient without electricity, for solar cooling and solar cooking it is just the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space and water heating require relatively small temperature differences, which can be provided by low-cost solar thermal collectors made of glass plates and water pipes. In contrast, cooling and cooking require larger temperature differences, which require more sophisticated (vacuum tube or parabolic) solar collectors – and these are more expensive than PV panels. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only exception is a simple solar cooker – an insulated box with a glass top – but it cannot achieve such high temperatures. Moreover, an electric solar cooker has some additional advantages. With a non-electric appliance, you have to cook outside, which is less practical but also less efficient, especially in winter: a thermal solar cooker will lose more heat to the environment. An electric solar cooker is also more energy-efficient because it is insulated on all sides. It also works better in cloudy weather and can be used after sunset. At the Living Energy Farm, the parabolic solar cooker is only used in optimal conditions – at full sun and high outdoor temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-the-technical-challenges&#34;&gt;What are the technical challenges?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the Living Energy Farm is putting all these applications of direct solar energy into practice, there are some technical challenges for those who want to follow suit. Almost all our modern technology is designed to operate with a stable and uninterrupted power supply. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be that way, but for now, direct solar power usually requires some tinkering. A direct solar system is much easier to build than an autonomous system with batteries, but it often requires modifications on the appliance side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some devices can be connected directly to a solar panel: it is enough to connect the positive and negative contacts of the solar panel and the device. For example, machines with a DC motor tolerate large fluctuations in the power supply. The metal workshop and agricultural machinery at the Living Energy Farm work this way. If clouds block the sun, the combined electrical load can become greater than the power supply from the solar panels, but this does not stop the machines. All the engines will slow down because they share the available energy, but they all continue to do useful work. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same applies to all appliances that work on the basis of resistive heating elements, such as kettles, hotplates or electric heating systems. They work regardless of power or voltage, just slower or faster. A direct solar-powered fridge preferably operates on a variable DC compressor, which can adjust its speed according to the varying solar power production. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many other devices need a specific and stable voltage input, which usually does not match what the solar panel produces. This can be solved by placing a DC-DC converter (a &amp;ldquo;buck&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;boost&amp;rdquo; converter) between the solar panel and the device. This is a small electronic module that converts the fluctuating voltage of a solar panel into a constant output voltage for a low-voltage device (5V, 12V or higher). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/solar-behind-the-scenes-3_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Experiments with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Experiments with direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use an inverter in addition to this, even mains appliances can operate directly on a solar panel. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; DC-DC converters are essential for all appliances that contain electronic components. This is the case for many appliances today, including those, such as washing machines or coffee machines, that until recently operated without electronics. That often gives you two options to run such appliances on direct solar power. You can either fit a DC-DC converter or modify the appliance by bypassing the electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;diy-manuals--commercial-devices&#34;&gt;DIY manuals &amp;amp; commercial devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most direct solar power applications &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&#34;&gt;operate at low voltage&lt;/a&gt;, so you can safely do it yourself. Low-tech Magazine will soon publish a manual on this. However, the Living Energy Farm uses direct current with higher voltages for a number of applications. Examples are the machine tools in the metal workshop (90V) and a number of powerful electric solar cookers (48V, 180V). It is not a good idea to build these systems yourself unless you have the help of a qualified electrician, as these voltages can lead to fatal accidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those wishing to build their own (low-voltage) electric solar cookers will find comprehensive manuals at both Living Energy Farm and Cal Poly. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The devices can be made with simple materials. The insulation material should be fireproof. Example materials are rock wool, fibreglass, natural wool or clay.goed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different technologies can be used for heating elements, but embedding nichrome wires in cement is the simplest option. These wires can be taken from a variety of appliances such as toasters, ovens and hotplates. In principle, the heating wires can be attached directly to the cooking pot, but it is more practical to make a heated &amp;ldquo;nest&amp;rdquo; in which a pot can be placed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/roxy-solar-oven_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Inspired by Cal Poly&amp;amp;rsquo;s work, Living Energy Farm also developed a number of electric solar cookers, one of which they offer for sale through their website. The Roxy Oven can be used as a hotplate or an oven, for example for baking bread. The door also remains closed when used as a hot plate. This solar cooker has no energy storage.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Inspired by Cal Poly&#39;s work, Living Energy Farm also developed a number of electric solar cookers, one of which they [offer for sale through their website](https://livingenergylights.com/product/roxy-solar-electric-oven/). The Roxy Oven can be used as a hotplate or an oven, for example for baking bread. The door also remains closed when used as a hot plate. This solar cooker has no energy storage. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/roxy-deluxe-without-door_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Roxy Oven without the door and with the glass wool insulation visible. The device - made in the metal workshop with direct solar power - runs on 48V and requires a solar panel of 200 to 500 watts. Living Energy Farm also offers Sunstar&amp;amp;rsquo;s solar refrigerator for sale online.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Roxy Oven without the door and with the glass wool insulation visible. The device - made in the metal workshop with direct solar power - runs on 48V and requires a solar panel of 200 to 500 watts. Living Energy Farm also offers Sunstar&#39;s solar refrigerator [for sale online](https://livingenergylights.com/product/sunstar-direct-drive-8-cuft-chest-style-refrigerator-freezer/). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;does-direct-solar-power-waste-energy&#34;&gt;Does direct solar power waste energy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sustainability of a solar installation depends not only on the energy required to produce and maintain the infrastructure, but also on the energy produced by the solar panels during their lifetime. Some people will argue that direct use of solar power is inferior to conventional grid-connected or battery-powered solar installations in this respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, the hoover, washing machine and power drill are not used every day, and if no electrical appliance is connected then a solar panel will not produce power either. Consequently, the amount of electricity produced by the panel will decrease over its lifetime, while the energy needed to manufacture the panel remains the same. This makes the power from a direct solar panel more carbon-intensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, because energy storage in batteries (or the grid-connected alternative) accounts for such a large proportion of the total energy invested, a standalone solar panel can waste quite a lot of energy before it becomes less sustainable than its counterpart with battery storage or grid connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, direct use of solar power avoids the charging and discharging losses caused by batteries, or the energy losses in the transmission infrastructure for grid-connected systems. Both have to be offset by additional solar panels. Furthermore, solar panels connected to batteries or the grid also waste power – a consequence of the large difference in energy production between summer and winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maximising-direct-solar-power-with-collective-services&#34;&gt;Maximising direct solar power with collective services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it is important to maximise the energy production of a direct solar panel. In that context, it is useful to return for a moment to the original example system located on my balcony. Direct solar power could be a nice addition to this system, especially for the fridge and cooker. It was because of these appliances that I &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/&#34;&gt;concluded in 2016 that it was impossible to completely disconnect my flat from the grid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the Living Energy Farm shows that it could be done: there is room for a further 200 watts of solar panels (4 x 50W) on the balcony, enough to power both a thermally insulated fridge and hob. Additional battery capacity would not be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other appliances, however, direct solar power is of little use in my case. It would not be very efficient to install an extra solar panel for the washing machine or the power drill, as they are only used occasionally. This seems to play into the hands of a &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; electricity grid, because that way many households can use the same solar power – there is always someone who needs to wash clothes or drill a hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, such a smart grid does require a lot of infrastructure, even if direct solar power were to be used at that scale. It may not require batteries or fossil fuels as backup, but it does require transmission and communication infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2023/08/direct-solar-power-off-grid-without-batteries/images/dithers/direct-solar-record-player_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A record player on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. Watch the video.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A record player on direct solar power. Photo: Marie Verdeil. [Watch the video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_LjSigJv0-0). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Living Energy Farm demonstrates an alternative solution: the communal organisation of household tasks and work. Instead of a communal power grid distributing energy to many indidvidual households, we can set up collective services with decentralised energy production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Living Energy Farm communal workshop, direct solar power can be used much more efficiently than in an individual workshop that is only used occasionally. A collective laundry in each street would also use direct solar power much more efficiently. Moreover, we save a lot of energy on building appliances this way, and gain a lot of space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;direct-wind-power&#34;&gt;Direct wind power?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strategy becomes even more important if we choose not direct solar power but direct wind power – or a combination of both. The Living Energy Farm is located in a sunny region, but the same approach could also work in windy places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is an important difference between solar power and wind power. The efficiency of a solar panel does not depend on its size, which makes solar power ideal for decentralised energy production. In contrast, the efficiency of a wind turbine &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2009/04/small-windmills-put-to-the-test/&#34;&gt;increases more than proportionally as the rotor diameter increases&lt;/a&gt;. Much better than one wind turbine per household, therefore, is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2019/06/reinventing-the-small-wind-turbine/&#34;&gt;somewhat larger wind turbine&lt;/a&gt; for a community of households, e.g. for powering a collective laundry or workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service life of lead-acid batteries depends on many factors. If they are discharged too deeply or are not fully charged regularly, the service life can be shorter than three years. On the other hand, a lead-acid battery that is hardly used or not discharged at all can last much longer than five years. However, the academic literature states a life expectancy of three to five years and this has also been my experience with the batteries I have used since 2016. See, for example, &amp;ldquo;Optimal Sizing and Life Cycle Assessment of Residential Photovoltaic Energy Systems With Battery Storage&amp;rdquo;, A. Celik, in &amp;ldquo;Progress in Photovoltaics: Research and Applications&amp;rdquo;, 2008. &amp;amp; &amp;ldquo;Energy pay-back time of photovoltaic energy systems: present status and prospects&amp;rdquo;, E.A. Alsema, in &amp;ldquo;Proceedings of the 2nd World Conference and Exhibition on photovoltaics solar energy conversion&amp;rdquo;, July 1998.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing a lead-acid battery (based on largely recycled materials) takes about 1 MJ of energy per watt-hour of storage capacity. My 100 amp-hour battery equates to a storage capacity of 1,200 watt-hours, and so the embedded energy equals 1,200 MJ. Over a 30-year lifespan, I need six of these batteries at best, so 7,200 MJ in total. Source: &amp;ldquo;Energy Analysis of Batteries in Photovoltaic systems. Part one (Performance and energy requirements)&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Part two (Energy Return Factors and Overall Battery Efficiencies)&amp;rdquo; (PDF). Energy Conversion and Management 46, 2005.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much research has been done on the embedded energy of charge controllers. The most relevant data I found is a value of 1 MJ per watt maximum power: Kim, Bunthern, et al. &amp;ldquo;Life cycle assessment for a solar energy system based on reuse components for developing countries.&amp;rdquo; Journal of cleaner production 208 (2019): 1459-1468. For a capacity of 120W (my charge controller has a maximum capacity of 10A x 12V = 120W), this amounts to 120 MJ. For the estimated lifetime, I found values of 7 and 12.5 years: same reference as above, as well as: Kim, Bunthern, et al. &amp;ldquo;Second life of power supply unit as charge controller in PV system and environmental benefit assessment.&amp;rdquo; IECON 2016-42nd Annual Conference of the IEEE Industrial Electronics Society. IEEE, 2016. I therefore made the calculation on an estimated lifetime of 10 years.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nawaz, I., and G. N. Tiwari. &amp;ldquo;Embodied energy analysis of photovoltaic (PV) system based on macro-and micro-level.&amp;rdquo; Energy Policy 34.17 (2006): 3144-3152. According to this widely quoted source, it takes 3,500 MJ to produce 1 m2 of solar panel. My two solar panels together measure 0.65 m2, representing a total energy cost of 2,275 MJ. A more recent literature review puts the energy cost for producing different types of solar panels at between 1,034 and 5,150 MJ/m2. The most recent studies of silicon solar panels in this review put the energy cost at around 1,000 MJ/m2, much lower than the figure I am using. See: Ludin, Norasikin Ahmad, et al. &amp;ldquo;Prospects of life cycle assessment of renewable energy from solar photovoltaic technologies: A review.&amp;rdquo; Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 96 (2018): 11-28.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lithium-ion batteries are a lot more expensive than lead-acid batteries, but unlike lead-acid batteries, they can be discharged deeper (up to 15% of their total capacity) and have a longer lifespan (7 to 10 years). Consequently, fewer and smaller batteries are needed. Taking these factors into account, the lifetime cost of the battery is €750, compared with €1,020 for lead-acid batteries. On the other hand, lithium-ion batteries require a more sophisticated and more expensive charge controller: a 10A charge controller costs between 200 and 600 euros, depending on the quality. Assuming a price of 400 euros for the charge controller and a 10-year lifetime for both the battery and the charge controller, battery storage accounts for 95% of the total lifetime cost (a total of 2,070 euros, much more than the total cost for the system with lead-acid batteries). Sources: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/product/12v-50ah-lithium-ion-battery&#34;&gt;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/product/12v-50ah-lithium-ion-battery&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/12v-lithium-ion-battery-chargers/&#34;&gt;https://www.lithiumion-batteries.com/products/12v-lithium-ion-battery-chargers/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the production of a lithium-ion battery costs more energy than the production of a lead-acid battery (1.4-1.9 MJ/Wh versus 1 MJ/Wh), this is offset by a longer lifespan and greater discharge capacity. The energy cost of lithium-ion batteries over a 30-year lifetime is then about 3,000 MJ, significantly less than a comparable lead-acid battery system. In contrast, the charge controller contains more complex electronics. Unfortunately, no data is available for the energy cost of such a charge controller. So there is no alternative but to estimate the energy cost based on the financial cost, which is four to twelve times more expensive than a charge controller for a lead-acid battery. Assuming a four times higher cost, the embedded energy of the charge controller increases to 480 MJ, or 1,440 MJ over a 30-year period. The total energy cost for the system is then 6,685 MJ, less than a comparable system with lead-acid batteries. Of this, almost 70% is attributable to battery storage.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nickel-iron batteries are even bigger and heavier than lead-acid batteries and they need regular maintenance. But they can be fully discharged and have a very long service life (20 years). Moreover, they can be used with the same charge controllers as lead-acid batteries. The lifetime cost over 30 years for the battery is €750, cheaper than the six lead-acid batteries of similar capacity. The total lifetime cost for a nickel-iron battery system with 100W solar panels is €1,020, of which 85% goes to energy storage. Unfortunately, nickel-iron batteries are hard to find, especially the smaller models. Sources: &lt;a href=&#34;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product/nickel-iron-battery-industrial-series/&#34;&gt;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product/nickel-iron-battery-industrial-series/&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product-category/batteries/nickel-iron/&#34;&gt;https://beyondoilsolar.com/product-category/batteries/nickel-iron/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the price of solar panels in a somewhat larger solar installation would be proportionally even smaller. This is because solar panels with small sizes (such as 50W) are proportionally more expensive per watt of peak capacity than solar panels with more conventional sizes (from 250W onwards). More or less the same applies to the energy cost.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://livingenergyfarm.org&#34;&gt;https://livingenergyfarm.org&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexis Zeigler, founder of the Living Energy Farm, wrote a book about the project, which is available in full online: &lt;a href=&#34;https://conev.org/empoweringcommunities14.pdf&#34;&gt;Empowering Communities. A Practical Guide to Energy Self Sufficiency and Stopping Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. It can also be &lt;a href=&#34;https://conev.org/&#34;&gt;ordered in hard copy&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since direct solar power does not require a charge controller for each separate system, splitting up a solar system does not involve any additional costs or energy consumption.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research shows that doubling the insulation thickness from 2.5 cm (standard insulation) to 5 cm reduces the annual electricity consumption of a refrigerator (50 litre capacity) from 250 to 125 kilowatt hours. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; With an insulation thickness of 10 to 12.5 cm, electricity consumption halves again to around 60 kilowatt hours per year. Even thicker insulation brings a smaller reduction in electricity consumption and is no longer attractive because thicker insulation also increases the cost and size of the refrigerator. The study concerns a solar-powered AC fridge that operates thanks to an inverter and a battery, which is less energy-efficient than a direct solar-powered fridge.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gupta, B. L., Mayank Bhatnagar, and Jyotirmay Mathur. &amp;ldquo;Optimum sizing of PV panel, battery capacity and insulation thickness for a photovoltaic operated domestic refrigerator.&amp;rdquo; Sustainable Energy Technologies and Assessments 7 (2014): 55-67.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thermal mass can literally be a container of water placed inside the fridge. or some water bottles for drinking. But the water can also be stored in reservoirs along the side of the appliance, behind an inner lining that keeps them in place and hides them from view. Water has a higher heat storage density than air, keeping the temperature stable for longer.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ewert, M., et al. &amp;ldquo;Photovoltaic direct drive, battery-free solar refrigerator field test results.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings of the solar conference. American solar energy society; American institute of architects, 2002.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This advantage only applies if the fridge is set up in an unheated room. The modern habit of placing a fridge in a heated kitchen when the outside temperature in winter is equal or lower than that in the fridge is obviously absurdly wasteful. But neither is this advantage valid in tropical countries, where temperatures are high all year round.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of direct solar power for space cooling has not been analysed as thoroughly as for domestic refrigerators. See: Luerssen, Christoph, et al. &amp;ldquo;Life cycle cost analysis (LCCA) of PV-powered cooling systems with thermal energy and battery storage for off-grid applications.&amp;rdquo; Applied energy 273 (2020): 115145. Moreover, it is unlikely to achieve equally large energy savings. A refrigerator is always insulated, but in the case of an air-cooled room or building, this is not necessarily the case. Moreover, a refrigerator is set up in a room where there is a stable temperature. A building is subject to greater temperature fluctuations and can also be heated by direct solar radiation. So direct solar air cooling is a lot more complicated. See: Qi, Ronghui, Lin Lu, and Yu Huang. &amp;ldquo;Parameter analysis and optimisation of the energy and economic performance of solar-assisted liquid desiccant cooling system under different climate conditions.&amp;rdquo; Energy conversion and management 106 (2015): 1387-1395.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sharedcurriculum.peteschwartz.net/solar-electric-cooking/&#34;&gt;Solar Electric Cooking&lt;/a&gt;, Pete Schwartz, Cal Poly Physics. See also &lt;a href=&#34;http://sharedcurriculum.peteschwartz.net/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2022/11/New-ISEC-Design-Ideas.pdf&#34;&gt;this PowerPoint&lt;/a&gt; by the same author.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1747&amp;amp;context=mesp&#34;&gt;Insulated Solar Electric Cooker with Solid Thermal Storage&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew McCombs et al., 2022. See also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FKIH7HDK6Dw&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See: Ferreira, Carlos Infante, and Dong-Seon Kim. &amp;ldquo;Techno-economic review of solar cooling technologies based on location-specific data.&amp;rdquo; International Journal of Refrigeration 39 (2014): 23-37. ///// Riffat, James, et al. &amp;ldquo;Development and testing of a PCM enhanced domestic refrigerator with use of miniature DC compressor for weak/off grid locations.&amp;rdquo; International Journal of Green Energy 19.10 (2022): 1118-1131. ///// Du, Wenping, et al. &amp;ldquo;Dynamic energy efficiency characteristics analysis of a distributed solar photovoltaic direct-drive solar cold storage.&amp;rdquo; Building and Environment 206 (2021): 108324. ///// Alsagri, Ali Sulaiman. &amp;ldquo;Photovoltaic and photovoltaic thermal technologies for refrigeration purposes: an overview.&amp;rdquo; Arabian journal for science and engineering 47.7 (2022): 7911-7944.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lack of research, whether the same applies to embedded energy consumption is not clear.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, however, it is necessary to bypass the device&amp;rsquo;s switch, because DC electricity produces more heat than AC electricity. Instead, a suitable external switch can help, but in doing so you bypass the device&amp;rsquo;s safety mechanism, which is obviously a risk. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref6:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Again, this does not have to be the case: it is technically possible to make devices suitable for direct solar power.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fixed-speed compressor can only use 50% of the solar power produced in a useful way, while a variable-speed compressor uses about 75% in a useful way. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A capacitor is needed to provide the compressor with an energy boost during the start-up phase.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a DC-DC converter, you can also install a small &amp;ldquo;buffer battery&amp;rdquo; and a charge controller. Like a DC-DC converter, the charge controller will ensure a stable output voltage. In addition, the small battery can provide limited energy storage that can be useful to handle short spikes in power consumption. For example, some devices have a current spike when charging. The disadvantage of a buffer battery is that the cost and embedded energy increase, and additional components can fail. A capacitor is an alternative technology to absorb power peaks.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, using low-voltage direct current devices is a lot more energy-efficient because solar panels also produce low-voltage direct current: &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&#34;&gt;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://conev.org/ISECmanual14.pdf&#34;&gt;Insulated Solar Cooker Construction Manual&lt;/a&gt;, Living Energy Farm. &lt;a href=&#34;http://sharedcurriculum.peteschwartz.net/isecooker-construction/&#34;&gt;Insulated solar electric cooker manual&lt;/a&gt;, Pete Schwartz, Cal Poly Physics. &lt;a href=&#34;https://livingenergylights.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/roxy-installation-instructions.pdf&#34;&gt;Roxy Oven Manual&lt;/a&gt;, Living Energy Farm. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SIDG8fTvf-I&#34;&gt;Video presentation manual solar electric cookers&lt;/a&gt;, Alexis Zeigler, Living Energy Farm. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uzZPstX1CbQ&#34;&gt;Video manual for making heating wires&lt;/a&gt;. Thermal heat storage: &lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1747&amp;amp;context=mesp&#34;&gt;Insulated Solar Electric Cooker with Solid Thermal Storage&lt;/a&gt;, Andrew McCombs et al., 2022. Also see &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FKIH7HDK6Dw&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Printed Website: Volume III &amp; The Comments</title>
      <link>/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="14598" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Printed Website.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Printed Website. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-volume-iii&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest Low-tech Magazine book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;collects 18 articles published between 2018 and 2021&lt;/a&gt;. At 368 pages it’s a thin book compared to earlier volumes. When we started the book series, the challenge was to unlock an archive of almost 12 years. It made sense to pack this content into as few volumes as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking ahead, we will publish more often, once every one to three years, depending on the number of articles written. From now on, the articles will be arranged chronologically, from oldest to newest, and no longer the other way around. This volume contains 184 images in black and white. It is &lt;a href=&#34;/fr/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/&#34;&gt;also available in French&lt;/a&gt; (400 pages).
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-the-comments&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also launched a book which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;collects almost 3,000 comments&lt;/a&gt; on the roughly 100 articles which are published in the three other books. This volume has 688 pages and no images. We included all feedback up to November 7, 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;/low-tech-magazine-the-printed-comments/&#34;&gt;Read more about the comments book here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, readers have often stated that the comments on the website are (at least) as interesting as the articles themselves. We agree. Low-tech Magazine would not have been even half what it is now without the comments. You can even take this literally, because this is one of the thickest books we have published so far, despite the extra small font we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-edition&#34;&gt;New Edition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;second edition of the first book we published&lt;/a&gt; in 2019. This new edition has almost twice as many images and follows the same design as the other volumes. In contrast to the first edition, the images are not &amp;ldquo;dithered&amp;rdquo; and of higher quality. We use a smaller font to pack more content on fewer pages. This second edition also fixes some errors in the articles and the references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/comments-book-cover_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/low-tech-magazine-volume-III-montage_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents-volume-iii&#34;&gt;Contents Volume III&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Circular is the Circular Economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping Some of the Lights On: Redefining Energy Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat your House with a Mechanical Windmill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinventing the Small Wind Turbine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Wind Power Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mist Showers: Sustainable Decadence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too Much Combustion, Too Little Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is a Solar Powered Website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit Trenches: Cultivating Subtropical Plants in Freezing Temperatures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermoelectric Stoves: Ditch the Solar Panels?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Biomass Energy Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and Why I Stopped Buying New Laptops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical Farming Does not Save Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is High-tech Health Care?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Urban Fish Ponds: Low-tech Sewage Treatment for Towns and Cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Build a Low-tech Solar Panel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fascine Mattresses: Basketry Gone Wild&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;print-on-demand&#34;&gt;Print on Demand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The books are printed on demand, meaning that there are no unsold copies (and no large upfront investment costs). Our US publisher Lulu.com works with printers all over the world, so that most copies are produced locally and travel relatively short distances. Note that it takes 3 to 5 work days to print the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2007-2012/paperback/product-1z742pek.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume I (2007-2012)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume II (2012-2018)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Build a Low-tech Solar Panel?</title>
      <link>/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/COVE-1910_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="48472" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/COVE-1910_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;George Cove stands next to his third solar array. Source: &amp;amp;quot;Generating electricity by the sun&amp;amp;rsquo;s rays&amp;amp;quot;, Popular Electricity, Volume 2, nr. 12, April 1910, pp.793.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 George Cove stands next to his third solar array. Source: \&#34;Generating electricity by the sun&#39;s rays\&#34;, Popular Electricity, Volume 2, nr. 12, April 1910, pp.793. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-efficient-less-sustainable&#34;&gt;More efficient, less sustainable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since Bell Labs presented the first practical solar PV panel in the 1950s, technological development has focused on reducing costs and increasing the efficiency of solar cells. According to these standards, researchers have made a lot of progress. The efficiency of solar panels increased from less than 5% in the 1950s to over 20% today, while the costs decreased from 30 dollars per watt-peak in 1980 to less than 0.2 dollars per watt-peak in 2020. Lower costs – to which higher efficiencies contribute – are considered of paramount importance because they allow solar PV panels to compete in the market with electricity generated by fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in terms of sustainability, very little progress has been made. To start with, ever since the 1950s, solar panels have been unfit for recycling, resulting in a waste stream that ends up in landfills. This waste stream will grow significantly during the coming years. Solar panels are discarded only after at least 25 to 30 years, and most have been installed only in recent years. By 2050, researchers expect that almost 80 million tonnes of solar panels will reach the end of their lives. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That is a significant waste of resources and a danger to the environment – discarded solar PV panels contain toxic elements and present a fire hazard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for capital-intensive technology and long supply lines prevents the local production of solar panels by less affluent societies or DIY communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing of solar PV panels is just as problematic. It produces toxic waste and requires a global supply chain, including capital-intensive factories, complex machinery, mined materials, and a steady input of fossil fuels. In life cycle analyses of solar panels, scientists calculate &lt;a href=&#34;/2015/04/how-sustainable-is-pv-solar-power/&#34;&gt;how much energy and materials are required to build a solar panel&lt;/a&gt;. However, they ignore the massive amount of energy and materials needed to set up and maintain the solar PV supply chain itself. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Consequently, these studies do not reveal the actual cost of solar panels in terms of fossil fuel dependence, emissions, and other environmental pollution. Furthermore, the need for capital-intensive technology and long supply lines prevents the local production of solar panels by less affluent societies or DIY communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-inspiration-in-the-past&#34;&gt;Finding inspiration in the past&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are solar PV panels inherently unsustainable, unrecyclable, and dependent on high-tech and capital-intensive manufacturing processes? Or, is it possible to build them with local, recyclable and less energy-intensive materials and production methods? In other words, can we build low-tech solar panels? And, if so, what would that mean for costs and efficiency?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we try to answer this question, it’s important to note that the best low-tech alternative for a high-tech solar panel is often not a low-tech solar panel but direct use of solar energy. That is, putting solar energy to use without converting it to electricity first. For example, a clothesline and a solar thermal water boiler are much more efficient, sustainable, and economical than an electric tumble dryer and a water boiler powered by solar PV panels. Direct use of solar energy can happen with local materials, relatively simple manufacturing technologies, and short supply lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, in this article, I take the question literally: can we build low-tech photovoltaic devices, which convert sunlight into electricity? In a previous article, we have seen that &lt;a href=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/&#34;&gt;history offers inspiration for building more sustainable wind turbines&lt;/a&gt;. Can history also inspire us to make more sustainable solar cells?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-prehistory-of-solar-cells&#34;&gt;The prehistory of solar cells&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bell Labs’ solar PV panel, presented in 1954, came not out of nowhere. The silicon solar cell had its roots in less complex devices that could produce electricity from either light or heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1821, Thomas Seebeck found that an electrical current will flow in a circuit made from two dissimilar metals, with the junctions at different temperatures. This “thermoelectric effect” formed the basis for the “thermoelectric generator” &amp;ndash; which converts heat (for example, &lt;a href=&#34;/2020/05/thermoelectric-stoves-ditch-the-solar-panels/&#34;&gt;from a wood stove&lt;/a&gt;) directly into electricity. In 1839, Antoine Becquerel discovered that light could also convert into electricity, and during the 1870s, several scientists proved this effect in solids, most notably in selenium. This “photoelectric effect” formed the basis for the “photoelectric generator” &amp;ndash; which we now call a “photovoltaic” generator or solar PV cell. In 1883, Charles Fritts constructed the first photovoltaic module ever made, using selenium on a thin layer of gold. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this period – and until the 1950s – the practical uses of thermoelectric and photoelectric devices were limited. Inventors built many experimental thermoelectric generators, usually powered by a gas flame, but their efficiency did not exceed 1%. Likewise, Charles Fritts’ solar panel, and the selenium solar cells made afterward, obtained just 1-2% efficiency in converting sunlight into electricity. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In short, the period before the 1950s doesn’t seem to offer much inspiration for building more sustainable solar PV panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-forgotten-pioneer-of-solar-power&#34;&gt;A forgotten pioneer of solar power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the prehistory of the solar panel may be incomplete. In 2019, I received a mail from a reader of Low-tech Magazine, Philip Pesavento:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have been studying an early pioneer in solar cell technology from the pre-WWI era since the early 1990s. I am getting too old to continue doing anything with this, and even though there have been one or two scholarly articles about Mr. Cove, they have completely missed what he accomplished. I am enclosing a PDF of a PowerPoint that I put together back in 2015 and never presented to anyone. If you are interested in pursuing writing a paper yourself, I could mail you a thumb drive with all the background material that I have collected.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Philip Pesavento’s historical account and hypotheses are correct, George Cove set out to build a thermoelectric generator but accidentally made a photovoltaic generator – a PV solar cell. Although this happened in the early 1900s, Cove obtained a comparable power output and efficiency to the Bell Labs scientists in 1954. His design also showed much higher performance than the selenium solar cells built between the 1880s and the 1940s. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Philip Pesavento:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It would be quite exciting to prove that relatively high-efficiency solar cells were invented 40 years before the development of silicon cells. More importantly, if it turns out there was a solar photovoltaic cell and panel system before World War I, it might also have some advantages concerning the cheapness of raw materials, low embodied energy to convert the ores into metallic materials, the efficiency of the final PV cells, and ease of fabrication.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if Philip Pesavento’s historical account and hypotheses are correct, it may be possible to build low-tech solar panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;george-coves-solar-electric-generator&#34;&gt;George Cove’s solar electric generator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George Cove presented his first “solar electric generator” in 1905 in the Metropole Building in Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada. Apart from an image, there are no data about this panel. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, its power output and efficiency were remarkable enough for US investors to send an expert to Halifax. Based on this expert’s examination of the machine, they then brought Cove to the US (Sommerville, Mass.) to continue the development of his device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cove presented his second solar electric generator there in 1909. This 1.5m2 panel could produce 45 watts of power and was 2.75% efficient in converting solar energy into electricity. By mid-1909, Cove had moved to New York City, where he presented his third prototype, a solar array consisting of four solar panels of 60 watt-peak each, which charged a total of five lead-acid batteries. The total surface area was 4.5 m2, the maximum power output was 240 watts, and efficiency rose to 5% – similar to the first solar panel presented by Bell Labs. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/cove-technical-world-magazine-1909_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Above: George Cove&amp;amp;rsquo;s first solar panel, demonstrated in 1905. Source: Technical World Magazine 11, nr.4, June 1909.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Above: George Cove&#39;s first solar panel, demonstrated in 1905. Source: Technical World Magazine 11, nr.4, June 1909. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/cove-one-section-missing_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Above: Cove&amp;amp;rsquo;s second solar panel, with one section missing. Source: Technical World Magazine 11, nr.4, June 1909.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Above: Cove&#39;s second solar panel, with one section missing. Source: Technical World Magazine 11, nr.4, June 1909. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/Cove-solar-panel-1909_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Above: George Cove&amp;amp;rsquo;s third solar panel. Source: &amp;amp;quot;Harnessing sunlight&amp;amp;quot;, René Homer, Modern Electrics, Vol. II, No.6, September 1909.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Above: George Cove&#39;s third solar panel. Source: \&#34;Harnessing sunlight\&#34;, René Homer, Modern Electrics, Vol. II, No.6, September 1909. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/COVE-THIRD-PANEL_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Above: George Cove&amp;amp;rsquo;s third solar panel. The panels are now tilted at an angle as opposed to lying flat. Source: Literary Digest 1909, pp. 1153.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Above: George Cove&#39;s third solar panel. The panels are now tilted at an angle as opposed to lying flat. Source: Literary Digest 1909, pp. 1153. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/cove-panel-close-up_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Above: One of the solar panels of Cove&amp;amp;rsquo;s third solar array, with the glass cover removed. Source: &amp;amp;quot;Harnessing sunlight&amp;amp;quot;, René Homer, Modern Electrics, Vol. II, No.6, September 1909.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Above: One of the solar panels of Cove&#39;s third solar array, with the glass cover removed. Source: \&#34;Harnessing sunlight\&#34;, René Homer, Modern Electrics, Vol. II, No.6, September 1909. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although George Cove is absent from most historical accounts of solar power, his solar electric generator impressed some popular tech media of the day. For example, in 1909, Technical World Magazine wrote that “such a machine is cheap and indestructible as a kitchen range. Even in its present and somewhat crude and experimental state, given two days of sun, it will store sufficient electrical energy to light an ordinary house for a week. The inventor has proved this now for months in his establishment”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;plugs-set-in-asphalt&#34;&gt;Plugs set in asphalt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did George Cove manage to build a solar panel that was 40 years ahead of its time? According to Philip Pesavento, who has a background in semiconductor engineering, Cove intended to build a better thermoelectric generator (TEG). He exposed his generator to the heat from a wood stove and direct solar energy &amp;ndash; Edward Weston had made the first experimental solar thermoelectric generator (or STEG) in 1888. Cove’s intentions are also clear from how he described his device:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The frame contains a number of panes of violet glass, behind which are set, through an asphalt compound backing, many little metal plugs. One end of the plugs is always exposed by sunlight, while the other end is cool and sheltered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating the largest possible temperature difference is &lt;a href=&#34;/2020/05/thermoelectric-stoves-ditch-the-solar-panels/&#34;&gt;key to thermoelectric power production&lt;/a&gt;, so Cove’s design makes sense. The problem is that when he measured the power output of his generator, it did not respond to heat like a thermo-electric generator was supposed to do. Initially, Cove observes that his invention uses both heat and light to produce electricity when exposed to solar energy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The principal part of my invention is the peculiar composition of the metallic plugs which are acted upon by the sun in such a way that the current is generated not only by heat rays but the violet rays as well”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, after further experiments with both the wood stove and solar energy, Cove states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When the machine is exposed to various sources of artificial heat it gives no electricity whatsoever. Other than the heat rays of the sun (short-wave infrared), perhaps the violet or ultraviolet rays are active in setting up the electrical current”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary cell of Cove’s solar PV panel was a three-inch-long plug or rod of metallic composition, an alloy of several common metals. The 1.5 m2 panel had 976 rods, while the 4.5 m2 array had 4 x 1804 plugs. However, keeping the rods cool on one side and hot on another – separated by an asphalt layer – did not matter. What mattered is that Cove had unknowingly built a metal-semiconductor contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-semiconductor-bandgap&#34;&gt;The semiconductor bandgap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George Cove did not understand how his solar generator worked, and neither did anyone else at the time. It was only with Einstein’s work on the photoelectric effect (in 1905) and later work in quantum mechanics (1930s and beyond) that the concept of a &lt;em&gt;semiconductor bandgap&lt;/em&gt; was realized. Electrons orbit the nucleus of an atom in different “states”, which form regions that are called “bands”. These bands keep their electrons firmly in place. In between these bands are “bandgaps” – states in which no electron can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George Cove did not understand how his solar generator worked, and neither did anyone else at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conductors have no bandgaps, and so electrons flow through them. That is why a copper wire conducts electricity, for example. In insulators (like wood, glass, plastics, or ceramics), there is a very wide bandgap, which blocks the flow of electricity. Finally, in semiconductors, there’s a relatively narrow bandgap. That allows them to either act as an insulator or a conductor. Semiconductors can become conductors when they absorb a “photon” (an elementary particle of light) with an energy potential equal to or greater than the bandgap of the semiconductor material. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The understanding of semiconductors led to the birth of the modern solar PV cell in the 1950s. It also improved the performance of thermoelectric generators – be it for different reasons. Thermoelectric generators do not take advantage of the semiconductor bandgap. However, semiconductors have higher thermo-voltages and lower thermal conductivities than metal and metal alloys with no bandgap, making thermoelectric generators more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-schottky-junction&#34;&gt;The Schottky Junction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a photovoltaic effect to exist, there must be some inhomogeneity in the system. In the 1950s, Bell Labs scientists managed to do this with the so-called p-n junction, which forms a boundary between a positively charged and a negatively charged semiconductor. P-type semiconductors have electron vacancies called “holes” (which attract electrons), while N-type semiconductors have extra electrons. At the junction between both is an electric potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s also possible to create a PV cell from a so-called Schottky junction, which connects a semiconductor with a metal. In this case, the metal functions as the n-type semiconductor. Philip Pesavento:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My hypothesis is that George Cove stumbled upon a Schottky contact photovoltaic cell, decades before it was described by Walter Schottky. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is the possibility of both photovoltaic (predominantly) and thermoelectric responses from these devices. The plug was an alloy of zinc and antimony – which we now know is a semiconductor. It was alternately capped by German silver (a nickel, copper, and zinc alloy) and copper on opposite ends. This formed an ohmic contact and Schottky contact, respectively. This is a photovoltaic device.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accidental-discovery&#34;&gt;Accidental discovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Philip Pesavento, George Cove probably started with “German silver” as the negative material on both ends of the plugs, and an antimony-zinc alloy (ZnSb) as the positive material. These were the best available thermoelectric materials at the time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He probably ran out of German silver and substituted copper to finish making up a bunch of plugs since the difference in thermoelectric voltage between using copper and German silver was small. Then, during testing, Cove noted that these plugs (with a German silver cap at one end and a copper cap at the other end) gave a much greater voltage: 100s of mV’s versus the usual 10s of mV for a thermoelectric generator.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? By using copper, Cove had unknowingly built a Schottky junction. That converted his thermoelectric generator into a “thermophotovoltaic generator.” Such a device works the same as a photovoltaic solar cell but on a different wavelength. The solar spectrum covers a range of approximately 0.5 to 2.9 electron-Volts (eV), from infrared to ultraviolet. A semiconductor with a bandgap between 1 and 1.7 eV efficiently converts visible light into electricity (a photovoltaic generator) &amp;ndash; while a semiconductor with a bandgap between 0.4 and 0.7 eV efficiently converts short-wave infrared solar energy into electricity (a thermophotovoltaic generator).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-solar-panel/images/dithers/Cove-plugs_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Above: This drawing from Cove&amp;amp;rsquo;s 1906 patent shows the zinc-antimony alloy “b”; the german silver (ohmic) end cap “c”; and the copper or tin (Schottky) end cap “f”. All these are press-fit because soldering the connections lowered the efficiency.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Above: This drawing from [Cove&#39;s 1906 patent](https://patentimages.storage.googleapis.com/bc/bb/50/6683e8b44edd4c/US824684.pdf) shows the zinc-antimony alloy “b”; the german silver (ohmic) end cap “c”; and the copper or tin (Schottky) end cap “f”. All these are press-fit because soldering the connections lowered the efficiency. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know that ZnSb – the negative material in Cove’s plugs – is a semiconductor with a bandgap of 0.5 eV. That largely explains why the inventor initially observed that his solar generator converted both heat and light into electricity. A thermophotovoltaic generator matches not only the infrared tail of the solar spectrum &amp;ndash; it also matches the direct spectrum of a burning flame or a red hot emitting surface which is heated by burning wood or natural gas. It also converts the lower portion of the visible spectrum into electricity, be it very inefficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Philip Pesavento, Cove then managed to refine the composition of the alloy close to Zn4Sb3 – a zinc-antimony alloy with proportions of 4 parts zinc to 6 parts antimony. That, we now know, is also a semiconductor. However, it has a bandgap of 1.2 eV – very close to the bandgap of silicon (1.1 eV). Consequently, it turned his thermophotovoltaic generator into a photovoltaic generator:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In his enthusiasm, Cove probably made up a larger number of plugs and somehow got the proportions “wrong” on one batch. He then measured an even larger voltage. Finally, he made a careful study of zinc-antimony alloys and found that the 40-42% range zinc alloy gave the highest voltage (compared to 35% zinc in ZnSb). Having – accidentally – discovered Zn4Sb3, the higher bandgap of this semiconductor meant that it no longer worked when it was exposed to the heat from a wood stove. However, it worked even better when it was exposed to solar energy – because it was now converting far more of the visible spectrum of sunlight efficiently into electricity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using colored glass filters, George Cove determined that most of the response was from the violet end of the spectrum and only a little from the so-called heat rays. His earlier PV plugs had responded equally well to heat rays and violet rays, while the older thermoelectric generators (German silver at both sides) did not respond to the violet rays at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bring-back-the-schottky-solar-cell&#34;&gt;Bring back the Schottky solar cell?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schottky junction solar cells have commanded only a small amount of attention from researchers and corporations – few solar cell designs use metals in the active region, other than for contacts. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nevertheless, Philip Pesavento believes that it would be worthwhile to attempt to fabricate some Schottky solar cells according to Cove’s design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If it could be demonstrated that Zn4Sb3 (bandgap 1.2 eV) can be used in a photovoltaic cell, there is a good chance that such a solar cell design will be sustainable. It would be a good candidate for a quick EROI and have an acceptably long operational life with a surplus energy output over several decades. It’s astounding that everyone seems to have missed this material and its application to photovoltaic cells and that no development has been done – even after researchers briefly recognized it as being a possible option in the early to mid-1980s. It fits in the category of a premature discovery which should mean it could be developed very quickly in this day and age.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from solar PV, Philip Pesavento sees potential in thermophotovoltaics for a wood stove, solar thermal, or dual junction tandem applications, using ZnSb instead of Zn4Sb3. Furthermore, if the plug-type solar cells prove to be effective, he believes that they would allow line concentrator solar collectors – such as parabolic troughs or non-imagining CPC concentrators – to be built at greatly reduced costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-manufacturing&#34;&gt;Low-tech manufacturing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary advantage of Cove’s design would be its low-tech fabrication method. In the 1970s and 1980s, scientists investigated Zn4Sb3 for use in photovoltaics and concluded that the material’s “obvious advantages are apparent simplicity and relatively low temperature of the preparation procedure.” &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The melting point for Zn4Sb3 is 570 degrees Celsius, while it’s 1,400 degrees for silicon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers studied metal-semiconductor junction solar cells based on other types of semiconductors than Zn4Sb3 in the 1970s. Again, their motivation was the simple and cost-effective fabrication procedure compared to silicon p-n junction solar cells at the time. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Schottky cells do not require a high-temperature phosphorus-diffusion step, which ordinarily creates the n-layer of the p-n junction in silicon today. This alone reduces the energy input into the solar cell production process by 35%. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 1980s, researchers made important advances in silicon p-n junctions, and interest in alternative configurations waned. However, there has been renewed interest in recent years. For example, research into graphene/silicon Schottky solar cells concludes that “simple and cost-effective device fabrication that does not require high temperatures is one of the advantages.” &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In other recent studies, scientists conclude that Schottky-type “selenium devices are… extremely simple and cheap to fabricate”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;easier-recycling&#34;&gt;Easier recycling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of Schottky solar cells may be easier recycling. Silicon modules are sandwiched between two laminate encapsulant layers (usually EVA, an ethylene/vinyl acetate copolymer). These layers are essential to ensure module service lifetime. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; To recycle the silicon – the most valuable component of a solar panel – these layers need to be separated, but burning them also destroys the modules. Silicon cells can only be recycled by a combination of thermal, chemical, and metallurgical steps. That is an expensive process with an impact on the environment. Although you can find statements claiming that around 10% of solar panels are “recycled&amp;quot;, they are more likely to be “downcycled”. The modules are shredded, and the resulting material is used as a filler material in asphalt and cement industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the solar cells built by George Cove were entirely recyclable. They required no protective layer and did not even contain solder. Philip Pesavento:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you were to build the cells exactly the way Cove did by press-fitting the caps and then overwrapping them with wire to try to keep them tight, they would also be easier to recycle, being strictly a mechanical operation, no chemicals need to be involved. It would be labor-intensive to put them together and take them apart again, but it could be automated, too.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pesavento believes that it’s also possible to build flat solar cells from Cove’s material. However, whether or not those would need a protective layer that interferes with recycling remains to be seen. In the 1970s, Schottky solar cells based on other materials did not always need protective layers to reach more than 20 years of life expectancy. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;efficiency&#34;&gt;Efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we could build more low-tech solar panels, how efficient could we make them? According to Philip Pesavento, Schottky cells are slightly less efficient for the same materials than p-n junctions because p-n junctions generate a higher voltage – they get more of the energy in the photons they absorb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When every bit of efficiency counts, you do that. If making solar cells easier to manufacture using manual or artisan methods is your goal, the Schottky diode would be a more logical choice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it may be possible to build Schottky cells thinner than silicon solar cells – and that would increase their efficiency. Philip Pesavento:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have not found the specific numbers for the parameters – carrier velocity, recombination lifetime, absorption coefficient – to say this unequivocally. But the fact that Cove made such long skinny cells and got as high efficiencies as he did bodes well for making them thinner.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, recent research into Schottky cells based on other materials seems to confirm this. For example, recent experiments with Schottky selenium cells brought layer thickness back to only 100 µm, compared to between 200 and 500 µm for silicon cells. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Scientists also reached 17% experimental efficiency for a graphene/silicon Schottky cell, up from 1.5% ten years earlier. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also question the current obsession with higher efficiencies. Many people will argue that if low-tech solar panels are less efficient, we would need more solar panels to produce the same power output. Consequently, the resources saved by low-tech production methods would be compensated by the extra resources to build more solar panels. However, efficiency is only crucial &lt;a href=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/&#34;&gt;when we take energy demand for granted&lt;/a&gt;, sacrificing some efficiency may gain us a lot in sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened-to-george-cove&#34;&gt;What happened to George Cove?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Cove’s solar panel was so revolutionary, why is it forgotten? On this question, Philip Pesavento’s research material reads like a crime novel. Cove’s attempt to produce and market his solar energy device failed in mysterious ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inventor became involved with a stock manipulator – Elmer Burlingame – who in 1909 and 1910 issued stock from businesses that were not his, including Cove’s start-up the Sun Electric Generator Company. In October 1909, Cove was allegedly kidnapped, and his life was threatened if he did not cease the development of his solar invention. However, the police dismissed Cove’s kidnapping as a hoax. In 1911, both Cove and Burlingame were arrested for stock fraud and spent a year in jail. Although Cove worked on other inventions after that, none of those were related to solar energy. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October 1909, Cove was allegedly kidnapped, and his life was threatened if he did not cease the development of his solar invention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was George Cove a charlatan? Was he the victim of one? Or was his reputation destroyed because the solar electric generator threatened other companies’ interests? There are many historical examples of suppression of technological innovations by large US corporations. George Cove was active in the same period as the Edison Electric Illuminating Company of New York, whose unscrupulous practices against competitors are well-documented. If Cove’s solar electric generator worked, it could have reduced the growing demand for Edison’s coal and oil-fired power stations. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:32&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;32&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Earlier, in the 1880s, Edison had bought the company that produced the best thermoelectric generator at the time – Clamonds’s Improved Thermopile – and subsequently stopped the development of the machines. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:33&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:33&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;33&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-mysteries&#34;&gt;More Mysteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while it’s tempting to see George Cove as a victim, we can only speculate. Philip Pesavento’s archive material contains more mysteries, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://patentimages.storage.googleapis.com/bc/bb/50/6683e8b44edd4c/US824684.pdf&#34;&gt;Cove’s patent&lt;/a&gt; – applied for in 1905, granted in 1906. In his patent, the inventor describes the making of his Zn4Sb3 plugs in detail, which helped Pesavento to calculate the power output and efficiency of the solar arrays. However, Cove describes these plugs for converting heat from a wood stove into electricity, which is not compatible with his choice of material. To make the stove generator work, it required ZnSb plugs with a bandgap of 0.5 eV. Philip Pesavento:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Was this misdirection on the part of Cove to prevent folks from copying his stove patent and getting it to work? I don’t know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more surprisingly, an image that shows Cove standing beside one of his solar panels also appears in John Perlin’s 2013 historical overview of solar power &lt;em&gt;Let It Shine: The 6,000-Year Story of Solar Energy&lt;/em&gt;. However, the solar panel in the image is attributed to Charles Fritts, the inventor of the selenium solar cell. Furthermore, George Cove himself has disappeared from the image. Excerpts from the book, as well as the photo, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/sponsored/brief-history-solar-panels-180972006/&#34;&gt;have appeared on several websites&lt;/a&gt;. Philip Pesavento was not surprised when I got back in touch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I made this discovery several years ago. I guess that somebody badly needed an image of Fritts’ solar panels, found this image, and then photoshopped George Cove out of it. After all, Cove is totally unknown and when known is thought to have invented a solar thermoelectric generator, not a solar PV panel. If you look closely at the two photos, you can see that the top of the right column portico behind him was cut and pasted to where Cove had been standing, it’s not quite right in its perspective.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bellingcat.com/news/2023/08/16/untangling-the-mystery-of-the-worlds-first-rooftop-solar-panel/?utm_source=twitter&#34;&gt;Bellingcat untangled the mystery of the image&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weckend, Stephanie, Andreas Wade, and Garvin A. Heath. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1561525&#34;&gt;End of life management: solar photovoltaic panels&lt;/a&gt;. No. NREL/TP-6A20-73852. National Renewable Energy Lab.(NREL), Golden, CO (United States), 2016.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xu, Yan, et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0956053X18300576&#34;&gt;Global status of recycling waste solar panels: A review&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Waste Management 75 (2018): 450-458.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sica, Daniela, et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Stefania-Supino/publication/320886399_Management_of_end-of-life_photovoltaic_panels_as_a_step_towards_a_circular_economy/links/5a7823a445851541ce5aa795/Management-of-end-of-life-photovoltaic-panels-as-a-step-towards-a-circular-economy.pdf&#34;&gt;Management of end-of-life photovoltaic panels as a step towards a circular economy&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 82 (2018): 2934-2945.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hornborg, Alf, Gustav Cederlöf, and Andreas Roos. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/2514848619863607&#34;&gt;Has Cuba exposed the myth of “free” solar power? Energy, space, and justice&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Environment and planning E: Nature and space 2.4 (2019): 989-1008.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cederlof, Gustav, and Alf Hornborg. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kclpure.kcl.ac.uk/portal/files/149206991/jpe_2303_cederl_f.pdf&#34;&gt;System boundaries as epistemological and ethnographic problems: Assessing energy technology and socio-environmental impact&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Political Ecology 28.1 (2021): 111-123.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bartie, N. J., et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0921344921001233&#34;&gt;The resources, exergetic and environmental footprint of the silicon photovoltaic circular economy: Assessment and opportunities&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Resources, Conservation and Recycling 169 (2021): 105516.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powell, Douglas M., et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlehtml/2015/ee/c5ee01509j&#34;&gt;The capital intensity of photovoltaics manufacturing: barrier to scale and opportunity for innovation&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Energy &amp;amp; Environmental Science 8.12 (2015): 3395-3408.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dehghani, Ehsan, et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0959652620314815&#34;&gt;An environmentally conscious photovoltaic supply chain network design under correlated uncertainty: A case study in Iran&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Cleaner Production 262 (2020): 121434.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carvalho, Maria, Antoine Dechezleprêtre, and Matthieu Glachant. &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.es/books?hl=nl&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;id=nSSjDwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;oi=fnd&amp;amp;pg=PA2&amp;amp;dq=Understanding+the+dynamics+of+global+value+chains+for+solar+PV+technologies&amp;amp;ots=m9f3jNSAKZ&amp;amp;sig=NCENGV7AU5d7ze6hIcuOflQ0NOY&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Understanding%20the%20dynamics%20of%20global%20value%20chains%20for%20solar%20PV%20technologies&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;Understanding the dynamics of global value chains for solar photovoltaic technologies&lt;/a&gt;. Vol. 40. WIPO, 2017.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dehghani, Ehsan, et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0098135418300371&#34;&gt;Resilient solar photovoltaic supply chain network design under business-as-usual and hazard uncertainties&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Computers &amp;amp; Chemical Engineering 111 (2018): 288-310.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kumar, Abhishek, et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pdf.sciencedirectassets.com/277910/1-s2.0-S1876610217X00283/1-s2.0-S1876610217345034/main.pdf?X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjELr%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLWVhc3QtMSJIMEYCIQD2rJs2Bwk%2Fptc6KvDsPMRxHpxwVvjh3m7PUOeECB3hcAIhALITZLCugdjA5IONheCiCTlC23iXPIdeJko%2B3G%2FwiYrZKoMECMP%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEQBBoMMDU5MDAzNTQ2ODY1Igxk03OGC9nabg9m8Kwq1wMkzNTJ4CEjog7CoWj3BdQfjRXemLdOutFwe3fid5pPMUyvPnd8mxd%2BuUdZOmNZxssbSVUVNdzf1IHRZxmJoHOSYVuwWYGBGnRaT7PaAlxDYY%2B24JLe1QcQgzasQ%2BczCtae8HvyMeiB5z1b%2FhnjMS1a1y9aJyQ%2Bx3yph%2Bj7zMZBU2EXKxXgoWwJJuemWdVCVbGJUZ0flrPPQks7li%2BHKSjXyUvfCwBEuHIRWhyAvbt86ALM%2BPTNEo0PMr4soHrOfNv9jUEIv5NTcYlMTY2A7YJ1qBJ0Y3CM3eRJyJI23rOhjcikeYZvtHml4HL%2FEWtvooLt%2Fj6hMbaUINLIdQ7hKrnkGt2OivN3R3YhGDzWr8Aiwdh%2BBPNbTQySk4GpmYwnruAlqL1y%2Bezw020bdDTIJS2Ta8DCPG1lQK1Tu%2F27b97wysh1ugVVEZRD4xHcd57vtLWAFufpezWn7luph6LHt%2BUHNjghfW2MnCSIyP79U9za%2BUerYgwsXJ3k5VFp8sAI2AcFdjhv3cZbG2bpsKsFQD9TvLyaX2eZUMZonoUFOpOaWUTkBZUd6Zn8U1fKUlC%2BLbZnQ4SH%2FCA%2BgksCykp0Dx7iKNBJPeeXAPNrY3e8%2BWbMsLBnJo65i4Ew4p%2BWiAY6pAFhGtfsqohtlYtjMt3%2FZnUcPLcOuiHX%2BYDywhj8v7wNlKQjPiBQz%2F024BPocmpVBeSZtyvOvdeu93QQtouGw1yYv2%2BvNf7Z5QS4%2Bdsgr5HGT1D%2FrKPnW8KHA0o5uAIFk8kHpXRLoA912cc%2FE16aHHstZ2Xka7awVt5aXPZn5yyvGF9pzPcGn3bChYypHLvb46hrc0pnpLgxi3hGWGzPVv5pAxhTKA%3D%3D&amp;amp;X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;amp;X-Amz-Date=20210731T184754Z&amp;amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;amp;X-Amz-Expires=300&amp;amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAQ3PHCVTYYAJ65I2D%2F20210731%2Fus-east-1%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;amp;X-Amz-Signature=2e952c3a77a9afb90f3e362d31625284a6fd702880d3c6653435014c17f8ddef&amp;amp;hash=973b80c57ae0465b941da461d3b2dde574bbe6dd043d7bb273882030797a29ba&amp;amp;host=68042c943591013ac2b2430a89b270f6af2c76d8dfd086a07176afe7c76c2c61&amp;amp;pii=S1876610217345034&amp;amp;tid=spdf-72bd8135-bf33-4ca4-a599-40b4efd00a0e&amp;amp;sid=c54258cc123e984af63a5c853f4a5e874174gxrqb&amp;amp;type=client&#34;&gt;Economic viability analysis of silicon solar cell manufacturing: Al-BSF versus PERC&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Energy Procedia 130 (2017): 43-49.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fritts, Charles E. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ajsonline.org/content/s3-26/156/465.short&#34;&gt;On a new form of selenium cell, and some electrical discoveries made by its use&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; American Journal of Science 3.156 (1883): 465-472.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/007303e0&#34;&gt;Effect of Light on Selenium During the Passage of An Electric Current&lt;/a&gt;*. Nature 7, 303 (1873).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green, Martin A. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/pip.612&#34;&gt;Silicon photovoltaic modules: a brief history of the first 50 years&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Progress in Photovoltaics: Research and applications 13.5 (2005): 447-455.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perlin, John. Let it shine: the 6,000-year story of solar energy. New World Library, 2013.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/seleniumcells00bensrich&#34;&gt;Selenium Cells&lt;/a&gt;, Thomas William Benson, 1919.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extrapolating from the performance of the next panel, we can guess that this one had a power output of about 25W and just under 3% efficiency.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cove claimed to have built an even larger panel of 9 m2, but no image has survived. It was said to have had a power output of 768 watt at 8% efficiency assuming 100 W/ft2 solar insolation. This array consisted of 8 panels with a total of 14,432 plugs.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winthrop Packard, Technical World Magazine 11, nr.4, June 1909.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why don’t we use conductors for solar panels? When light hits a conductor surface it mostly reflects, and little or no energy is absorbed. Furthermore, in conductors, the free electrons move randomly, there is no flow of current, no directional capacity.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cove was not the first, though. Charles Fritts’ solar cell was also based on a Schottky junction.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Byrnes, Steve. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sjbyrnes.com/NSE290-FinalPaper.pdf&#34;&gt;Schottky junction solar cells&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; (2008).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tapiero, M., et al. &amp;ldquo;Preparation and characterization of Zn4Sb4.&amp;rdquo; Solar Energy Materials 12.4 (1985): 257-274. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0165163385900516&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0165163385900516&lt;/a&gt;. See also: Mozharivskyj, Yurij, et al. &amp;ldquo;A promising thermoelectric material: Zn4Sb3 or Zn6-δSb5. Its composition, structure, stability, and polymorphs. Structure and stability of Zn1-δSb.&amp;rdquo; Chemistry of Materials 16.8 (2004): 1580-1589. &lt;a href=&#34;https://lib.dr.iastate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1787&amp;amp;context=chem_pubs&#34;&gt;https://lib.dr.iastate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1787&amp;amp;context=chem_pubs&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rothwarf, A., and K. W. Böer. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0079678675900072&#34;&gt;Direct conversion of solar energy through photovoltaic cells&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Progress in Solid State Chemistry 10 (1975): 71-102..&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anderson, W. A., A. E. Delahoy, and R. A. Milano. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aip.scitation.org/doi/abs/10.1063/1.1663886&#34;&gt;An 8% efficient layered Schottky‐barrier solar cell&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Applied Physics 45.9 (1974): 3913-3915.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yavuz, Serdar. &lt;a href=&#34;https://escholarship.org/content/qt6k73b3ps/qt6k73b3ps.pdf&#34;&gt;Graphene/Silicon Schottky Junction Based Solar Cells&lt;/a&gt;. University of California, San Diego, 2018.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todorov, Teodor K., et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-017-00582-9&#34;&gt;Ultrathin high band gap solar cells with improved efficiencies from the world’s oldest photovoltaic material&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Nature communications 8.1 (2017): 1-8.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selenium can be deposited by thermal evaporation at only 200°C. This temperature is within easy reach of &lt;a href=&#34;/2011/07/the-bright-future-of-solar-thermal-powered-factories/&#34;&gt;solar thermal technologies&lt;/a&gt;, which means that in principle these processes could be run by direct use of solar energy.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadar, Ido, et al. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/am-pdf/10.1002/aenm.201802766&#34;&gt;Modern processing and insights on selenium solar cells: the world&amp;rsquo;s first photovoltaic device&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Advanced Energy Materials 9.16 (2019): 1802766.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ferhati, H., F. Djeffal, and D. Arar. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0925346718306463&#34;&gt;Above 14% efficiency earth-abundant selenium solar cells by introducing gold nanoparticles and Titanium sub-layer&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Optical Materials 86 (2018): 24-31.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhu, Menghua, Guangda Niu, and Jiang Tang. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2019/tc/c8tc05873c/unauth&#34;&gt;Elemental Se: fundamentals and its optoelectronic applications&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Materials Chemistry C 7.8 (2019): 2199-2206.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:32&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details in “&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.lib.unb.ca/index.php/MCR/article/view/17744/22231&#34;&gt;George Cove’s solar energy device&lt;/a&gt;”, Dennis Bartels, 1997.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:32&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:33&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polozine, Alexandre, Susanna Sirotinskaya, and Lírio Schaeffer. &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scielo.br/j/mr/a/6pQV5d6yY7dQfJj4pWNdyTv/abstract/?lang=en&amp;amp;format=html&#34;&gt;History of development of thermoelectric materials for electric power generation and criteria of their quality&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Materials Research 17 (2014): 1260-1267.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:33&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
