<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>./tags/shipping/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="./tags/shipping/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thematic Book Series: How to Downsize a Transport Network?</title>
      <link>./2023/10/thematic-book-series-how-to-downsize-a-transport-network/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2023/10/thematic-book-series-how-to-downsize-a-transport-network/images/dithers/Cover-thumbnail-test-12_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="9452" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>./2023/10/thematic-book-series-how-to-downsize-a-transport-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2023/10/thematic-book-series-how-to-downsize-a-transport-network/images/dithers/thematic-transport-book-cover_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Book cover. How to downsize a transport network?, Kris De Decker, 166 pages, Low-tech Magazine, 2023.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Book cover. [How to downsize a transport network?](https://www.lulu.com/shop/kris-de-decker/how-to-downsize-a-transport-network/paperback/product-42n4p7.html?q=&amp;page=1&amp;pageSize=4), Kris De Decker, 166 pages, Low-tech Magazine, 2023. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast and cheap transportation props up industrial societies, both for the moving of people and cargo. However, our transport networks are very wasteful of energy and utterly dependent on fossil fuels. In this series of articles, Low-tech Magazine critically examines the call for electrified vehicles, which depend on unsustainable batteries and infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much more important than the chosen power source is vehicle design: size, weight, speed, acceleration, and comfort level. Furthermore, public transport is more resource efficient, and we could electrify it without batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book&amp;rsquo;s second part deals with long-distance transportation: planes, trains, sailing ships, and ocean liners. By placing transportation technology in a historical context, Low-tech Magazine challenges our high-tech approach to sustainability and highlights the possibilities of alternative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents-table&#34;&gt;Contents table:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Downsize a Transport Network: the Chinese Wheelbarrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Citroën 2CV: Cleantech from the 1940s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Status Quo of Electric Cars: Better Batteries, Same Range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electric Velomobiles: as Fast and Comfortable as Automobiles, but 80 times more Efficient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get Wired again: Trolleybuses and Trolleytrucks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Speed Trains are Killing the European Railway Network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life Without Airplanes: from London to New York in 3 Days and 12 Hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/shop/kris-de-decker/how-to-downsize-a-transport-network/paperback/product-42n4p7.html?q=&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;pageSize=4&#34;&gt;How to downsize a transport network?&lt;/a&gt;, Kris De Decker, 166 pages, Low-tech Magazine, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-thematic-books-in-the-series&#34;&gt;Other thematic books in the series:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lulu.com/shop/roel-roscam-abbing-and-marie-otsuka-and-kris-de-decker/how-to-build-a-low-tech-internet/paperback/product-9yq8v7.html?q=&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;pageSize=4&#34;&gt;How to build a low-tech internet?&lt;/a&gt;, Kris De Decker, 162 pages, Low-tech Magazine, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Low-tech Magazine archives are also available as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/offline-reading/&#34;&gt;chronological series consisting of three volumes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.patreon.com/lowtechmagazine&#34;&gt;Patrons get early access to new books at a reduced price&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?</title>
      <link>./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Garthsnaid_-_SLV_H91.250-933_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="48677" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Garthsnaid_-_SLV_H91.250-933_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;On board the ship Garthsnaid at sea. A view from high up in the rigging. Image by Allan C. Green, circa 1920.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 On board the ship *Garthsnaid* at sea. A view from high up in the rigging. Image by Allan C. Green, circa 1920.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sailing ship is a textbook example of sustainability. For at least 4,000 years, sailing ships have transported passengers and cargo across the world’s seas and oceans without using a single drop of fossil fuels. If we want to keep travelling and trading globally in a low carbon society, sailing ships are the obvious alternative to container ships, bulk carriers, and airplanes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, by definition, the sailing ship is not a carbon neutral technology. For most of history, sailing ships were built from wood, but back then whole forests were felled for ships, and those trees often did not grow back. In the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, sailing ships were increasingly made from steel, which also has a significant carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carbon neutrality of sailing in the 21st century is even more elusive. That’s because we have changed profoundly since the Age of Sail. Compared to our forebears, we have higher demands in terms of safety, comfort, convenience, and cleanliness. These higher standards are difficult to achieve unless the ship also has a diesel engine and generator on-board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-revival-of-the-sailing-ship&#34;&gt;The revival of the sailing ship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sailing ship has seen a modest revival in the last decade, especially for the transportation of cargo. In 2009, Dutch company &lt;a href=&#34;https://fairtransport.eu/&#34;&gt;Fairtransport&lt;/a&gt; started shipping freight between Europe and the Americas with the &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt;, a sailing ship built in 1943. The company remains active today and has a second ship in service since 2015, the &lt;em&gt;Nordlys&lt;/em&gt; (built in 1873).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, others have joined the sail cargo business. In 2016, the German company &lt;a href=&#34;https://timbercoast.com/en/&#34;&gt;Timbercoast&lt;/a&gt; started shipping cargo with the &lt;em&gt;Avontuur&lt;/em&gt;, a ship built in 1920. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 2017, the French &lt;a href=&#34;https://blueschoonercompany.com/en/home/&#34;&gt;Blue Schooner Company&lt;/a&gt; started transporting cargo between Europe and the Americas with the &lt;em&gt;Gallant&lt;/em&gt;, a sailing ship that was built in 1916. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All these sailing ships were constructed in the twentieth or nineteenth century, and were restored at a later date. However, a revival of sail cannot rely on historical ships alone, because there’s not enough of them. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/clipper-ship-noach_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Noach, built in 1857.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Noach, built in 1857. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, there are at least two sailing ships in development that are being built from scratch: the &lt;em&gt;Ceiba&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;. The first ship is being constructed in Costa Rica by a company named &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sailcargo.org/&#34;&gt;Sailcargo&lt;/a&gt;. She is built from wood and inspired by a Finnish ship from the twentieth century. The second ship is designed by a company called &lt;a href=&#34;https://ecoclipper.org/&#34;&gt;EcoClipper&lt;/a&gt;, which is led by one of the founders of the Dutch FairTransport, Jorne Langelaan. Their &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is a steel replica of a Dutch clipper ship from 1857: the &lt;em&gt;Noach&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Old designs are not necessarily the best&amp;quot;, says Jorne Langelaan, &amp;ldquo;but whenever proven design is used, one can be sure of its performance. A new design is more of a gamble. Furthermore, in the 20th and 21st century, sailing technology developed for fast sailing yachts, which is an entirely different story compared to ships which need to be able to carry cargo.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-economical-sailing-ships&#34;&gt;More economical sailing ships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two ships – one under construction and one in the design phase – have the potential to make sail cargo a lot more economical than it is today. That’s because they have a much larger cargo capacity than the sailing ships currently in operation. As a ship becomes longer, her cargo capacity increases more than proportionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/ecoclipper-prototype500-colour_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The EcoClipper500 is a full-scale replica of the Noach.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The EcoClipper500 is a full-scale replica of the Noach. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 46 metre long &lt;em&gt;Ceiba&lt;/em&gt; is powered by 580 m2 of sails and carries 250 tonnes of cargo. The 60 metre long &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is powered by almost 1,000 m2 of sails and takes 500 tonnes of cargo. For comparison, the &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt; is not that much shorter at 32 metres, but she takes only 40 tonnes of cargo – twelve times less than the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;. A larger ship is also faster and saves labour. The &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt; requires a crew of seven, while the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; only has a slightly larger crew of twelve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;life-cycle-analysis-of-a-sailing-ship&#34;&gt;Life cycle analysis of a sailing ship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is still in the design phase, she will be the focus of this article. This is because the company conducted a life cycle analysis of the ship prior to building it. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As far as I know, this is the first life cycle analysis of a sailing ship ever made. The study reveals that it takes around 1,200 tonnes of carbon to build the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of those emissions are generated during steel production, and roughly one third is generated by steel working processes and other shipyard activities. Solvent-based paints as well as electric and electronic systems each account for roughly 5% of emissions. The emissions produced during the manufacturing of the sails are not included because there are no scientific data available, but a quick back-of-the-envelope calculation (for sails based on aramid fibres) signals that their contribution to the total carbon footprint is very small. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; has a carbon footprint of  2 grammes of CO2 per tonne-kilometre, which is five times less than the carbon footprint of a container ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these 1,200 tonnes of emissions are spread out over an estimated lifetime of 50 years, then the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; would have a carbon footprint of about 2 grammes of CO2 per tonne-kilometre of cargo, concludes researcher Andrew Simons, who made the life cycle analysis for the ship. This is roughly five times less than the carbon footprint of a container ship (10 grammes CO2/tonne-km) and three times less than the carbon footprint of a bulk-carrier (6 grammes CO2/tonne-km). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_looking_aft_from_aloft_on_the_deck_while_at_anchor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Looking aft from aloft on the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo; while at anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. Villiers&amp;amp;rsquo;s work vividly records the period of early 20th century maritime history when merchant sailing vessels or ‘tall ships’ were in rapid decline.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Looking aft from aloft on the &#39;Parma&#39; while at anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. Villiers&#39;s work vividly records the period of early 20th century maritime history when merchant sailing vessels or ‘tall ships’ were in rapid decline. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transporting one ton of cargo over a distance of 8,000 km (roughly the distance between the Caribbean and the Netherlands) would thus produce 16 kg of carbon with the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;, compared to 80 kg on a container ship and 48 kg on a bulk carrier. The proportions are similar for other environmental factors, such as ozone depletion, ecotoxicity, air pollution, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the sailing ship boasts a convincing advantage, it may not be as big as you might have expected. First, as Simons explains, there’s scale. A container ship or bulk carrier enjoys the same benefits over the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; as the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; enjoys over the &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt;. It can take a lot more cargo – on average 50,000 tonnes instead of 500 tonnes – and it needs only a slightly larger crew of 20-25 people. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, fossil fuel powered ships are faster than sailing ships, meaning that fewer ships are needed to transport a given amount of cargo over a given period of time. The original ship on which the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is based, sailed between the Netherlands and Indonesia in 65 to 78 days, while a container ship does it in about half the time (taking the short cut through the Suez canal).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-a-fleet-of-sailing-ships&#34;&gt;Building a fleet of sailing ships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s two ways to further lower the carbon emissions of sailing ships in comparison to container ships and bulk carriers. One is to build ships from wood instead of steel, such as the &lt;em&gt;Ceiba&lt;/em&gt;. If the harvested trees are allowed to grow back (which the makers of the Ceiba have promised), such a ship may even be considered a carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there’s a good reason why the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; will be made from steel: the company’s aim is to build not just one ship, but a fleet of them. Jorne Langelaan: “There are few shipyards who can deliver wooden ships nowadays. Steel makes it easier to build a fleet in a shorter period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible compromise would be a composite construction, in which a steel skeleton is clad with timber keel, planks, and deck. Andrew Simons: “This would reduce the carbon footprint of construction by half. It could also be feasible to make superstructures and some of the mast sections and spars from timber instead of steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_driving_sprays_over_the_main_deck_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Driving sprays over the main deck of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Driving sprays over the main deck of the &#39;Parma&#39;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the future, another possibility to further decrease a sailings ship’s emissions per tonne-km is to build it even larger. While the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; has much more cargo capacity than the cargo sailing ships now in operation, she is far from the largest sailing ship ever built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical ships such as the &lt;em&gt;Great Republic&lt;/em&gt; (5,000 tonnes), the &lt;em&gt;Parma&lt;/em&gt; (5,300 tonnes), the &lt;em&gt;France II&lt;/em&gt; (7,300 tonnes), and the &lt;em&gt;Preussen&lt;/em&gt; (7,800 tonnes), were more than 100 metres long and could take more than ten times the freight capacity of the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;. Langelaan already dreams of a &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper3000&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;passengers&#34;&gt;Passengers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cargo sailing ships travelling across the oceans today can also take some passengers. Fully loaded with cargo, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; takes 12 crew members, 12 passengers, and 8 trainees (passengers who learn how to sail). If the upper hold deck is not used for cargo, another 28 trainees can join, so that the ship can take up to 60 people on board (with a smaller cargo volume: 480 m3 instead of 880 m3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carbon footprint for passengers amounts to 10 g per passenger-km, compared to roughly 100 g per passenger-km on an airplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, and &lt;a href=&#34;./2008/06/life-without-airplanes-from-london-to-new-york-in-3-days-and-12-hours/&#34;&gt;since ocean liners have disappeared&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; also becomes an alternative to the airplane. According to the results of the life cycle analysis, the carbon footprint for passengers on the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; amounts to 10 grammes per passenger-kilometre, compared to roughly 100 grammes per passenger-kilometre on an airplane. Transporting one passenger thus produces as much carbon emissions as transporting 1 tonne of freight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;engine-or-not&#34;&gt;Engine or not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the life cycle analysis of the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; assumes that there is no diesel engine on-board. On a sailing ship, a diesel engine can serve two purposes, which can be combined. First, it allows to propel the ship when there is no wind or when sails cannot be used, for example when leaving or entering a harbour. Second, combined with a generator, a diesel engine can produce electricity for daily life on board of the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of history, energy use on-board of a sailing ship was not too problematic. There was firewood for cooking and heating, and there were candles and oil lamps for lighting. There were no refrigerators for food storage, no showers or laundry machines for washing and cleaning, no electronic instruments for navigation and communication, no electric pumps in case of leaks or fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we now have higher standards in terms of safety, health, hygiene, thermal comfort, and convenience. The problem is that these higher standards are difficult to achieve when the ship does not have an engine that runs on fossil fuels. Modern heating systems, cooking devices, hot water boilers, refrigerators, freezers, lighting, safety equipment, and electronic instruments all need energy to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_crewman_with_his_model_of_the_%27Parma%27_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Crewman of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo; with a model of his ship. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Crewman of the &#39;Parma&#39; with a model of his ship. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern sailing ships often use a diesel engine to provide that energy (and to propel the ship if necessary). An example is the &lt;em&gt;Avontuur&lt;/em&gt; from Timbercoast, who has an engine of 300 HP, a 20 kW generator, and a fuel tank of 2,330 litres. Large sail training vessels and cruising ships have several engines and generators on-board. For example, the 48m long &lt;em&gt;Brig Morningster&lt;/em&gt; has a 450 HP engine and three generators with a total capacity of 100 kW, while the 56m long &lt;em&gt;Bark Europa&lt;/em&gt; has two 365 HP engines with three generators – and burns hundreds of litres of oil per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the lifestyle of the people on board, the emissions per passenger-km may rise to, or surpass, the levels of those of an airplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the emissions and other pollutants of these engines need to be taken into account when the environmental footprint of a sail trip is calculated. Depending on the lifestyle of the people on board, the emissions per passenger-km may rise to, or surpass, the levels of those of an airplane. To a lesser extent, electricity use on-board also increases the emissions of cargo transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;energy-use-on-board-a-sailing-ship&#34;&gt;Energy use on board a sailing ship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; has no diesel engine on board, which is a second reason to focus on this ship. Obviously, a sailing ship without an engine cannot proceed her voyage when there’s no wind. This is &lt;a href=&#34;./2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/&#34;&gt;easily solved in the old-fashioned way&lt;/a&gt;: the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; stays where she is until the wind returns. A ship without an engine also needs tug boats – which usually burn fossil fuels – to get in and out of ports. For the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;, these tug services account for 0.3 g/tkm of the total carbon footprint of 2 g/tkm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a diesel engine, the ship also needs to generate all energy for use on board from local energy sources, and this is the hard part. Renewable energy is intermittent and has low power density compared to fossil fuels, meaning that more space is needed to generate a given amount of power – which is more problematic at sea than it is on land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_--_renewing_caulking_on_the_poop_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Renewing caulking on the poop of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Renewing caulking on the poop of the &#39;Parma&#39;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; self-sufficient in terms of energy use, a first design decision was to shift energy use away from electricity whenever possible. This is especially important for high temperature heat, which cannot be supplied by electric heat pumps. The ship will have a pellet-stove on board to provide space heating, as well as a biodigester – never before used on a ship – to convert human and kitchen waste into gas for cooking. Thermal insulation of the ship is another priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, even with pellet-stove and biodigester (which themselves require electricity to operate), and with thermal insulation, energy demand on the ship can be as high as 50 kilowatt-hours of electricity per day (2 kW average power use). This concerns a “worst-case normal operation” scenario, when the ship is sailing in cold weather with 60 people on board. Power use will be lower in warmer weather and/or when less people are taken. During an emergency, the power requirements can amount to 8 kW, while more than 24 kWh of energy can be needed in just three hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hydrogenerators&#34;&gt;Hydrogenerators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to produce this power? Solar panels and wind turbines are only a small part of the solution. Producing 50 kWh of energy per day would require at least 100 square metres of solar panels, for which there is little space on a 60 m long sailing ship. Vulnerability and shading by the sails make for further problems. Wind turbines can be attached in the rigging, but their power output is also limited. The low potential of solar and wind power are demonstrated by the earlier mentioned sailing ship &lt;em&gt;Avontuur&lt;/em&gt;. She has a 20 kW generator, powered by the diesel engine, but only 2.1 kW of solar panels and 0.8 kW of wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrogenerator is the only renewable power source that can provide a large sailing ship with enough energy for the use of modern technology on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrogenerator is the only renewable power source that can provide a large sailing ship with enough energy for the use of modern technology on board. Hydrogenerators are attached underneath the hull and work in the opposite way as a ship’s propeller. Instead of the propeller powering the ship, the ship powers the propeller, which turns a generator that produces electricity. In spite of its name and appearance, the hydrogenerator is actually a form of wind energy: the sails power the propellers. Obviously, this only works when the ship is sailing fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_furling_sail_on_the_main_yard_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Furling sail on the main yard of the Parma. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Furling sail on the main yard of the Parma. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; will be equipped with two large hydrogenerators, for which Simons calculated the power output at different speeds, taking into account the fact that the extra drag they produce slows down the ship somewhat. He concludes that the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; needs to sail at a speed of at least 7.5 knots to generate enough electricity. At that speed, the hydrogenerators produce an estimated 2,000 watts of power, which converts to roughly 50 kWh of electricity per day (24 hours of sailing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a lower speed of 4.75 knots, the generators produce 350 watts, which comes down to 8.4 kWh of energy over a period of 24 hours – only 1/6th of the maximum required energy. On the other hand, at higher speeds, the hydrogenerators produce more energy than necessary. At a speed of almost 10 knots they provide 120 kWh/day, at a speed of 12 knots this becomes 182 kWh/day – 3.5 times more than needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saltwater-batteries&#34;&gt;Saltwater batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to her hull speed, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; will be able to sail a little over 16 knots at absolute top speed – this is double the minimum speed required to generate enough power. Achieving this speed will be rare, because it needs calm seas and strong winds from the right direction. Nevertheless, in good wind conditions, the ship easily sails fast enough to produce all electricity for use on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good wind conditions can last for days, especially on the oceans, where winds are more powerful and predictable than on land. However, they are not guaranteed, and the ship will also sail at lower speeds, or find herself in becalmed conditions – when hydrogenerators are as useless as solar panels in the middle of the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because she has no engine, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; faces a double problem when there’s no wind: she cannot continue her voyage, and she has no energy to maintain life on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because she has no engine, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; faces a double problem when there’s no wind: she cannot continue her voyage, and she has no energy to maintain life on board. The first problem is easily solved but the second is not. Life on board goes on, and so there is a continued need for power. To provide this, the ship needs energy storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To cover the needs for three days drifting in cold weather, an energy storage of 150 kWh would be required, not taking into account charge and discharge losses. Five or seven days of energy use on-board would require 250 to 350 kWh of storage. For emergency use, another 25 kWh of energy storage is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_scraping_the_deck_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Scraping the deck onboard the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Scraping the deck onboard the &#39;Parma&#39;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not having an engine, generator and fuel tank saves space on board, but this advantage can be quickly lost again when one starts to add batteries for the hydrogenerators. Lithium-ion batteries are very compact, but they cannot be considered sustainable and bring safety risks. That’s why Jorne Langelaan and Andrew Simons see more potential in – very aptly – saltwater batteries, which are non-flammable, non-toxic, easy to recycle, have wide temperature-tolerance, and can last for more than 15 years. Like the biodigester, they have never been used on a sailing ship before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike lithium-ion batteries, saltwater batteries are large and heavy. At 60 kg per kWh of storage capacity, a 150 kWh battery storage would add a weight of 9 tonnes, while a 350 kWh storage capacity would add 21 tonnes. Still, this compares favourably to the total cargo capacity (500 tonnes), and the batteries can serve as ballast if they are placed in the lower part of the ship’s hull. The space requirements are not too problematic, either. Even a 350 kWh energy storage only requires 14 to 29m3 of space, which is small compared to the 880m3 of cargo volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emissions that are produced by the manufacturing of the hydrogenerators, biodigester, and batteries are not included in the life cycle analysis of the ship, because there are no data available. However, these emissions must be relatively small. Hydrogenerators have much higher power density than wind turbines, and thus a relatively low embodied energy. A quick back-of-the-envelope calculation learns that the carbon footprint of 350 kWh saltwater batteries is around 70 tonnes of CO2. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;human-power&#34;&gt;Human Power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another renewable power source and energy storage on board of the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper&lt;/em&gt;, and that’s the humans themselves. Like the pellet stove and the biodigester, the use of human power could reduce the need for electricity. Nowadays, cargo ships and most large sailing ships have electric or hydraulic winches, pumps, and steering gear, saving manual labour at the expense of higher energy use. In contrast, &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper&lt;/em&gt; sticks to manual handling of the ship as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_crew_at_the_capstan_weighing_anchor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Crew at the capstan of the Parma, weighing anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Crew at the capstan of the Parma, weighing anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simons and Langelaan are also considering the addition of a few rowing machines, coupled to generators, to produce emergency power. Two rowing machines could provide roughly 400 watts of power. If they are operated around the clock in shifts, they could supply the ship with an extra 9.6 kWh of energy per day (ignoring energy losses) – one fifth of the total maximum electricity use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as I tell Simons and Langelaan ten rowing machines operated continually in shifts would provide as much power as the hydrogenerators at a speed of 7.5 knots. If there are 60 people on board, and everybody would generate power for less than one hour per day, no hydrogenerators and batteries would be needed at all. “A very interesting thought”, answers Simons, “but what impression would we be painted with?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hot-showers&#34;&gt;Hot Showers?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with a biodigester, hydrogenerators, batteries, and rowing machines, the passengers and crew on board the EcoClipper500 would be far short of luxurious, and perhaps too short of comfortable for some. For example, if 60 people on board the ship would take a daily hot shower – &lt;a href=&#34;./2019/10/mist-showers-sustainable-decadence/&#34;&gt;which requires on average 2.1 kilowatt-hours of energy and 76.5 litres of water on land&lt;/a&gt; – total electricity use per day would be 126 kWh, more than double the energy the ship produces at a speed of 7.5 knots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ship could supply this energy at a higher sailing speed, but there would also be a need for 4,590 liters of water per day, a quantity that could only be produced from seawater – a process that requires a lot of energy. Even a crew of 12 taking a daily hot shower would require 25.2 kWh of energy per day, half of what the hydrogenerators produce at a sailing speed of 7.5 knots. The &lt;em&gt;Bark Europa&lt;/em&gt; is the only sailing ship mentioned in this article that has hot showers in every (shared) cabin, but it is also the ship with the biggest generators and the highest fuel use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_on_the_forecastle_in_fine_weather_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;On the forecastle head of the Parma in fine weather. Image by Alan Villiers, 1932.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 On the forecastle head of the Parma in fine weather. Image by Alan Villiers, 1932. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Simons: “On the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; there needs to be a manageable compromise between energy use and comfort. Energy use on board will have to be actively managed. Resources are finite, just like for the planet. In many ways the ship is a microcosm of challenges that the wider world has to face and find solutions to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jorne Langelaan: “At sea you are in a different world. It doesn’t matter anymore if you can take a daily shower or not. What matters are the people, the movements of the ship, and the vast wilderness of ocean around you”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;measuring-the-right-things&#34;&gt;Measuring the right things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article has compared the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; sailing ship with the average container ship, bulk carrier, and airplane in terms of emissions per tonne- or passenger-kilometer. However, these values are abstractions that obscure much more important information: the total emissions that are produced by all passengers and all cargo, over all kilometres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The international ocean freight trade increased from 4 billion tonnes of cargo in 1990 to 11.2 billion tonnes in 2019, resulting in more than 1 billion tonnes of emissions. International air passenger numbers grew from 1 billion in 1990 to 4.5 billion in 2019, resulting in 915 million tonnes of emissions. Consequently, lowering the emissions per tonne- and passenger-kilometre is neither a necessity nor a guarantee for a reduction in emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we cut international cargo traffic more than fivefold, and passenger traffic more than tenfold, then the emissions of all container ships and airplanes would be lower than the emissions of all sailing ships carrying 11.2 billion tonnes of cargo and 4.5 billion of passengers. Vice versa, if we switch to sailing ships, but keep on transporting more and more cargo and passengers across the planet, we will eventually produce just as much in emissions as we do today with fossil fuel powered transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Grace_Harwar_-_the_mizzen_of_the_ship;_view_aft_from_the_main_crosstrees_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The mizzen of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Grace Harwar&amp;amp;rsquo;; view aft from the main crosstrees. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The mizzen of the &#39;Grace Harwar&#39;; view aft from the main crosstrees. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this would ever happen. The amount of cargo that was traded across the oceans in 2019 equals the freight capacity of 22.4 million &lt;em&gt;EcoClippers&lt;/em&gt;. Assuming the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; can make 2-3 trips per year, we would need to build and operate at least 7.5 million ships, with a total crew of at least 90 million people. Those ships could only take 0.5 billion passengers (12 passengers and 8 trainees per ship), so we would need millions of ships and crew members more to replace international air traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should not be fooled by abstract relative measurements, which only serve to keep the focus on growth and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is technically possible, and as we have seen, it would produce less in emissions than the present alternatives. However, it’s more likely that a switch to sailing ships is accompanied by a decrease in cargo and passenger traffic, and this has everything to do with scale and speed. A lot of freight and passengers would not be travelling if it were not for the high speeds and low costs of today’s airplanes and container ships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would make little sense to transport iPhones parts, Amazon wares, sweatshop clothes, or citytrippers with sailing ships. A sailing ship is more than a technical means of transportation: it implies another view on consumption, production, time, space, leisure, and travel. For example, a lot of freight now travels in different directions for each next processing stage before it is delivered as a final product. In contrast, all sail cargo companies mentioned in this article only take cargo that cannot be produced locally, and which is one trip from producer to consumer. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that even if sailing ships have diesel engines on board, they would still bring a significant decrease in the total emissions for freight and passenger traffic, simply because they would reduce the absolute number of passengers, cargo, and kilometers. We should not be fooled by abstract relative measurements, which only serve to keep the focus on growth and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ecoclipper.org/&#34;&gt;More about the EcoClipper500&lt;/a&gt;. Most images: &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Photographs_by_Alan_Villiers&#34;&gt;Alan Villiers collection&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1978 and 2004, the Avontuur was operated as sail cargo vessel under Captain Paul Wahlen. The Apollonia, originally built in 1946, is another cargo sailing ship in operation since 2014. It is 19.5 metres long and carries 10 tonnes of cargo.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very recently, &lt;a href=&#34;https://graindesail.com/fr/&#34;&gt;Grain de Sail&lt;/a&gt; was built and launched for Trans-Atlantic shipping of wine and cocoa. She is a modern sailing ship without an engine, built from aluminium, and can take 35 tonnes of cargo.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Simons: “There are plenty historical sailing ships, but either very costly to get into service as a regulatory compliant cargo vessel, because they are still used for other purposes, or not suitable.”&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study can be downloaded when you subscribe to EcoClipper&amp;rsquo;s newsletter. The research is based on a typical life cycle analysis, but note that this is not a peer reviewed study.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the envelope got lost.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the EcoClipper, most of the emissions are produced during the construction of the ship, while in the case of bulk carriers and container ships, they are mainly produced during operation and fuel production.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest container ships now take 190,000 tonnes of cargo.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not much data available on saltwater batteries, but they are less energy-intensive to build than many other types of batteries. The calculation is based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.solarquotes.com.au/blog/aquion-salt-water-battery/&#34;&gt;an estimate of 66 kg CO2/kWh of storage capacity&lt;/a&gt; and three generations of batteries over a period of 50 years.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost one third of all cargo transported are fossil fuels themselves.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Could We Dredge the Netherlands Without Fossil Fuels?</title>
      <link>./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/krabbelaar_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="32815" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/krabbelaar_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;1699 scale model of a scratcher rigged with sails. Image: Maritiem Digitaal&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 1699 scale model of a scratcher rigged with sails. Image: [Maritiem Digitaal](http://www.maritiemdigitaal.nl/index.cfm?event=page.home) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dredging industry has been the backbone of the Dutch economy for centuries. If canals, harbours and rivers would not be maintained for a few years, the whole country would literally grind to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, dredging happens with oil powered ships, which burn up to 3,000 litres of fuel per hour. However, in earlier times, the Dutch waterways were dredged mostly by hand, using simple but ingenious tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manual dredging was heavy labour, especially when waterways became deeper. Therefore, it was supplemented by animal power, wind power and tidal power. However, in some parts of the Netherlands, people chose a different strategy: they designed a new type of cargo ship that could sail in shallow waterways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;35-million-m-of-mud&#34;&gt;35 million m³ of mud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siltation is a serious problem in the Netherlands, which lies in the delta area of various rivers that supply large amounts of silt and clay particles. At the same time, navigable waterways are essential to maintain transportation and trade — the country is home to the largest port in Europe, Rotterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year, some 30 to 35 million m³ of mud are dredged out for the maintenance of the Dutch waterways. Approximately 75% comes from salty waters. In the port of Rotterdam alone, 20 million m³ of mud is collected each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demand for dredging continues to increase. Both inland ships and seagoing vessels continue to get bigger, requiring ever deeper and wider waterways. A &amp;ldquo;modal shift&amp;rdquo; policy, in which cargo transport moves from the road to the water in order to improve sustainability and reduce congestion, also leads to more and larger ships, and thus to more dredging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/dredging-by-hand_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Dredging by hand in Delft, the Netherlands. Image: Maritiem Digitaal.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Dredging by hand in Delft, the Netherlands. Image: [Maritiem Digitaal](http://www.maritiemdigitaal.nl). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although most of the mud is dumped into the sea, each year 3.5 to 5 million m³ of contaminated sediments must be landfilled. Then there is the dependency on fossil fuels. A typical suction hopper dredger has a pumping power of 2,500 kW and removes 100 m³ of sediments per minute. The largest dredgers have 30,000 kW engines and 6,000 kW of pumping power. At full power, these ships consume 3,000 litres of oil per hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dredging-a-country-by-hand&#34;&gt;Dredging a Country by Hand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silting is a very old problem in the Netherlands, so how did this job happen before the arrival of fossil fuel powered dredging machines and boats?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For centuries, the Netherlands were mainly dredged by hand. Dredgers stood on a small boat and scraped mud from the bottom with their &amp;ldquo;dredge bag&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;baggerbeugel&amp;rdquo;). In an alternative configuration, the dredger stood on a wooden board that was supported by the river bank on one side, and by a floating container on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/baggerbeugel_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A dredging bag. Image: Maritiem Digitaal&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A dredging bag. Image: [Maritiem Digitaal](http://www.maritiemdigitaal.nl/index.cfm?event=page.home) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/beugelaar_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Dredging by hand, standing on a boat. Image.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Dredging by hand, standing on a boat. [Image](https://www.yumpu.com/nl/document/view/18609381/pre-industrial-dredging-rosmolens-en-krabbelaars-baggeren-vssd/2).  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/gieterse-methode_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Handling a dredge bag.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Handling a dredge bag. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dredge bag, a tool that was also used for peat cutting, was a long stick (up to 6 metres long) with an annular metal scraper and a net at the end. There were different types of nets and bags, depending on the composition of the sediment. Working with the dredge bag, the handle was rested against the shoulder, so that the net could be dragged over the bottom with two hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For large dredging works, thousands of workers with dredging bags were deployed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mud was pulled ashore or deposited in a flat barge. For large dredging works, such as the construction of the Northern Holland Canal in 1822-1825, thousands of workers with dredging bags were deployed. Until about 1960, contractors of dredging works employed men with dredging bags for the maintenance of shallow ditches and canals. The tool is still for sale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dredge-mills&#34;&gt;Dredge Mills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manual dredging is heavy and time-consuming work, so people designed technology that could ease and speed up the task. Furthermore, ships became ever larger. In the last quarter of the sixteenth century, the &amp;ldquo;dredge mill&amp;rdquo; was introduced, which worked up to a depth of two metres. It was still based on human power, but now people were merely the power source for a machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a dredge mill, a group of people worked large treadmills or capstans, which drove a paddle wheel that scooped the mud from the bottom and threw it into a barge that was moored across. The dredge mill was usually made up of two flat barges with the rotating wheel in between. These machines were often operated by prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/dredging-mill_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Dredge mill operated by prisoners. Image: Beeldarchief Rijkswaterstaat.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Dredge mill operated by prisoners. Image: [Beeldarchief Rijkswaterstaat](https://beeldbank.rws.nl/MediaObject/Details/331290). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one century later, the depth of a merchant ship had increased to between 3.5 and 5 metres — and this was too deep for the human powered dredge mill. In 1622, the first horse-powered dredge mill was built. Three to six horses ran a pivot which set in motion a bucket chain. The horses had to be changed every hour because of the heavy labour involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1829, horse powered dredge mills could be used to dredge up to a depth of 5-7 metres. If working at a depth of 3.2 metres, with three to six horses, approximately 20 m³ of mud could be collected each hour. By comparison, the average modern suction dredger — which removes 100 m³ of mud per minute — is as powerful as 300 horse powered dredge mills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/mechanical-dredge-bags-on-pontoon_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Mechanical dredge bags on a pontoon. Image.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Mechanical dredge bags on a pontoon. [Image](https://www.yumpu.com/nl/document/view/18609381/pre-industrial-dredging-rosmolens-en-krabbelaars-baggeren-vssd/2). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original dredging techniques were also improved. Mechanical dredge bags emerged in the sixteenth century, when someone got the idea to pull the dredging bag with a rope over a winch. Mechanical dredge bags could be mounted on ships, but several dredge bags and winches could also work side by side on a pontoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first half of the nineteenth century the valve barge was invented. The bottom of this small boat could be opened without causing it to sink. In this way, it took less time to remove the mud. The technique is still used in some modern dredgers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/Valve-barge-with-dredge-bag_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Valve barge with dredge bag. Image: Maritiem Digitaal.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Valve barge with dredge bag. Image: [Maritiem Digitaal](http://www.maritiemdigitaal.nl/index.cfm?event=page.home). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;scratchers&#34;&gt;Scratchers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dutch also took advantage of renewable energy sources to lighten the work — in particular wind and tidal power. From the fifteenth century onwards, the &amp;ldquo;scratcher&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;krabbelaar&amp;rdquo;) was used, a scraper that could dredge gullies if there was enough current.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a strong current, dredging becomes easier, because the mud only needs to be loosened. The tide ensures the discharge of the material to the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/human-powered-scratcher_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Human powered scratcher. Source: Maritiem Digitaal.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Human powered scratcher. Source: [Maritiem Digitaal](http://www.maritiemdigitaal.nl/index.cfm?event=page.home). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/human-powered-scratcher-model_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Human powered scratcher. Source unknown.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Human powered scratcher. Source unknown. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple scratchers were a kind of large rakes that were dragged across the bed of the water body. These were pulled by horses or people — some were pulled by a rowing boat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wind-powered-dredgers&#34;&gt;Wind Powered Dredgers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In harbours with strong winds and tides, scratchers were rigged with sails. These triangular sailing ships had a broad stern and a flat bottom. Attached to the bottom was a harrow with iron spikes. At mid tide, the scratcher was placed just before the lock gates of a scouring basin, which was filled during high tide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low tide, the sluice gates of the basin were opened and the scratcher was pushed through the harbour with great force as the iron teeth scraped across the bottom. The ship gathered extra speed through the wide stern and, if the wind was good, the use of sails. Horses could also be used, pulling the ship in the absence of good winds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low tide, the sluice gates of the basin were opened and the scratcher was pushed through the harbour with great force as the iron teeth scraped across the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wind powered scratchers were in use at least since 1435 in the southeastern part of the Netherlands. The flat bottom of the scratcher hinged and could sink with the help of cables to improve the draft. Two revolving doors, which could make a sharp angle of about 45 degrees with the ship, increased the reach of the barge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/wind-powered-scratcher-backside_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Backside of a wind powered scratcher.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Backside of a wind powered scratcher. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, manpower was still needed. Five to six men kept the monster in the right lane, while two to three men kept the harrow at the desired depth through pulleys and hoist blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;alternatives-to-dredging&#34;&gt;Alternatives to Dredging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dredging was not the only answer to the siltation of waterways. Until the nineteenth century, the choice was also made to increase the height of river banks and dikes, so that the water level was allowed to rise. This was especially true for large rivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a report from 1825, the dredging of large rivers was not considered a possibility because they were too deep and too wide for the technology of those days. It was only with steam power that dredging was also done on major rivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./2018/08/could-we-dredge-the-netherlands-without-fossil-fuels/images/dithers/skutje_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Frisian Skûtsje. Image: Skûtsje Langwar&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Frisian Skûtsje. Image: [Skûtsje Langwar](http://skutsjelangwar.nl) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The province of Friesland, in the north of the country, reveals yet another alternative to dredging. The Frisians never used dredge mills, horse mills or other tools than dredge bags. They continued to dredge by hand until the arrival of the steam engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, they innovated in a different way: from 1889 to 1933, they built 1,200 large cargo ships with a very limited draft — the so-called &amp;ldquo;skûtjes&amp;rdquo;. Obviously, boats with a smaller draft meant less dredging. The strategy reminds of the medieval &lt;a href=&#34;./2011/12/how-to-downsize-a-transport-network-the-chinese-wheelbarrow/&#34;&gt;Chinese wheelbarrow&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed transportation to keep functioning at a time when the road infrastructure was crumbling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-many-people-do-we-need&#34;&gt;How many people do we need?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a more sustainable future, could we dredge the Netherlands without fossil fuels? Sustainability is all about cars and smart appliances, but what about large infrastructure and maintenance works? Powering today&amp;rsquo;s dredgers with solar or wind power sounds unrealistic: those ships would require enormous chemical batteries, which is not practical or sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.humanpowerplant.be&#34;&gt;Human Power Plant&lt;/a&gt;, we investigated how many people would be needed if we were to dredge the Netherlands by hand again. To answer this question, we &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.humanpowerplant.be/manual-dredging-workshop-may-24.html&#34;&gt;organised a workshop&lt;/a&gt; in which we dredged a piece of Frisian waterway by hand and measured how long it takes to collect 1 m³ of mud. The results are discussed in the video below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For English substitles, click CC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/A47LkB4-ZmM?cc_load_policy=1&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;autoplay; encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviews and documentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationaalbaggermuseum.nl/&#34;&gt;Nationaal Baggermuseum&lt;/a&gt;, Sliedrecht, Rotterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canon van de geschiedenis van Smallingerland, Smelne&amp;rsquo;s Erfskip 2010; Drachtstervaart, Smelne&amp;rsquo;s Erfskip 2015, ISBN 978-94-90543-08-02.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geschiedenis van de Techniek in Nederland. De wording van een moderne samenleving (1800-1890). H.W. Lintsen, 1992.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.yumpu.com/nl/document/view/18609381/pre-industrial-dredging-rosmolens-en-krabbelaars-baggeren-vssd/2&#34;&gt;Rosmolens en krabbelaars: baggeren in pre-industriële tijd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maritiemdigitaal.nl/&#34;&gt;Maritiem Digitaal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hdsr.nl/publish/pages/2230/grootonderhoudsplan_baggeren_2015_tot_2020.pdf&#34;&gt;Groot onderhoudsplan Baggeren 2015 tot 2020&lt;/a&gt;. Hoogheemraadschap de Stichtse Rijnlanden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uitvoeringsplan 2010 Meerjarenbaggerprogramma Waterschap Rivierenland&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zeeuwseankers.nl/nl-NL/verhaal/1282/scheepsmodel-krabbelaar&#34;&gt;Scheepsmodel Krabbelaar&lt;/a&gt;, Katie Heyning, Zeeuwse Ankers, juli 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluatie van het Friese Merenproject, 2000-2010, Provincie Fryslân.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wetterskipfryslan.nl/documenten-catalogus/schoon/baggeren-en-waterbodem/baggeruitvoeringsplan-2007-2015.pdf/view&#34;&gt;Baggeruitvoeringsplan 2007-2015&lt;/a&gt;. Wetterskip Fryslân&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clo.nl/indicatoren/nl0210-baggerproblematiek-in-nederland&#34;&gt;Baggerproblematiek in Nederland&lt;/a&gt;, Compendium voor de leefomgeving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;ttps://www.wshd.nl/binaries/content/assets/wshd---website/common/werken/meerjaren-baggerplan-2012-2018.pdf&#34;&gt;Meerjarenbaggerplan 2012-2018&lt;/a&gt;, Waterschap Hollandse Delta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maritiemnederland.com/achtergrond/hoe-was-het-ook-weer-1687/item1687&#34;&gt;Baggerschepen: van baggermolen tot sleephopperzuiger&lt;/a&gt; Maritiem Nederland.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
