<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/tags/clothes/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/tags/clothes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Revenge of the Hot Water Bottle</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/hot-water-bottles-bar-terrace_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="40997" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/hot-water-bottles-bar-terrace_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hot water bottles could save a great deal of energy and money without sacrificing thermal comfort. They work both indoors and outdoors. Illustration: Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hot water bottles could save a great deal of energy and money without sacrificing thermal comfort. They work both indoors and outdoors. Illustration: Marie Verdeil. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hot water bottle is a sealable container filled with hot water, often enclosed in a textile cover, which is directly placed against a part of the body for thermal comfort. The hot water bottle is still a common household item in some places – such as the UK and Japan – but it is largely forgotten or disregarded in most of the industrialised world. If people know of it, they usually associate it with pain relief rather than thermal comfort, or they consider its use an outdated practice for the poor and the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, when I sent two dozen hot water bottles to friends and family as a Christmas present, the reactions were almost unanimously enthusiastic. People show themselves very much surprised that such a humble object can provide so much comfort. Because I don’t have the time nor the budget to send hot water bottles to everyone, I have written this article. It’s largely based on my personal experience – I have been using hot water bottles for many years and they are the only heat source in my apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-history-of-the-hot-water-bottle&#34;&gt;The history of the hot water bottle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Croat inventor Eduard Penkala patented the rubber hot water bottle – which he dubbed the “Termofor” – in 1903. However, it did not come out of nowhere. In fact, the history of the hot water bottle goes back thousands of years, albeit in different guises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/warmwaterzak_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Rubber hot water bottle, made in Germany (1925-35). Source: Museum Rotterdam.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Rubber hot water bottle, made in Germany (1925-35). Source: [Museum Rotterdam](https://museumrotterdam.nl/collectie/item/76113-A-B). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first “hot water bottles” – quite literally – were other people and animals. Since time immemorial, people have warmed themselves by huddling together. For example, it was common for the whole family to sleep together in the same bed – and this included potential visitors. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; People also took advantage of the heat from animals – “hot water bottles” with a standard fur cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They snuggled up against cows and pigs, which were either sharing the living space or lived in the stables below it. In the eighteenth century, wealthy women kept specially bred “hand dogs” – toy poodles – around to keep their lap and hands warm. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Personal heating devices also took the form of objects – stones, bricks, potatoes – that were heated in or near the fire, wrapped in cloth or paper, and kept in people’s laps, in pockets, or in the bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As early as the 1500s, people started to use all kinds of portable containers filled with hot coals from the fire. These were used as foot warmers, hand warmers, and bed warmers. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Most were made of metal, either brass or copper, and placed inside wooden or ceramic enclosures to prevent skin burns. Over time, hot coals were replaced by hot water, which is a cleaner and safer heat storage medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, these first “real” hot water bottles were made from hard materials such as glass, metal, or stoneware. It was only with the invention of vulcanised rubber in the nineteenth century that more comfortable lightweight and flexible hot water bottles became an option. Spanish friends told me that hot water bottles used to be made from animal skins, but I could not verify this. It may well be true, because all over the world there’s a long tradition of using “water skins” for storing liquids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/VictorianCollections-large_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;An example of a hot water bottle in common use in households in the mid 20th century before the use of rubber ones (1940s, Melbourne, Australia). Source: Victorian Collections. https://victoriancollections.net.au/items/5a2622e921ea6a17dcba0799.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 An example of a hot water bottle in common use in households in the mid 20th century before the use of rubber ones (1940s, Melbourne, Australia). Source: Victorian Collections. [https://victoriancollections.net.au/items/5a2622e921ea6a17dcba0799](https://victoriancollections.net.au/items/5a2622e921ea6a17dcba0799). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/Copper-foment-can-England-1880-1930_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A foment can is filled with hot water and used very much like a hot-water bottle to apply warmth to the body. Fomentation actually means “to apply warm liquids to treat the skin.” This oval-shaped can is curved to fit the body. Maker: Kenworthy Son and Company. Place made: Southport, Sefton, Merseyside, England, United Kingdom. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). https://wellcomecollection.org/works/gf42542b.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A foment can is filled with hot water and used very much like a hot-water bottle to apply warmth to the body. Fomentation actually means “to apply warm liquids to treat the skin.” This oval-shaped can is curved to fit the body. Maker: Kenworthy Son and Company. Place made: Southport, Sefton, Merseyside, England, United Kingdom. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). [https://wellcomecollection.org/works/gf42542b](https://wellcomecollection.org/works/gf42542b). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/Hexagonal-hot-water-bottle-Austria-1791-1798_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hexagonal hot-water bottle, Austria, 1791-1798. This hexagonal hot-water bottle is made of pewter and is engraved with a forest scene. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). https://wellcomecollection.org/works/b452vwjm.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hexagonal hot-water bottle, Austria, 1791-1798. This hexagonal hot-water bottle is made of pewter and is engraved with a forest scene. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). [https://wellcomecollection.org/works/b452vwjm](https://wellcomecollection.org/works/b452vwjm). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/foot-warmer-Lister-Ward_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;This foot warmer (made in 1927) was used to give warmth and comfort to patients who were resting in the hospital wards. Made from tinned iron, the warmer would have been filled with hot water and secured with a cork. Place made: Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). https://wellcomecollection.org/works/mfjujndv&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 This foot warmer (made in 1927) was used to give warmth and comfort to patients who were resting in the hospital wards. Made from tinned iron, the warmer would have been filled with hot water and secured with a cork. Place made: Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). [https://wellcomecollection.org/works/mfjujndv](https://wellcomecollection.org/works/mfjujndv) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/M0354_930804-004_1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;French foot warmer, date unknown. Source: Musée Départemental Albert Demard&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 French foot warmer, date unknown. Source: Musée Départemental Albert Demard 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hot-water-bottles-today&#34;&gt;Hot water bottles today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classical hot water bottle for sale today is either made from rubber or PVC plastic. The latter material has few advantages. It’s often a bit cheaper and can be made transparant, but unlike rubber it contains toxic chemicals (which make the plastic flexible). A third option – a bit harder to find – are plastic hot water bottles without chemical softeners, which are rigid instead of flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinctly shaped Japanese hot water bottle – the “yutampo” – is usually of that type. Its use dates back to the fifteenth century when it was made from metal or stoneware. Of course any sealable container can function as a hot water bottle. I have successfully used metal drinking bottles and even plastic PET-bottles – more about those later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of its dull image, the hot water bottle has seen some interesting innovations lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical hot water bottle has a rectangular shape and holds up to two litres of water. However, in spite of its dull image, the hot water bottle has seen some interesting innovations lately. A first novelty are much smaller rectangular bottles, which hold between 0.2 and 0.8 litres of water. Judging by their covers, these are mostly aimed at children, but they can be just as useful for adults who can carry them in pockets or put them inside clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now also larger hot water bottles available, which hold up to three litres of water or more. Finally, the most successful novelty has the form of a hot dog: it’s a hot water bottle 80 centimetres long. It can be tied around the waist but is just as practical as a companion on the couch or in the bed. It can easily be shared by two people and its shape makes it luxuriously comfortable. It holds up to two litres of water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/waterbottle002_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Rubber and PVC hot water bottles. Image by Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Rubber and PVC hot water bottles. Image by Marie Verdeil.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/waterbottle005_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Rubber hot water bottles. Image by Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Rubber hot water bottles. Image by Marie Verdeil.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/yutampo2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Japanese hot water bottle, or yutampo, made of hard plastic. Source: All About Japan. https://allabout-japan.com/en/article/6244/&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Japanese hot water bottle, or yutampo, made of hard plastic. Source: All About Japan. [https://allabout-japan.com/en/article/6244/](https://allabout-japan.com/en/article/6244/) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/maruka-yutampo_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Japanese yutampo is still available in metal. Source: Maruka.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Japanese yutampo is still available in metal. Source: Maruka.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-use-hot-water-bottles&#34;&gt;How to use hot water bottles?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who know hot water bottles usually think of them as bed companions. However, they can keep you warm wherever you are, throughout the day. This includes the sofa, of course, but you can also surround yourself with one or more hot water bottles when seated at a desk or a table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use one, two, or exceptionally three hot water bottles simultaneously, depending on the indoor temperature. They usually end up in my lap, behind my lower back, and/or under my feet. Although only some body parts are directly heated, the warmth from the bottle(s) is distributed throughout the body by skin blood flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot water bottles can be combined with a blanket, which further increases thermal comfort. If I put a blanket over the lower part of my body when seated at my desk, it traps the heat from the bottles and keeps them warm for longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better is a blanket with a hole in the middle to stick your head through – a basic poncho – or a blanket with sleeves. If it’s large enough, it creates a tent-like structure that puts your whole body in the warm microclimate created by the water bottles. Draping long clothes over a personal heat source was a common comfort strategy in earlier times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/hot-water-bottles-kotatsu-grey-background_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A blanket traps the heat of hot water bottles. Illustration by Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A blanket traps the heat of hot water bottles. Illustration by Marie Verdeil.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can go one more step further and put a large blanket over the desk or table and then put your legs underneath it. Such heating arrangements have been used in different parts of the world, usually with hot coals as the heat storage medium. Examples are the Japanese “kotatsu”, the Middle-Eastern “korsi”, and the Spanish “brasero de picon”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two are rather low to the ground – people sit on the floor – while the latter fits the common seat height in the Western world. It’s easy to build such a heating arrangement – and a few hot water bottles are the ultimate heat source for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hot-water-bottles-outdoors--on-the-move&#34;&gt;Hot water bottles outdoors &amp;amp; on the move&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrangements described above only work for people who stay in one place. The need for an external heat source decreases when we move around and are physically active, because our body produces more heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, hot water bottles can also keep you warm when you are standing up doing things or when you are moving through a space or a building. They can be worn underneath clothing or even put in specially designed pockets or backpacks. A small backpack holding a hot water bottle – positioned between the shoulder blades – also works great while sitting on a chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/hot-water-bottles-school_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hot water bottles provide thermal comfort with all the windows open. Illustration by Marie Verdeil.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hot water bottles provide thermal comfort with all the windows open. Illustration by Marie Verdeil.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot water bottles work both indoors and outdoors – provided that the body is protected from wind and rain – or indoors with the all the windows open. Modern central heating systems provide thermal comfort mainly by heating the air in a space, an approach that obviously won’t work well outdoors or in a well-ventilated indoor space. In contrast, hot water bottles transfer heat directly to people through physical contact (a heat transfer method called “conduction”). &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/&#34;&gt;They heat people, not spaces&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes hot water bottles a safe and sustainable alternative for terrace heaters in bars and restaurants. The investment is minimal: a collection of hot water bottles and a kettle – the water can be re-used over and over again. Alternatively, everyone could bring their own hot water bottle and fill it up on the terrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot water bottles are a safe and sustainable alternative for terrace heaters in bars and restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could take this idea even further and envision a public infrastructure for refilling hot water bottles, not just on bar terraces but in multiple locations such as schools, offices, and public buildings. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; People could gather around the hot water dispenser just like they gather around the water cooler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, hot water bottles – and their predecessors using hot coals – were also taken out of the house. Their use was common in coaches and trains, as well as in churches, which were unheated. Smaller hot water containers with carrying strings and fabric covers were put into fur muffs or pockets. Nowadays, you could also store hot water in a vacuum flask and then pour it into a hot water bottle hours later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/Stoneware_Queens_Muff_Warmer_H_as151a1645z_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Stoneware Queens Muff Warmer. Source: Antiques Atlas. https://www.antiques-atlas.com.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Stoneware Queens Muff Warmer. Source: Antiques Atlas. [https://www.antiques-atlas.com](https://www.antiques-atlas.com). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/Curved-rectangular-hot-water-bottle-France-1751-1810_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Curved rectangular hot-water bottle, France, 1751-1810. Made of pewter, an alloy of tin and lead, this hot-water bottle is engraved with birds and plants and has a curved shape to fit close against the body. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). https://wellcomecollection.org/works/g5ufhayn.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Curved rectangular hot-water bottle, France, 1751-1810. Made of pewter, an alloy of tin and lead, this hot-water bottle is engraved with birds and plants and has a curved shape to fit close against the body. Source: Science Museum, London. (CC BY 4.0). [https://wellcomecollection.org/works/g5ufhayn](https://wellcomecollection.org/works/g5ufhayn).  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;900-hot-water-bottles-per-day-energy-savings&#34;&gt;900 hot water bottles per day: energy savings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, there’s little – or actually no – academic research into the energy savings potential of hot water bottles. Instead, in recent years scientists have investigated more sophisticated personal heating devices such as electrically heated desks and seats, radiant heat bulbs, or battery-powered heat pillows. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These alternatives look needlessly complex in comparison to the hot water bottle. Water can be heated in many ways both high-tech and low-tech, and containers can be made from locally available materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, these studies show that personal heating sources with similar effects as hot water bottles could save a great deal of energy while maintaining and often even improving thermal comfort. For example, one study revealed that lowering the air temperature in an office from 20.5°C to 18.8°C (69°F to 66°F) and giving employees a heated chair to compensate for the discomfort leads to 35% less energy use and consistently higher scores for thermal comfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few interventions in the building envelope that can achieve such large energy savings for such a small investment, and yet the decrease in air temperature was far from radical in this experiment. If personal heating devices would be &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/02/insulation-first-the-body-then-the-home/&#34;&gt;combined with a change in clothing insulation&lt;/a&gt; and/or blankets the energy savings could become much larger still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to investigate the energy savings potential of the hot water bottle is to calculate how much energy it takes to prepare one and compare that to the energy use of a central heating system. Because rubber or PVC bottles can only be filled up to two-thirds for safe and comfortable use, I assume a somewhat larger model – 3 L – which can hold two litres of water in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes the calculation also valid for containers that can be filled completely, such as the Japanese yutampo. It takes 4,200 joule to raise the temperature of 1 litre of water by 1°C, meaning that heating two litres of water from 10°C to 60°C (50°F to 140°F) requires 420 kilojoule or 116.7 watt-hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/sleep-well_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Advertisement for Westbrook &amp;amp;amp; Thompson Ltd&amp;amp;rsquo;s &amp;amp;lsquo;Cosimax&amp;amp;rsquo; hot water bottles, made with Dunlop rubber. 1938. Science Museum / Science &amp;amp;amp; Society Picture Library. Source: https://www.ssplprints.com/image/95677/sleep-well-hot-water-bottle-august-1938.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Advertisement for Westbrook &amp; Thompson Ltd&#39;s &#39;Cosimax&#39; hot water bottles, made with Dunlop rubber. 1938. Science Museum / Science &amp; Society Picture Library. Source: [https://www.ssplprints.com/image/95677/sleep-well-hot-water-bottle-august-1938](https://www.ssplprints.com/image/95677/sleep-well-hot-water-bottle-august-1938). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comparison, the average household energy use for gas heating in Belgium – which has a moderate climate – is 20,000 kWh per year. Assuming that the average Belgian heating system is used for six months per year, daily energy use corresponds to 109.6 kWh per day. This energy could heat roughly 900 water bottles per day – enough to keep the whole neighbourhood comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that four household members each use two hot water bottles simultaneously and reheat them every two hours throughout their waking hours (16 hours). Total energy use is then below 4 kilowatt-hours, almost 30 times less than the heating energy consumed by the average Belgian household.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to suggest that hot water bottles need to replace a central heating system. The rather short and mild winters here in Barcelona allow me to use hot water bottles as the only heating system because it rarely gets colder than 12°C (54°F) in my unheated apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In less hospitable climates, hot water bottles can be combined with a central heating system. The hot water bottles create islands of thermal comfort for low metabolism activities while the rest of the indoor space is comfortable to move through or be physically active in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;safety&#34;&gt;Safety&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot water is a safer heat storage medium than hot coals, but it is not without its risks and hot water bottles need to be used carefully. They carry the instruction not to use boiling water, which is very sound advice, but hot water doesn’t need to boil to be dangerous. Water above a temperature of 60°C (140°F) can scald you and lead to very serious injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it’s recommended to use only hot tap water, or any other hot water source below 60°C. This temperature is sufficiently high to make you comfortable and the only advantage of using hotter water is that you need to reheat it less often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too hot water can hurt you in several ways. First, there’s always a chance you spill water on your hands while filling the bottle. Second, a rubber or plastic hot water bottle can start leaking, either through the cap or through the seams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and this is the worst-case scenario, a hot water bottle can burst and release two liters of hot water on your body. Such accidents are rare, because nowadays hot water bottles are made according to quality standards. However, they do occur, usually because the bottle has worn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/jayne-mansfield-hot-water-bottle-ad-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Jayne Mansfield Hot Water Bottle hit the market in 1957. The Mansfield figure—in a pin-up pose with hands behind her neck and wearing a painted-on black bikini—is made of “blushing” pink–colored plastic with a screw-on “hat” cap and measures close to two feet head-to-foot. Source: https://vintagenewsdaily.com/at-the-height-of-her-career-in-the-1950s-jayne-mansfield-even-modeled-for-this-awesome-hot-water-bottle/.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Jayne Mansfield Hot Water Bottle hit the market in 1957. The Mansfield figure—in a pin-up pose with hands behind her neck and wearing a painted-on black bikini—is made of “blushing” pink–colored plastic with a screw-on “hat” cap and measures close to two feet head-to-foot. Source: [https://vintagenewsdaily.com/at-the-height-of-her-career-in-the-1950s-jayne-mansfield-even-modeled-for-this-awesome-hot-water-bottle/](https://vintagenewsdaily.com/at-the-height-of-her-career-in-the-1950s-jayne-mansfield-even-modeled-for-this-awesome-hot-water-bottle/). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To safely use rubber or PVC hot water bottles at higher water temperatures, it’s important to replace them after a few years of use, and to store them properly. If you really want to use higher water temperatures, metal hot water bottles – inside a cover to prevent skin burns – are the safest option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you keep the temperature below 60°C (140°F), the worst-case scenario is just getting wet. If you use PET-bottles, you should surely stick to this maximum temperature, because at higher temperatures they could melt. Furthermore, a PET-bottle should not be used for drinking after it has been used for heating, because the higher temperatures may release chemicals in the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;water-use--infrastructure&#34;&gt;Water use &amp;amp; infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot water bottles also require a source of water. It’s possible to reheat the same water over and over again, thus limiting the water use to a few litres during the lifetime of the bottle. However, that’s not always the most practical solution. In modern households, hot water can be sourced from an electric kettle, a pot on the cooking stove, or the hot water tap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although hot tap water is the safest source of water for a hot water bottle, once the water has cooled down there’s no way to get it back into the pipes for reheating. Furthermore, it takes time before the water comes up to temperature, meaning that more than two litres of water will be consumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a slightly lower shower frequency easily provides you with the water and energy for continuous hot water bottle use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using an electric kettle – or a pot on the cookstove – makes it easy to reuse the same water over and over again, but it faces some problems too. First, if your electric kettle does not come with a programmable water temperature, you need to make sure the water does not get too hot. I solve this by dipping the probe of a digital thermometer in the kettle while warming the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if you reheat the water from rubber bottles, the kettle (or pot) can no longer be used to heat water for human consumption because it will taste bad. So, either you use a separate kettle for use with hot water bottles, or you warm the water in the only household kettle and discard it after use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the water is not reused for other purposes (such as watering the plants) the waste is quite limited. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2019/10/mist-showers-sustainable-decadence/&#34;&gt;average shower&lt;/a&gt; consumes enough water to fill 37 hot water bottles. Likewise, the energy use of the average shower corresponds to the energy use for heating 17 hot water bottles (which use water with a higher temperature than a shower). Consequently, even a slightly lower shower frequency easily provides you with the water and energy for continuous hot water bottle use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/stone-bottle_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Stoneware hot water bottle (1901-1910). Source: Auckland War Memorial Museum&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Stoneware hot water bottle (1901-1910). Source: Auckland War Memorial Museum 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2022/01/the-revenge-of-the-hot-water-bottle/images/dithers/te-aburi_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Japanese offered guests a small roundish ceramic pot with fuel inside, called a “te-aburi”. Copper or bronze box-shaped hand warmers a few inches across, often with perforations and carrying handles, were called “shou lu” in China. Image in the public domain. Read more: https://homethingspast.com/2011/11/26/hand-warmers-muff-warmer/.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Japanese offered guests a small roundish ceramic pot with fuel inside, called a “te-aburi”. Copper or bronze box-shaped hand warmers a few inches across, often with perforations and carrying handles, were called “shou lu” in China. Image in the public domain. Read more: [https://homethingspast.com/2011/11/26/hand-warmers-muff-warmer/](https://homethingspast.com/2011/11/26/hand-warmers-muff-warmer/). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cold-water-bottles&#34;&gt;Cold water bottles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot water bottles can be used for cooling as well. In this case, they are filled with cold water or put in the freezer. Cooling people is much more energy efficient than cooling spaces. I don’t have air conditioning and rely entirely on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2014/09/the-revenge-of-the-circulating-fan/&#34;&gt;fans&lt;/a&gt; and cold water bottles in summer, when temperatures are usually above 30°C. I use “cold water bottles” in a similar fashion to hot water bottles – they go into the bed, under my feet, or behind my back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For cooling I use plastic PET-bottles and metal drinking containers, not rubber water bottles as they get hard and brittle. Keep in mind not to fill the bottle completely – water expands when it’s frozen – and to put the bottle inside a protective cover to prevent iceburn. Also keep in mind that they will get a bit wet on the outside as the ice melts – although this effect only enhances the cooling. Like hot water bottles, cold water bottles work outdoors as well as indoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This custom was accompanied by strict rules. For example, male visitors ended up sleeping on one side of the bed, while the family’s daughters were on the other side. Source: Ekirch, A. Roger. At day&amp;rsquo;s close: night in times past. WW Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2006.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.encompassingdesigns.com/blog/hot-water-bottlesa-thing-of-the-past&#34;&gt;https://www.encompassingdesigns.com/blog/hot-water-bottlesa-thing-of-the-past&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “warming pan” or “bed warmer” was a metal container filled with hot coals and fitted with a long handle. It was slid between the bedsheets and then moved across the bed to warm all corners before someone got into it. Yet another solution to warm the bed was the so-called “bed wagon”: a wooden frame or sledge designed to hold a pot of hot coals, which was slid below the bed and covered with a metal sheet. Unlike a warming pan, the bed wagon provided warmth throughout the night. See: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldandinteresting.com/warming-the-bed.aspx&#34;&gt;http://www.oldandinteresting.com/warming-the-bed.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cities had public hot water supply systems. For example, in the first half of the twentieth century, the Dutch city of Rotterdam counted hundreds of &amp;ldquo;water distilleries&amp;rdquo; where people came to fill buckets with hot water for domestic use. China has a long and continuing tradition of providing its citizens with hot water everywhere they go – mainly for drinking. By the 1830s, hot water stores – known as “laohuzao” or “tiger stoves” – popped up in major cities all over the Yangtze river delta. Today, almost every government body, business and school administrative office in China has hot water dispensers – even high speed trains have them. Read more: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1000919/the-history-behind-chinas-obsession-with-hot-water&#34;&gt;https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1000919/the-history-behind-chinas-obsession-with-hot-water&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verhaart, Jacob, Michal Veselý, and Wim Zeiler. &amp;ldquo;Personal heating: effectiveness and energy use.&amp;rdquo; Building Research &amp;amp; Information 43.3 (2015): 346-354. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09613218.2015.1001606&#34;&gt;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09613218.2015.1001606&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deng, Qihong, et al. &amp;ldquo;Human thermal sensation and comfort in a non-uniform environment with personalized heating.&amp;rdquo; Science of the total environment 578 (2017): 242-248.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mishra, A. K., M. G. L. C. Loomans, and Jan LM Hensen. &amp;ldquo;Thermal comfort of heterogeneous and dynamic indoor conditions—An overview.&amp;rdquo; Building and Environment 109 (2016): 82-100. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0360132316303560&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0360132316303560&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Restoring the Old Way of Warming: Heating People, not Places</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/restoring-old-way-of-warming_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="85831" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/restoring-old-way-of-warming_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;People gathering around a tile stove. Die Bauern und die Zeitung. A painting by Albert Anker, 1867.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 People gathering around a tile stove. [Die Bauern und die Zeitung](http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Anker_Die_Bauern_und_die_Zeitung_1867.jpg). A painting by Albert Anker, 1867. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, we provide thermal comfort in winter by heating the entire volume of air in a room or building. In earlier times, our forebear&amp;rsquo;s concept of heating was more localized: heating people, not places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They used radiant heat sources that warmed only certain parts of a room, creating micro-climates of comfort. These people countered the large temperature differences with insulating furniture, such as hooded chairs and folding screens, and they made use of additional, personal heating sources that warmed specific body parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would make a lot of sense to restore this old way of warming, especially since modern technology has made it so much more practical, safe and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conduction-convection-radiation&#34;&gt;Conduction, Convection, Radiation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most modern heating systems are primarily based on the heating of air. This seems an obvious choice, but there are far worthier alternatives. There are three types of (sensible) heat transfer: convection (the heating of air), conduction (heating through physical contact), and radiation (heating through electromagnetic waves).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old way of warming was based upon radiation and conduction, which are more energy-efficient than convection. While convection implies the warming of each cubic centimetre of air in a space in order to keep people comfortable, radiation and conduction can directly transfer heat to people, making energy use independent of the size of a room or building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at the different methods of heat transfer in some more detail. Conduction and convection are closely related. Conduction concerns the transfer of energy due to the physical contact between two objects: heat will flow from the warmer to the cooler object. The speed at which this happens depends on the thermal resistance of the substance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, heat is transferred much faster through metal than through wood, because metal has a lower thermal resistance. This explains why, for instance, a cold metal object feels much colder than a cold wooden object, even though they both have the same temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/convection_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Convective heat transfer from the body to the environment.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Convective heat transfer from the body to the environment. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conduction not only occurs between physical objects, but also between physical objects and gasses (like air), and between gasses mutually. Each physical object that is warmer than the air that surrounds it, heats up the air in the immediate vicinity through conduction. By itself, this effect is limited, because air has a high thermal resistance - that&amp;rsquo;s why it forms the basis of most thermal insulation materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the air that is warmed by conduction expands and rises. Its place is taken by cold air, which is heated in turn, expands, rises, and so on. This plume of warm air that rises from every object that is warmer than the surrounding air, is called convection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radiation, the third form of sensible heat transfer, works in a very different way from conduction and convection. Radiant energy is transferred through electromagnetic waves, similar to light or sound. More precisely, it concerns the part of the electromagnetic spectrum that&amp;rsquo;s called infrared radiation. Radiation doesn&amp;rsquo;t need a medium (like air or water) for heat transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also works in a vacuum and it&amp;rsquo;s the most important form of heat transfer in outer space. The primary source of radiant energy is the sun, but every object on earth radiates infared energy as long as it has mass and a temperature above absolute zero. This energy can be absorbed by other objects with a lower temperature. Radiant energy doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a temperature. Only when it hits the surface of an object with mass, the energy can be absorbed and converted into heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thermal-comfort-at-low-air-temperatures&#34;&gt;Thermal Comfort at Low Air Temperatures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the general use of central air heating (and cooling) systems, we have come to believe that our indoor thermal comfort depends mainly on air temperature. However, the human body exchanges heat with its environment through convection, radiation, conduction and evaporation (a form of &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; heat transfer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convection relates to the heat exchange between the skin and the surrounding air, radiation is the heat exchange between the skin and the surrounding surfaces, evaporation concerns the moisture loss from the skin, and conduction relates to the heat exchange between a part of the human body and another object that it&amp;rsquo;s in contact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the share of radiation or conduction in the total heat transfer increases, people can be perfectly comfortable at a lower air temperature during the heating season&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In winter we can remain comfortable in lower air temperatures by increasing the share of radiation or conduction in the total heat transfer of a space. The opposite is also true: conduction and radiation can make people feel uncomfortable in spite of a high air temperature. For example, a person standing on a cold floor with bare feet will feel cold, even if the air temperature is a comfortable 21ºC (70ºF). This is because the body loses heat to the floor through conduction. A hot cup of soup in the hand, floor heating, or a heated bench have the opposite effect, because heat is transferred from the warm object to the body through conduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radiant heat can make people comfortable at a lower air temperature, too. The obvious example is direct sunlight. In spring or autumn, we can sit comfortably outside in the sun wearing only a T-shirt, even if the air temperature is relatively low. A metre away, in the shade, it can be cold enough to need a jacket, although the air temperature is more or less the same. In summer, we prefer the shade. The difference is explained by the radiant energy of the sun, which heats the body directly when it is exposed to sunlight. This higher &amp;ldquo;radiant temperature&amp;rdquo;, which can be measured with a black-globe thermometer, allows thermal comfort at a colder air temperature in winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/radiant-heating-explained_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Radiant heating systems compensate a lower air temperature with a higher radiant temperature, while air heating systems compensate a lower radiant temperature with a higher air temperature. The operative temperature -a weighted average of both- can be the same. Source: Richard Watson, 2008.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Radiant heating systems compensate a lower air temperature with a higher radiant temperature, while air heating systems compensate a lower radiant temperature with a higher air temperature. The operative temperature -a weighted average of both- can be the same. Source: Richard Watson, 2008. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that on earth, radiation always goes hand in hand with convection. Because air has little mass, the radiant energy of the sun doesn&amp;rsquo;t heat the air directly. However, it does so indirectly. The radiant energy of the sun is absorbed by the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface, where it is converted to heat. The warmer earth&amp;rsquo;s surface then slowly releases this heat to the air through the earlier described mechanisms of conduction and convection. In other words, it&amp;rsquo;s not the sun but the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface that heats the air on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The radiant temperature is equally important when heating a building, no matter which heating system is used. Indoors, the radiant temperature represents the total infrared radiation that is exchanged between all surfaces in a room. Radiant heating systems, which we will discuss later on, work in a similar manner as the sun: they don&amp;rsquo;t heat the air but the surfaces in a space, including human skin, raising the radiant temperature and providing thermal comfort at a colder air temperature. The use of radiant heating is more practical indoors, where environmental factors are under control. If a wind picks up outside, for example, the warming effect of the sun quickly &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2014/09/the-revenge-of-the-circulating-fan/&#34;&gt;disappears&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not the sun but the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface that heats the air on our planet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 100% radiant heating system doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, because both the radiant heating surface and the irradiated surfaces make contact with the air and warm it by conduction and convection. However, this heating of the air has a delayed onset and is more limited than in the case of a direct air heating system. Likewise, an air heating system will also raise the radiant temperature in a space, because the hot air warms the building&amp;rsquo;s
surfaces through conduction. But again, the increase of the radiant temperature is slow and limited in comparison to a radiant heating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with conduction, radiation can also make people uncomfortable in spite of warm air temperature. If we are seated next to a cold window, our body will radiate heat to this cold surface, making us feel cold even when the air temperature is a comfortable 21ºC (70ºF). In short, neither a high air temperature nor a high radiant temperature are a guarantee of thermal comfort. The best understanding of the thermal environment in a space is given by the &amp;ldquo;operative temperature&amp;rdquo;, which is a weighted average of both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-old-way-of-warming&#34;&gt;The Old Way of Warming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the arrival of central air heating systems in the twentieth century, buildings were mainly heated by a central radiant heat source, such as a fireplace or a wood, coal or gas stove. Usually, only one of the rooms in a building was heated. But even within this room, there were large differences in comfort depending on your exact location in the space. While air heating distributes warmth relatively evenly throughout an area, a radiant heating source creates a local microclimate that can be radically different from the rest of the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because the energy potential of a radiant heat source decreases with distance. It&amp;rsquo;s not that the infrared waves become weaker, but that they become more dispersed as they are fanning out from a specific source. This is shown in the two illustrations below, which appear in Richard Watson&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Radiant Heating and Cooling Handbook&amp;rdquo;. The drawing on top shows the radiant heat distribution (or &amp;ldquo;radiant landscape&amp;rdquo;) in a room, seen from above, which is warmed by a forced-air heating system. The average radiant temperature in the space is 20ºC (68ºF). Except for the influence of a cold window surface (at the top of the illustration), the radiant temperature is relatively constant throughout the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/contour-plot-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/contour-plot-2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Source: Radiant Heating and Cooling Handbook. Richard Watson, 2008&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Source: Radiant Heating and Cooling Handbook. Richard Watson, 2008 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second illustration shows the same room, again with a mean radiant temperature of 20ºC (68ºF), but now heated with a radiant heat source which is located at the centre of the ceiling. It concerns an electric longwave infrared panel, a new technology that we will explain in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/03/radiant-conductive-heating-systems/&#34;&gt;second part of this article&lt;/a&gt;, but a fireplace in the middle of the room would give a similar result. The radiant landscape is now very different. The highest radiant temperature is measured in the middle of the room, right below the heating panel. The radiant temperature then decreases rapidly in concentric circles towards the sides of the room. The difference between minimum and maximum radiant temperature is much larger than in the case of an air heating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an air-heated room, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter much where you are. In a room heated by a radiant heating source, location is everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, a different location of the radiant heating surface, or a combination of two or more radiant heating surfaces, would again present a very different radiant landscape. Furthermore, as with solar radiation, other objects can throw shadows, which means that even the location of the furniture can have an effect on the heat distribution in a room. Also note that the heterogeneous distribution of the radiant temperature will be somewhat tempered by the homogeneous character of the air temperature, no matter which heating system is being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;energy-efficiency&#34;&gt;Energy-Efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an air-heated room, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter much where you are. In a room heated by a central radiant heating source, location is everything. The mean radiant temperature can be optimal, but the radiant temperature in parts of the space may be too low. But the opposite is also possible:
the mean radiant temperature can be too low, while at certain locations the room is perfectly comfortable. This is the ancient principle of spot or zone heating, which is impossible to realize with an air heating system. Instead of heating the entire space, our ancestors only heated the occupied parts of a building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/air-versus-radiant-heating_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Air heating (left) versus radiant heating (right) in a church building. Source: Fabric-friendly heating, Dario Camuffo.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Air heating (left) versus radiant heating (right) in a church building. Source: [Fabric-friendly heating, Dario Camuffo](http://www.buildingconservation.com/articles/fabric-friendly-heating/fabric-friendly-heating.htm). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar thing happens on the vertical plane. Warm air rises, so that most heat ends up under the ceiling, where it is of little use. With radiant heating, it&amp;rsquo;s perfectly possible to only heat the lower part of a space, no matter how high the ceiling is. Radiant heat doesn&amp;rsquo;t rise, unless the radiant heating surface is aimed upwards. In conclusion, instead of heating the entire volume of air in a space, a radiant heating system can heat only that part of a space which is occupied, which is of course much more energy efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless the room is very small or very crowded, only a very small part of the energy used by an air heating system benefits people. On the other hand, almost all the energy used by a radiant heating system is effectively heating humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;local-insulation&#34;&gt;Local Insulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem with the heterogeneous indoor climate of old times was radiant assymetry—the difference in radiant temperature between distinct parts of the body. A person sitting in front of an open fire will receive sufficient radiant heat on one side of their body, while the other side loses heat to the cold air and surfaces at the opposite half of the room. The body can be in thermal balance—the heat loss on one side equals the heat gain on the other—but if the temperature differences are too large, thermal comfort will not be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/radiant-assymetry_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A bench with adjustable backrest. Source: Dictionnaire de l&amp;amp;rsquo;ameublement et de la décoration depuis le XIII siècle, 1887-1890&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A bench with adjustable backrest. Source: [Dictionnaire de l&#39;ameublement et de la décoration depuis le XIII siècle](http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k57648255), 1887-1890 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is illustrated on the engraving above. The back of the bench could be switched from side to side. By regularly turning the body to the fire and then away from it, both the front and the back of the body could be heated alternately. Although radiant assymetry can be an issue with forced-air heating systems, it&amp;rsquo;s much more likely to appear in spaces that are warmed by a a radiant heat source. In historical buildings, the difference in surface temperatures was aggravated by the fact that building surfaces were not insulated. Drafts, another cause of local thermal discomfort, were also a problem in old buildings, because they were anything but air-tight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a comfortable microclimate without radiant assymetry or draft, our forefathers supplemented local heating with local insulation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a comfortable microclimate without radiant assymetry or drafts, our ancestors supplemented local heating with local insulation. One example was the hooded chair. This chair, which could be upholstered or covered with leather or wool blankets, fully exposed people to a radiant heat source, while protecting their back from the drafts and the low surface temperatures behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the shape of the furniture ensured that a greater share of the radiant heat emitted by the fire was effectively used: the chair was heated directly by the fire through radiation, and this heat was transferred to the person sitting in it. Recent research has shown that the insulation value of these types of chair amounted to at least 0.4 clo, which corresponds to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/02/insulation-first-the-body-then-the-home/&#34;&gt;insulation value&lt;/a&gt;
of a heavy pullover or coat. Some hooded chairs could host more than one person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/hooded-chairs_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hooded chairs from the nineteenth century. Sources: Period Oak Antiques (left) and Polyvore (right).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hooded chairs from the nineteenth century. Sources: [Period Oak Antiques](http://www.periodoakantiques.co.uk/antique-sales-archive/a-rare-18thc-elm-hooded-lambing-chair-with-box-seat-27-stockno-429/) (left) and [Polyvore](http://www.polyvore.com/buttoned_leather_chesterfield_porter_chair/thing?id=55242872) (right). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/folding-screen_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A folding screen for winter use. Source: Alain Truong.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A folding screen for winter use. Source: [Alain Truong](http://elogedelart.canalblog.com/archives/2009/04/05/13277504.html). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An additional solution, which could also be used alone, was the folding screen. The folding screens used as winter furniture were insulated with fabrics or built with heavy wood panels. They could be placed behind an insulated chair, or behind a table, for instance. Like the hooded chair, the folding screen protected the back of a person against drafts and cold temperatures, creating a comfortable microclimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/bench-in-fireplace_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A sitting area close to the fireplace (Source: The English Fireplace).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A sitting area close to the fireplace (Source: [The English Fireplace](https://archive.org/details/cu31924015345139)). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/four-poster-bed_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A four-poster bed (Source: Wikipedia Commons).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A four-poster bed (Source: [Wikipedia Commons](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four-poster_bed#mediaviewer/File:Four_Poster_Bed_350b.jpg)). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third example of local insulation were special sitting areas close to the fireplace. These could be benches placed between the fire and the side walls of the fireplace, or a niche in the wall with a built-in seat. In both cases, a person would lean against a wall that was warmed by the fire and protected from drafts. In some cases, the fireplace itself was placed in a room-inside-a-room. In the bedroom, which often remained unheated, yet another piece of furniture was aimed at providing a microclimate: the four poster bed, which had a canopy and thick curtains. When the curtains were closed, drafts were eliminated and body heat was trapped inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;portable-heating-systems&#34;&gt;Portable Heating Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The apparent downside of spot heating is that you have to be in a specific location in order to be comfortable. In earlier times, the family gathered around the fireplace or the stove when no physical work had to be done, or when the body had to be warmed up after a long stay in a cold environment. Other locations in the room, as well as unheated rooms, were better suited for activities which required a higher metabolism. People were &amp;ldquo;migrating&amp;rdquo; throughout the room and throughout the house in search of the climate that suited their needs best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/albert-anker-tile-stove_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Familienszene in einem Interieur, a painting by Albert Anker, 1910&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Familienszene in einem Interieur, a painting by Albert Anker, 1910 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the use of radiant heat sources and local insulation were also complemented by portable heating sources which transferred heat through radiation, convection and/or conduction. These could be used to further increase thermal comfort in the presence of a central heat source, and were also helpful in bringing warmth to other locations. Portable heating systems were designed especially to heat the feet or the hands:
the parts of the body that are most sensitive to cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal heating sources allowed people to enjoy the heat from the central fireplace in unheated rooms, or even outside the house&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example is the foot stove, a box with one or more perforated partitions, which contained a metal or earthenware bowl or pan filled with embers from the fireplace. The feet were placed on top of the stove and the often long garments worn in those days increased the effect of the small heating device: the warmth was guided through a skirt or a chamber coat along the legs to the upper body. The upper part of the stove was made of wood or stone, as these materials have low thermal conductivity to avoid burns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/dutch-foot-stove_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Dutch foot stove (Wikipedia Commons).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Dutch foot stove ([Wikipedia Commons](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foot_stove#mediaviewer/File:Voetenstoof.jpg)). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/woman-warming-hands_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&amp;amp;quot;Young woman warming her hands&amp;amp;quot;, a painting by Caesar van Everdingen.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 \&#34;[Young woman warming her hands](http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Young_woman_warming_her_hands._Caesar_van_Everdingen.jpg)\&#34;, a painting by Caesar van Everdingen. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cultures worldwide, similar heat sources were used for warming the hands. They were made from metal or ceramics and were filled with embers from the fireplace, or with coal or &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/09/medieval-smokestacks-fossil-fuels-in-pre-industrial-times/&#34;&gt;peat&lt;/a&gt;. These personal heating sources also allowed people to enjoy the heat from the central fireplace or stove outside the house. They were taken in unheated coaches and railcars, or to Sunday Mass. Poor people made use of heated stones or bricks, or even heated potatoes put in coat pockets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For heating the bed, people made use of brass bedpans with a long handle which were shoved underneath the mattress. Some beds had a bed wagon: a large, wooden frame designed to hold a pot of glowing fuel in the centre of the bed. In the 19th century, following the arrival of the public water supply, the use of ceramic hot water bottles became common &amp;ndash;
water is a much safer heat medium than smouldering fire. These devices, which were often protected by a fabric cover, were used as foot warmers, hand warmers, or bed warmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/korsi_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;An Afghan &amp;amp;quot;Korsi&amp;amp;quot;. Source unknown.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 An Afghan \&#34;Korsi\&#34;. Source unknown. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some peoples took the concept of the foot stove one level higher. The Japanese had their &amp;ldquo;kotatsu&amp;rdquo;, a movable low table with a charcoal heater underneath. A thick cloth or quilt was placed over the table to trap the heat and the whole family slid their legs under the table, sitting on the floor. As with the European and American foot stoves, contemporary clothing increased the effect of the device. The heat of the charcoal burner was transferred through the traditional Japanese kimono, warming the whole body. Similar heating devices were used in Afghanistan (such as the &amp;ldquo;korsi&amp;rdquo;), as well as Iran, Spain and Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conductive-heating-systems&#34;&gt;Conductive Heating Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some historical radiant heating systems also transferred heat through conduction, further improving efficiency and comfort. More than 3,000
years ago, the Chinese and the Koreans built heating systems which were based on trapping smoke gases in a thermal mass. The northern Chinese &amp;ldquo;kang&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;heated bed&amp;rdquo;) was a raised platform made from stone, masonry or adobe, which occupied about half of the room. As the name indicates, the kang was in the first place a heated bed, but the platform was also used during the day as a heated work and living space. The &amp;ldquo;dikang&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;warmed floor&amp;rdquo;), which was typical in North-Eastern China, worked in the same way as the kang, but had a larger floor area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/chinese-kang_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Chinese Kang, photographed in the 1920s. Source: Wandering in Northern China, Harry A. Franck.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Chinese Kang, photographed in the 1920s. Source: [Wandering in Northern China](https://openlibrary.org/books/OL6658339M/Wandering_in_northern_China), Harry A. Franck. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Koreans used the &amp;ldquo;ondol&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;heated stone&amp;rdquo;), which was a wall-to-wall platform. A similar heating system in Afghanistan, the &amp;ldquo;tawakhaneh&amp;rdquo;
(&amp;ldquo;hot room&amp;rdquo;) is possibly the oldest of these systems: its use may date back 4,000 years. In all these systems, the heat of an open fire was led underneath the platform to a chimney at the other side of the room. Both the fireplace and the chimney could be in the room or in adjacent rooms. The heat of the hot smoke gases was transferred to the thermal mass of the platform, which slowly released the warmth to the space. Conduction was as important as radiation and convection in the total heat transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/tile-stove-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Blick in eine Schwarzwaldstube mit kleinem Mädchen auf der Ofenbank, a painting by Georg Saal, 1861.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 [Blick in eine Schwarzwaldstube mit kleinem Mädchen auf der Ofenbank](http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Georg_Saal_Schwarzwaldstube_1861.jpg), a painting by Georg Saal, 1861. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/02/restoring-the-old-way-of-warming-heating-people-not-places/images/dithers/kids-on-tile-stove_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Auf dem Ofen, a painting by Albert Anker, 1895&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 [Auf dem Ofen](http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Tiled_stoves_in_art#mediaviewer/File:Auf_dem_Ofen_1895.jpg), a painting by Albert Anker, 1895 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ancient Eastern heating systems are somewhat reminiscent of the European tile stoves that appeared in the middle ages. Tile stoves (or &amp;ldquo;masonry heaters&amp;rdquo; as they are known in the USA) are &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2008/12/sunbathing-in-the-living-room-oven-stoves-and-heat-walls/&#34;&gt;heat accumulating wood stoves that make use of a high thermal mass to burn wood at very high temperatures&lt;/a&gt;, which is cleaner and more efficient. The smoke gases are trapped in a labyrinth of smoke channels, transferring most of the heat to the masonry structure before leaving the chimney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tile stoves produce a large share of radiant heat, but on top of this they allow heat transfer through conduction, as many tile stoves had built-in platforms to sit or sleep on. Even if these platforms were not there, wooden benches were placed next to the stove so that one could lean against the warm (but not too hot) surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-we-also-need-modern-technology&#34;&gt;Why We Also Need Modern Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, all historic heating systems used radiation and/or conduction as the primary modes of heat transfer, while convection was merely a by-product. It makes good sense to return to this concept of heating, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we have to go back to using fireplaces and carrying burning embers around the house. While the old concept of heating is more energy-efficient, the same cannot be said of most of the old heating devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the old concept of heating is more energy efficient, the same cannot be said of most of the old heating devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fireplaces, for one thing, are hugely inefficient, because most of the heat escapes through the chimney. They also suck in large amounts of cold air through cracks and gaps in the building envelope, which cools the air indoors and introduces strong drafts. Owing to this, fireplaces can even have negative efficiency as far as the air temperature is concerned: they can make the room colder instead of warmer. Stoves do better, but they remain relatively inefficient and have to be fired regularly, just like a fireplace. And for both options, air pollution can be substantial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The (improved) tile stove is the only ancient heating system that can still be recommended, but we have far more options now, such as electric and hydronic radiant and conductive heating systems. These are more efficient, more practical, and safer than the heating sources of yesteryear. In the next two articles, we investigate &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/03/radiant-conductive-heating-systems/&#34;&gt;how the old way of warming can be improved upon by modern technology&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2015/03/how-to-keep-warm-in-a-cool-house/&#34;&gt;how much energy could be saved&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sources-in-order-of-importance&#34;&gt;Sources (in order of importance):&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eburon.nl/stralingsverwarming&#34;&gt;Stralingsverwarming: Gezonde Warmte met Minder     Energie&lt;/a&gt;, Kris De Decker,     2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/technicalpaper14.pdf&#34;&gt;Keeping Warm in a Cooler House. Creating Comfort with Background     Heating and Local Supplementary     Warmth&lt;/a&gt;     (PDF). Historical Scotland Technical Paper 14, Michael Humphreys,     Historic Scotland, 2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00LVDVS8I/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00LVDVS8I&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;linkId=WTF5AZV7AQ2ZW74T&#34;&gt;Radiant Heating and Cooling Handbook (Mcgraw-Hill     Handbooks)&lt;/a&gt;, Richard Watson, 2008&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/146659599X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=146659599X&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;linkId=NMA5IA65R7XAKU3R&#34;&gt;Human Thermal Environments: The Effects of Hot, Moderate, and Cold     Environments on Human Health, Comfort, and Performance, Third     Edition&lt;/a&gt;, Ken Parsons, 2014&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1890132098/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1890132098&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;linkId=ELXQCAXGMLF3WP5K&#34;&gt;The Book of Masonry Stoves: Rediscovering an Old Way of     Warming&lt;/a&gt;, David Lyle, 1984&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.healthyheating.com/History_of_Radiant_Heating_and_Cooling/history_of_radiant_heating_Asia.htm#.VN36IS5W88I&#34;&gt;History of radiant heating and cooling systems, part     one&lt;/a&gt;.     Robert Bean, Bjarne W. Olesen, Kwang Woo Kim, in &amp;ldquo;ASHRAE Journal&amp;rdquo;,
January 2010, pp. 40-47&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0415691591/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0415691591&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=lowtemagaz-20&amp;amp;linkId=ALEQFIDNAT6TBHC5&#34;&gt;Adaptive Thermal Comfort: Principles and     Practice&lt;/a&gt;, Fergus Nicol, Michael Humphreys &amp;amp; Susan Roaf, 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k57648255&#34;&gt;Dictionnaire de l&amp;rsquo;Ameublement et de la Décoration depuis le XIII     siècle&lt;/a&gt;, Henry     Havard, 1887-1890.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.homethingspast.com/foot-warmers/&#34;&gt;Foot warmers: hot coals, hot     water&lt;/a&gt;. Home Things     Past.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldandinteresting.com/bed-warmers.aspx&#34;&gt;Bed warmers&lt;/a&gt;.     Old &amp;amp; Interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.homethingspast.com/hand-warmers-muff-warmer/&#34;&gt;Muff warmers &amp;amp; other antique hand     warmers&lt;/a&gt;.     Home Things Past.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.koerper-waermespender.de/&#34;&gt;Körperwärmespender&lt;/a&gt;. Website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heat Your Clothes, Not Your House</title>
      <link>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/images/dithers/heated-sock_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="26916" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/images/dithers/heated-sock_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A heated sock from Grabber.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A [heated sock](http://www.thewarmingstore.com/grabber-heated-socks.html#.UmzkDxBUo3p) from Grabber. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2011/02/insulation-first-the-body-then-the-home/&#34;&gt;As we wrote two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, insulation of the body is more energy efficient than insulation of living space. Because of its excellent insulating properties, modern thermal underclothing makes it possible to burn the heating at much lower temperatures without sacrificing comfort or sex appeal. The potential energy savings are huge, and the costs are almost nil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This low-tech insulation strategy can also be applied to heating the body. In use since World War Two, electrically heated clothes have become more effective and comfortable in recent years. While their use outdoors increases energy consumption, heated clothes have the potential to save massive amounts of energy indoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;world-war-two&#34;&gt;World War Two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrically heated clothing is used by soldiers, adventurers, hunters, winter sports enthusiasts, bikers and construction workers &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Heated leather jackets were already used by pilots in World War Two. Bikers have used the technology for decades, using the battery of their motorbikes to supply the required energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrival of compact lithium-ion batteries has increased the performance and diversity of electrically heated clothing. There are now more types of heated clothes on the market: jackets, vests, pants, socks, underclothing, baselayers, sweaters, scarfs, shoes and gloves. Some have even become fashionable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy for these garments is supplied by one or two relatively small and light batteries, hidden in a special pocket, which supply the lucky owner with some five hours of warmth. Some brands offer the possibility to plug in heated gloves or socks in a heated pants or jacket, so that they don&amp;rsquo;t need a separate battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;carbon-fibres&#34;&gt;Carbon Fibres&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also new is the use of carbon fibres as a heating element. This material is flexible and can be inserted anywhere in the clothes without creating discomfort for the wearer. Carbon fibres are replacing embedded heating wires, which are rigid and heavy, break easily, and require more energy. Making use of low voltages for safety, electrically heated clothing comes with a button on the outside which enables the regulation of the heating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/images/dithers/heated-vest_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A heated jacket from Blazewear.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A [heated jacket](http://www.blazewear.com/heated-garments/heated-body-warmers/deluxe-men-s-gilet-in-khaki.html) from Blazewear. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, electrically heated clothing doesn&amp;rsquo;t save energy when it is used outdoors. Like most technologies that increase comfort, it increases energy consumption. The big advantage for people who work or play outdoors is that heated clothing keeps them warm during breaks in activity, when body temperature can decrease quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;effective-and-efficient&#34;&gt;Effective and Efficient&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When used as a heating strategy indoors, however, electrically heated clothing is as sustainable as it can get. A fully heated wardrobe &amp;ndash;
pants, socks, underclothing, shirt and vest—has an energy output of 100 watts maximum. There&amp;rsquo;s no need for the heating elements to get very hot because they remain close to the skin. An electric heater of that calibre used for space heating brings little comfort, even if it heats a very small room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://lowtechmag.gitlab.io/solar/2013/11/heat-your-clothes-not-your-house/images/dithers/heated-pants_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Electrically heated pants from Venture Heat.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 [Electrically heated pants](http://www.thewarmingstore.com/ventureheat-12v-heated-pant-liners.html#.Unl8RBBUo3o) from Venture Heat.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using electrically heated clothing we could be more comfortable at even lower indoor temperatures than when using thermal clothing (which already offered heating till near-freezing conditions). Another advantage of electric clothes is that you need less volume and weight to stay comfortable. This effectiveness and efficiency of heated clothes has been confirmed by scientific research &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrically heated clothing can also be used without activating the heating elements—the good insulation of the garments traps body heat, as with thermal clothes. In this sense, heated clothing is similar to a bicycle with an electrically assisted motor. Unlike electric cars or smartphones, the clothes don&amp;rsquo;t become useless when the battery dies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wired-or-wireless&#34;&gt;Wired or Wireless?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only unsustainable feature of electrically heated clothing is its use of batteries. A wireless energy supply is very practical, but it would be perfectly possible to connect electrically heated clothes directly to the grid, just as you would do with your phone and laptop. It would function like an electric blanket or sleeping bag. Since many of us are sedentry, this is not as far-fetched as it may seem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.instructables.com/id/DIY-heated-clothing/&#34;&gt;make your own electrically heated clothing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some manufacturers who sell electrically heated clothes are &lt;a href=&#34;http://gerbing.com/&#34;&gt;Gerbing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thewarmingstore.com/venture-heated-clothing.html#.Umx8NhBUo3o&#34;&gt;Venture Heat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.engadget.com/2011/03/04/columbia-omni-heat-circuit-breaker-softshell-electric-heated-j/&#34;&gt;Columbia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blazewear.com/&#34;&gt;Blazewear&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.milwaukeetool.com/power-tools/cordless/2344&#34;&gt;Milwaukee Power Tools&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.academia.edu/1112843/A_Review_of_Technology_of_Personal_Heating_Garments&#34;&gt;A Review of Technology of Personal Heating Garments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;,
Faming Wang et al., International Journal of Occupational Safety and Ergonomics (JOSE) 2010, Vol.16, No. 3, 387-404. This study also reviews other techniques to make heated cloths, such as phase-changing materials.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
