<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>/tags/wind-power/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/wind-power/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Printed Website: Volume III &amp; The Comments</title>
      <link>/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="14598" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Printed Website.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Printed Website. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-volume-iii&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest Low-tech Magazine book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;collects 18 articles published between 2018 and 2021&lt;/a&gt;. At 368 pages it’s a thin book compared to earlier volumes. When we started the book series, the challenge was to unlock an archive of almost 12 years. It made sense to pack this content into as few volumes as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking ahead, we will publish more often, once every one to three years, depending on the number of articles written. From now on, the articles will be arranged chronologically, from oldest to newest, and no longer the other way around. This volume contains 184 images in black and white. It is &lt;a href=&#34;/fr/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/&#34;&gt;also available in French&lt;/a&gt; (400 pages).
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-the-comments&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also launched a book which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;collects almost 3,000 comments&lt;/a&gt; on the roughly 100 articles which are published in the three other books. This volume has 688 pages and no images. We included all feedback up to November 7, 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;/low-tech-magazine-the-printed-comments/&#34;&gt;Read more about the comments book here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, readers have often stated that the comments on the website are (at least) as interesting as the articles themselves. We agree. Low-tech Magazine would not have been even half what it is now without the comments. You can even take this literally, because this is one of the thickest books we have published so far, despite the extra small font we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-edition&#34;&gt;New Edition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;second edition of the first book we published&lt;/a&gt; in 2019. This new edition has almost twice as many images and follows the same design as the other volumes. In contrast to the first edition, the images are not &amp;ldquo;dithered&amp;rdquo; and of higher quality. We use a smaller font to pack more content on fewer pages. This second edition also fixes some errors in the articles and the references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/comments-book-cover_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/low-tech-magazine-volume-III-montage_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents-volume-iii&#34;&gt;Contents Volume III&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Circular is the Circular Economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping Some of the Lights On: Redefining Energy Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat your House with a Mechanical Windmill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinventing the Small Wind Turbine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Wind Power Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mist Showers: Sustainable Decadence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too Much Combustion, Too Little Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is a Solar Powered Website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit Trenches: Cultivating Subtropical Plants in Freezing Temperatures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermoelectric Stoves: Ditch the Solar Panels?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Biomass Energy Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and Why I Stopped Buying New Laptops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical Farming Does not Save Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is High-tech Health Care?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Urban Fish Ponds: Low-tech Sewage Treatment for Towns and Cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Build a Low-tech Solar Panel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fascine Mattresses: Basketry Gone Wild&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;print-on-demand&#34;&gt;Print on Demand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The books are printed on demand, meaning that there are no unsold copies (and no large upfront investment costs). Our US publisher Lulu.com works with printers all over the world, so that most copies are produced locally and travel relatively short distances. Note that it takes 3 to 5 work days to print the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2007-2012/paperback/product-1z742pek.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume I (2007-2012)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume II (2012-2018)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?</title>
      <link>/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Garthsnaid_-_SLV_H91.250-933_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="48677" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Garthsnaid_-_SLV_H91.250-933_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;On board the ship Garthsnaid at sea. A view from high up in the rigging. Image by Allan C. Green, circa 1920.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 On board the ship *Garthsnaid* at sea. A view from high up in the rigging. Image by Allan C. Green, circa 1920.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sailing ship is a textbook example of sustainability. For at least 4,000 years, sailing ships have transported passengers and cargo across the world’s seas and oceans without using a single drop of fossil fuels. If we want to keep travelling and trading globally in a low carbon society, sailing ships are the obvious alternative to container ships, bulk carriers, and airplanes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, by definition, the sailing ship is not a carbon neutral technology. For most of history, sailing ships were built from wood, but back then whole forests were felled for ships, and those trees often did not grow back. In the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, sailing ships were increasingly made from steel, which also has a significant carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carbon neutrality of sailing in the 21st century is even more elusive. That’s because we have changed profoundly since the Age of Sail. Compared to our forebears, we have higher demands in terms of safety, comfort, convenience, and cleanliness. These higher standards are difficult to achieve unless the ship also has a diesel engine and generator on-board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-revival-of-the-sailing-ship&#34;&gt;The revival of the sailing ship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sailing ship has seen a modest revival in the last decade, especially for the transportation of cargo. In 2009, Dutch company &lt;a href=&#34;https://fairtransport.eu/&#34;&gt;Fairtransport&lt;/a&gt; started shipping freight between Europe and the Americas with the &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt;, a sailing ship built in 1943. The company remains active today and has a second ship in service since 2015, the &lt;em&gt;Nordlys&lt;/em&gt; (built in 1873).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, others have joined the sail cargo business. In 2016, the German company &lt;a href=&#34;https://timbercoast.com/en/&#34;&gt;Timbercoast&lt;/a&gt; started shipping cargo with the &lt;em&gt;Avontuur&lt;/em&gt;, a ship built in 1920. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 2017, the French &lt;a href=&#34;https://blueschoonercompany.com/en/home/&#34;&gt;Blue Schooner Company&lt;/a&gt; started transporting cargo between Europe and the Americas with the &lt;em&gt;Gallant&lt;/em&gt;, a sailing ship that was built in 1916. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All these sailing ships were constructed in the twentieth or nineteenth century, and were restored at a later date. However, a revival of sail cannot rely on historical ships alone, because there’s not enough of them. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/clipper-ship-noach_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Noach, built in 1857.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Noach, built in 1857. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, there are at least two sailing ships in development that are being built from scratch: the &lt;em&gt;Ceiba&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;. The first ship is being constructed in Costa Rica by a company named &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sailcargo.org/&#34;&gt;Sailcargo&lt;/a&gt;. She is built from wood and inspired by a Finnish ship from the twentieth century. The second ship is designed by a company called &lt;a href=&#34;https://ecoclipper.org/&#34;&gt;EcoClipper&lt;/a&gt;, which is led by one of the founders of the Dutch FairTransport, Jorne Langelaan. Their &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is a steel replica of a Dutch clipper ship from 1857: the &lt;em&gt;Noach&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Old designs are not necessarily the best&amp;quot;, says Jorne Langelaan, &amp;ldquo;but whenever proven design is used, one can be sure of its performance. A new design is more of a gamble. Furthermore, in the 20th and 21st century, sailing technology developed for fast sailing yachts, which is an entirely different story compared to ships which need to be able to carry cargo.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-economical-sailing-ships&#34;&gt;More economical sailing ships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two ships – one under construction and one in the design phase – have the potential to make sail cargo a lot more economical than it is today. That’s because they have a much larger cargo capacity than the sailing ships currently in operation. As a ship becomes longer, her cargo capacity increases more than proportionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/ecoclipper-prototype500-colour_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The EcoClipper500 is a full-scale replica of the Noach.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The EcoClipper500 is a full-scale replica of the Noach. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 46 metre long &lt;em&gt;Ceiba&lt;/em&gt; is powered by 580 m2 of sails and carries 250 tonnes of cargo. The 60 metre long &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is powered by almost 1,000 m2 of sails and takes 500 tonnes of cargo. For comparison, the &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt; is not that much shorter at 32 metres, but she takes only 40 tonnes of cargo – twelve times less than the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;. A larger ship is also faster and saves labour. The &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt; requires a crew of seven, while the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; only has a slightly larger crew of twelve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;life-cycle-analysis-of-a-sailing-ship&#34;&gt;Life cycle analysis of a sailing ship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is still in the design phase, she will be the focus of this article. This is because the company conducted a life cycle analysis of the ship prior to building it. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As far as I know, this is the first life cycle analysis of a sailing ship ever made. The study reveals that it takes around 1,200 tonnes of carbon to build the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of those emissions are generated during steel production, and roughly one third is generated by steel working processes and other shipyard activities. Solvent-based paints as well as electric and electronic systems each account for roughly 5% of emissions. The emissions produced during the manufacturing of the sails are not included because there are no scientific data available, but a quick back-of-the-envelope calculation (for sails based on aramid fibres) signals that their contribution to the total carbon footprint is very small. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; has a carbon footprint of  2 grammes of CO2 per tonne-kilometre, which is five times less than the carbon footprint of a container ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these 1,200 tonnes of emissions are spread out over an estimated lifetime of 50 years, then the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; would have a carbon footprint of about 2 grammes of CO2 per tonne-kilometre of cargo, concludes researcher Andrew Simons, who made the life cycle analysis for the ship. This is roughly five times less than the carbon footprint of a container ship (10 grammes CO2/tonne-km) and three times less than the carbon footprint of a bulk-carrier (6 grammes CO2/tonne-km). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_looking_aft_from_aloft_on_the_deck_while_at_anchor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Looking aft from aloft on the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo; while at anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. Villiers&amp;amp;rsquo;s work vividly records the period of early 20th century maritime history when merchant sailing vessels or ‘tall ships’ were in rapid decline.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Looking aft from aloft on the &#39;Parma&#39; while at anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. Villiers&#39;s work vividly records the period of early 20th century maritime history when merchant sailing vessels or ‘tall ships’ were in rapid decline. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transporting one ton of cargo over a distance of 8,000 km (roughly the distance between the Caribbean and the Netherlands) would thus produce 16 kg of carbon with the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;, compared to 80 kg on a container ship and 48 kg on a bulk carrier. The proportions are similar for other environmental factors, such as ozone depletion, ecotoxicity, air pollution, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the sailing ship boasts a convincing advantage, it may not be as big as you might have expected. First, as Simons explains, there’s scale. A container ship or bulk carrier enjoys the same benefits over the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; as the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; enjoys over the &lt;em&gt;Tres Hombres&lt;/em&gt;. It can take a lot more cargo – on average 50,000 tonnes instead of 500 tonnes – and it needs only a slightly larger crew of 20-25 people. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, fossil fuel powered ships are faster than sailing ships, meaning that fewer ships are needed to transport a given amount of cargo over a given period of time. The original ship on which the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; is based, sailed between the Netherlands and Indonesia in 65 to 78 days, while a container ship does it in about half the time (taking the short cut through the Suez canal).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-a-fleet-of-sailing-ships&#34;&gt;Building a fleet of sailing ships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s two ways to further lower the carbon emissions of sailing ships in comparison to container ships and bulk carriers. One is to build ships from wood instead of steel, such as the &lt;em&gt;Ceiba&lt;/em&gt;. If the harvested trees are allowed to grow back (which the makers of the Ceiba have promised), such a ship may even be considered a carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there’s a good reason why the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; will be made from steel: the company’s aim is to build not just one ship, but a fleet of them. Jorne Langelaan: “There are few shipyards who can deliver wooden ships nowadays. Steel makes it easier to build a fleet in a shorter period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible compromise would be a composite construction, in which a steel skeleton is clad with timber keel, planks, and deck. Andrew Simons: “This would reduce the carbon footprint of construction by half. It could also be feasible to make superstructures and some of the mast sections and spars from timber instead of steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_driving_sprays_over_the_main_deck_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Driving sprays over the main deck of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Driving sprays over the main deck of the &#39;Parma&#39;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the future, another possibility to further decrease a sailings ship’s emissions per tonne-km is to build it even larger. While the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; has much more cargo capacity than the cargo sailing ships now in operation, she is far from the largest sailing ship ever built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical ships such as the &lt;em&gt;Great Republic&lt;/em&gt; (5,000 tonnes), the &lt;em&gt;Parma&lt;/em&gt; (5,300 tonnes), the &lt;em&gt;France II&lt;/em&gt; (7,300 tonnes), and the &lt;em&gt;Preussen&lt;/em&gt; (7,800 tonnes), were more than 100 metres long and could take more than ten times the freight capacity of the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;. Langelaan already dreams of a &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper3000&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;passengers&#34;&gt;Passengers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cargo sailing ships travelling across the oceans today can also take some passengers. Fully loaded with cargo, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; takes 12 crew members, 12 passengers, and 8 trainees (passengers who learn how to sail). If the upper hold deck is not used for cargo, another 28 trainees can join, so that the ship can take up to 60 people on board (with a smaller cargo volume: 480 m3 instead of 880 m3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carbon footprint for passengers amounts to 10 g per passenger-km, compared to roughly 100 g per passenger-km on an airplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, and &lt;a href=&#34;/2008/06/life-without-airplanes-from-london-to-new-york-in-3-days-and-12-hours/&#34;&gt;since ocean liners have disappeared&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; also becomes an alternative to the airplane. According to the results of the life cycle analysis, the carbon footprint for passengers on the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; amounts to 10 grammes per passenger-kilometre, compared to roughly 100 grammes per passenger-kilometre on an airplane. Transporting one passenger thus produces as much carbon emissions as transporting 1 tonne of freight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;engine-or-not&#34;&gt;Engine or not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the life cycle analysis of the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; assumes that there is no diesel engine on-board. On a sailing ship, a diesel engine can serve two purposes, which can be combined. First, it allows to propel the ship when there is no wind or when sails cannot be used, for example when leaving or entering a harbour. Second, combined with a generator, a diesel engine can produce electricity for daily life on board of the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of history, energy use on-board of a sailing ship was not too problematic. There was firewood for cooking and heating, and there were candles and oil lamps for lighting. There were no refrigerators for food storage, no showers or laundry machines for washing and cleaning, no electronic instruments for navigation and communication, no electric pumps in case of leaks or fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we now have higher standards in terms of safety, health, hygiene, thermal comfort, and convenience. The problem is that these higher standards are difficult to achieve when the ship does not have an engine that runs on fossil fuels. Modern heating systems, cooking devices, hot water boilers, refrigerators, freezers, lighting, safety equipment, and electronic instruments all need energy to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_crewman_with_his_model_of_the_%27Parma%27_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Crewman of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo; with a model of his ship. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Crewman of the &#39;Parma&#39; with a model of his ship. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern sailing ships often use a diesel engine to provide that energy (and to propel the ship if necessary). An example is the &lt;em&gt;Avontuur&lt;/em&gt; from Timbercoast, who has an engine of 300 HP, a 20 kW generator, and a fuel tank of 2,330 litres. Large sail training vessels and cruising ships have several engines and generators on-board. For example, the 48m long &lt;em&gt;Brig Morningster&lt;/em&gt; has a 450 HP engine and three generators with a total capacity of 100 kW, while the 56m long &lt;em&gt;Bark Europa&lt;/em&gt; has two 365 HP engines with three generators – and burns hundreds of litres of oil per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the lifestyle of the people on board, the emissions per passenger-km may rise to, or surpass, the levels of those of an airplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the emissions and other pollutants of these engines need to be taken into account when the environmental footprint of a sail trip is calculated. Depending on the lifestyle of the people on board, the emissions per passenger-km may rise to, or surpass, the levels of those of an airplane. To a lesser extent, electricity use on-board also increases the emissions of cargo transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;energy-use-on-board-a-sailing-ship&#34;&gt;Energy use on board a sailing ship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; has no diesel engine on board, which is a second reason to focus on this ship. Obviously, a sailing ship without an engine cannot proceed her voyage when there’s no wind. This is &lt;a href=&#34;/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/&#34;&gt;easily solved in the old-fashioned way&lt;/a&gt;: the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; stays where she is until the wind returns. A ship without an engine also needs tug boats – which usually burn fossil fuels – to get in and out of ports. For the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt;, these tug services account for 0.3 g/tkm of the total carbon footprint of 2 g/tkm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a diesel engine, the ship also needs to generate all energy for use on board from local energy sources, and this is the hard part. Renewable energy is intermittent and has low power density compared to fossil fuels, meaning that more space is needed to generate a given amount of power – which is more problematic at sea than it is on land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_--_renewing_caulking_on_the_poop_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Renewing caulking on the poop of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Renewing caulking on the poop of the &#39;Parma&#39;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; self-sufficient in terms of energy use, a first design decision was to shift energy use away from electricity whenever possible. This is especially important for high temperature heat, which cannot be supplied by electric heat pumps. The ship will have a pellet-stove on board to provide space heating, as well as a biodigester – never before used on a ship – to convert human and kitchen waste into gas for cooking. Thermal insulation of the ship is another priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, even with pellet-stove and biodigester (which themselves require electricity to operate), and with thermal insulation, energy demand on the ship can be as high as 50 kilowatt-hours of electricity per day (2 kW average power use). This concerns a “worst-case normal operation” scenario, when the ship is sailing in cold weather with 60 people on board. Power use will be lower in warmer weather and/or when less people are taken. During an emergency, the power requirements can amount to 8 kW, while more than 24 kWh of energy can be needed in just three hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hydrogenerators&#34;&gt;Hydrogenerators&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to produce this power? Solar panels and wind turbines are only a small part of the solution. Producing 50 kWh of energy per day would require at least 100 square metres of solar panels, for which there is little space on a 60 m long sailing ship. Vulnerability and shading by the sails make for further problems. Wind turbines can be attached in the rigging, but their power output is also limited. The low potential of solar and wind power are demonstrated by the earlier mentioned sailing ship &lt;em&gt;Avontuur&lt;/em&gt;. She has a 20 kW generator, powered by the diesel engine, but only 2.1 kW of solar panels and 0.8 kW of wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrogenerator is the only renewable power source that can provide a large sailing ship with enough energy for the use of modern technology on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrogenerator is the only renewable power source that can provide a large sailing ship with enough energy for the use of modern technology on board. Hydrogenerators are attached underneath the hull and work in the opposite way as a ship’s propeller. Instead of the propeller powering the ship, the ship powers the propeller, which turns a generator that produces electricity. In spite of its name and appearance, the hydrogenerator is actually a form of wind energy: the sails power the propellers. Obviously, this only works when the ship is sailing fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_furling_sail_on_the_main_yard_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Furling sail on the main yard of the Parma. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Furling sail on the main yard of the Parma. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; will be equipped with two large hydrogenerators, for which Simons calculated the power output at different speeds, taking into account the fact that the extra drag they produce slows down the ship somewhat. He concludes that the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; needs to sail at a speed of at least 7.5 knots to generate enough electricity. At that speed, the hydrogenerators produce an estimated 2,000 watts of power, which converts to roughly 50 kWh of electricity per day (24 hours of sailing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a lower speed of 4.75 knots, the generators produce 350 watts, which comes down to 8.4 kWh of energy over a period of 24 hours – only 1/6th of the maximum required energy. On the other hand, at higher speeds, the hydrogenerators produce more energy than necessary. At a speed of almost 10 knots they provide 120 kWh/day, at a speed of 12 knots this becomes 182 kWh/day – 3.5 times more than needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saltwater-batteries&#34;&gt;Saltwater batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to her hull speed, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; will be able to sail a little over 16 knots at absolute top speed – this is double the minimum speed required to generate enough power. Achieving this speed will be rare, because it needs calm seas and strong winds from the right direction. Nevertheless, in good wind conditions, the ship easily sails fast enough to produce all electricity for use on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good wind conditions can last for days, especially on the oceans, where winds are more powerful and predictable than on land. However, they are not guaranteed, and the ship will also sail at lower speeds, or find herself in becalmed conditions – when hydrogenerators are as useless as solar panels in the middle of the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because she has no engine, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; faces a double problem when there’s no wind: she cannot continue her voyage, and she has no energy to maintain life on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because she has no engine, the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; faces a double problem when there’s no wind: she cannot continue her voyage, and she has no energy to maintain life on board. The first problem is easily solved but the second is not. Life on board goes on, and so there is a continued need for power. To provide this, the ship needs energy storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To cover the needs for three days drifting in cold weather, an energy storage of 150 kWh would be required, not taking into account charge and discharge losses. Five or seven days of energy use on-board would require 250 to 350 kWh of storage. For emergency use, another 25 kWh of energy storage is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_scraping_the_deck_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Scraping the deck onboard the &amp;amp;lsquo;Parma&amp;amp;rsquo;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Scraping the deck onboard the &#39;Parma&#39;. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not having an engine, generator and fuel tank saves space on board, but this advantage can be quickly lost again when one starts to add batteries for the hydrogenerators. Lithium-ion batteries are very compact, but they cannot be considered sustainable and bring safety risks. That’s why Jorne Langelaan and Andrew Simons see more potential in – very aptly – saltwater batteries, which are non-flammable, non-toxic, easy to recycle, have wide temperature-tolerance, and can last for more than 15 years. Like the biodigester, they have never been used on a sailing ship before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike lithium-ion batteries, saltwater batteries are large and heavy. At 60 kg per kWh of storage capacity, a 150 kWh battery storage would add a weight of 9 tonnes, while a 350 kWh storage capacity would add 21 tonnes. Still, this compares favourably to the total cargo capacity (500 tonnes), and the batteries can serve as ballast if they are placed in the lower part of the ship’s hull. The space requirements are not too problematic, either. Even a 350 kWh energy storage only requires 14 to 29m3 of space, which is small compared to the 880m3 of cargo volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emissions that are produced by the manufacturing of the hydrogenerators, biodigester, and batteries are not included in the life cycle analysis of the ship, because there are no data available. However, these emissions must be relatively small. Hydrogenerators have much higher power density than wind turbines, and thus a relatively low embodied energy. A quick back-of-the-envelope calculation learns that the carbon footprint of 350 kWh saltwater batteries is around 70 tonnes of CO2. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;human-power&#34;&gt;Human Power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another renewable power source and energy storage on board of the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper&lt;/em&gt;, and that’s the humans themselves. Like the pellet stove and the biodigester, the use of human power could reduce the need for electricity. Nowadays, cargo ships and most large sailing ships have electric or hydraulic winches, pumps, and steering gear, saving manual labour at the expense of higher energy use. In contrast, &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper&lt;/em&gt; sticks to manual handling of the ship as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_crew_at_the_capstan_weighing_anchor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Crew at the capstan of the Parma, weighing anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Crew at the capstan of the Parma, weighing anchor. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simons and Langelaan are also considering the addition of a few rowing machines, coupled to generators, to produce emergency power. Two rowing machines could provide roughly 400 watts of power. If they are operated around the clock in shifts, they could supply the ship with an extra 9.6 kWh of energy per day (ignoring energy losses) – one fifth of the total maximum electricity use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as I tell Simons and Langelaan ten rowing machines operated continually in shifts would provide as much power as the hydrogenerators at a speed of 7.5 knots. If there are 60 people on board, and everybody would generate power for less than one hour per day, no hydrogenerators and batteries would be needed at all. “A very interesting thought”, answers Simons, “but what impression would we be painted with?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hot-showers&#34;&gt;Hot Showers?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with a biodigester, hydrogenerators, batteries, and rowing machines, the passengers and crew on board the EcoClipper500 would be far short of luxurious, and perhaps too short of comfortable for some. For example, if 60 people on board the ship would take a daily hot shower – &lt;a href=&#34;/2019/10/mist-showers-sustainable-decadence/&#34;&gt;which requires on average 2.1 kilowatt-hours of energy and 76.5 litres of water on land&lt;/a&gt; – total electricity use per day would be 126 kWh, more than double the energy the ship produces at a speed of 7.5 knots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ship could supply this energy at a higher sailing speed, but there would also be a need for 4,590 liters of water per day, a quantity that could only be produced from seawater – a process that requires a lot of energy. Even a crew of 12 taking a daily hot shower would require 25.2 kWh of energy per day, half of what the hydrogenerators produce at a sailing speed of 7.5 knots. The &lt;em&gt;Bark Europa&lt;/em&gt; is the only sailing ship mentioned in this article that has hot showers in every (shared) cabin, but it is also the ship with the biggest generators and the highest fuel use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Parma_-_on_the_forecastle_in_fine_weather_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;On the forecastle head of the Parma in fine weather. Image by Alan Villiers, 1932.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 On the forecastle head of the Parma in fine weather. Image by Alan Villiers, 1932. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Simons: “On the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; there needs to be a manageable compromise between energy use and comfort. Energy use on board will have to be actively managed. Resources are finite, just like for the planet. In many ways the ship is a microcosm of challenges that the wider world has to face and find solutions to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jorne Langelaan: “At sea you are in a different world. It doesn’t matter anymore if you can take a daily shower or not. What matters are the people, the movements of the ship, and the vast wilderness of ocean around you”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;measuring-the-right-things&#34;&gt;Measuring the right things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article has compared the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; sailing ship with the average container ship, bulk carrier, and airplane in terms of emissions per tonne- or passenger-kilometer. However, these values are abstractions that obscure much more important information: the total emissions that are produced by all passengers and all cargo, over all kilometres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The international ocean freight trade increased from 4 billion tonnes of cargo in 1990 to 11.2 billion tonnes in 2019, resulting in more than 1 billion tonnes of emissions. International air passenger numbers grew from 1 billion in 1990 to 4.5 billion in 2019, resulting in 915 million tonnes of emissions. Consequently, lowering the emissions per tonne- and passenger-kilometre is neither a necessity nor a guarantee for a reduction in emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we cut international cargo traffic more than fivefold, and passenger traffic more than tenfold, then the emissions of all container ships and airplanes would be lower than the emissions of all sailing ships carrying 11.2 billion tonnes of cargo and 4.5 billion of passengers. Vice versa, if we switch to sailing ships, but keep on transporting more and more cargo and passengers across the planet, we will eventually produce just as much in emissions as we do today with fossil fuel powered transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century/images/dithers/Grace_Harwar_-_the_mizzen_of_the_ship;_view_aft_from_the_main_crosstrees_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The mizzen of the &amp;amp;lsquo;Grace Harwar&amp;amp;rsquo;; view aft from the main crosstrees. Alan Villiers, 1932-33.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The mizzen of the &#39;Grace Harwar&#39;; view aft from the main crosstrees. Alan Villiers, 1932-33. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this would ever happen. The amount of cargo that was traded across the oceans in 2019 equals the freight capacity of 22.4 million &lt;em&gt;EcoClippers&lt;/em&gt;. Assuming the &lt;em&gt;EcoClipper500&lt;/em&gt; can make 2-3 trips per year, we would need to build and operate at least 7.5 million ships, with a total crew of at least 90 million people. Those ships could only take 0.5 billion passengers (12 passengers and 8 trainees per ship), so we would need millions of ships and crew members more to replace international air traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should not be fooled by abstract relative measurements, which only serve to keep the focus on growth and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is technically possible, and as we have seen, it would produce less in emissions than the present alternatives. However, it’s more likely that a switch to sailing ships is accompanied by a decrease in cargo and passenger traffic, and this has everything to do with scale and speed. A lot of freight and passengers would not be travelling if it were not for the high speeds and low costs of today’s airplanes and container ships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would make little sense to transport iPhones parts, Amazon wares, sweatshop clothes, or citytrippers with sailing ships. A sailing ship is more than a technical means of transportation: it implies another view on consumption, production, time, space, leisure, and travel. For example, a lot of freight now travels in different directions for each next processing stage before it is delivered as a final product. In contrast, all sail cargo companies mentioned in this article only take cargo that cannot be produced locally, and which is one trip from producer to consumer. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that even if sailing ships have diesel engines on board, they would still bring a significant decrease in the total emissions for freight and passenger traffic, simply because they would reduce the absolute number of passengers, cargo, and kilometers. We should not be fooled by abstract relative measurements, which only serve to keep the focus on growth and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ecoclipper.org/&#34;&gt;More about the EcoClipper500&lt;/a&gt;. Most images: &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Photographs_by_Alan_Villiers&#34;&gt;Alan Villiers collection&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1978 and 2004, the Avontuur was operated as sail cargo vessel under Captain Paul Wahlen. The Apollonia, originally built in 1946, is another cargo sailing ship in operation since 2014. It is 19.5 metres long and carries 10 tonnes of cargo.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very recently, &lt;a href=&#34;https://graindesail.com/fr/&#34;&gt;Grain de Sail&lt;/a&gt; was built and launched for Trans-Atlantic shipping of wine and cocoa. She is a modern sailing ship without an engine, built from aluminium, and can take 35 tonnes of cargo.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Simons: “There are plenty historical sailing ships, but either very costly to get into service as a regulatory compliant cargo vessel, because they are still used for other purposes, or not suitable.”&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study can be downloaded when you subscribe to EcoClipper&amp;rsquo;s newsletter. The research is based on a typical life cycle analysis, but note that this is not a peer reviewed study.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the envelope got lost.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the EcoClipper, most of the emissions are produced during the construction of the ship, while in the case of bulk carriers and container ships, they are mainly produced during operation and fuel production.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest container ships now take 190,000 tonnes of cargo.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not much data available on saltwater batteries, but they are less energy-intensive to build than many other types of batteries. The calculation is based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.solarquotes.com.au/blog/aquion-salt-water-battery/&#34;&gt;an estimate of 66 kg CO2/kWh of storage capacity&lt;/a&gt; and three generations of batteries over a period of 50 years.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost one third of all cargo transported are fossil fuels themselves.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make Wind Power Sustainable Again</title>
      <link>/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/forest-of-wind-turbines_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="59998" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/forest-of-wind-turbines_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration: Eva Miquel for Low-tech Magazine.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration: Eva Miquel for Low-tech Magazine.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than two thousand years, windmills were built from recyclable or reusable materials: wood, stone, brick, canvas, metal. When – electricity producing – wind turbines appeared in the 1880s, the materials didn’t change. It’s only since the arrival of plastic composite blades in the 1980s that wind power has become the source of a toxic waste product that ends up in landfills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New wood production technology and design makes it possible to build larger wind turbines almost entirely out of wood again – not just the blades, but also the rest of the structure. This would solve the waste issue and make the manufacturing of wind turbines largely independent of fossil fuels and mined materials. A forest planted in between the wind turbines could provide the wood for the next generation of wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-sustainable-is-a-windmill-blade&#34;&gt;How Sustainable is a Windmill Blade?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wind turbines are considered to be a clean and sustainable source of power.  However, while they can indeed generate electricity with lower CO2-emissions than fossil fuel power plants, they also produce a lot of waste. This is easily overlooked, because roughly 90% of the mass of a large wind turbine is steel, mainly concentrated in the tower. Steel is commonly recycled and this explains why wind turbines have very short energy payback times – the recycled steel can be used to produce new wind turbine parts, which greatly lowers the energy required during the manufacturing process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, wind turbine blades are made from light-weight plastic composite materials, which are voluminous and impossible to recycle. Although the mass of the blades is limited compared to the total mass of a wind turbine, it’s not negligible. For example, one 60 m long fiberglass blade weighs 17 tonnes, meaning that a 5 MW wind turbine produces more than 50 tonnes of plastic composite waste from the blades alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/wind-turbine-blade_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A fiberglass reinforced plastic blade. Source: Gurit.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A fiberglass reinforced plastic blade. Source: [Gurit](https://www.gurit.com/Our-Business/Industries--Markets/Wind). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A windmill blade typically consists of a combination of epoxy – a petroleum product – with fiberglass reinforcements. The blades also contain sandwiched core materials, such as polyvinyl chloride foam, polyethylene terephtalate foam, balsa wood (intertwined in fibers and epoxy) and polyurethane coatings. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the steel in the tower, the plastic in blades cannot be recycled to make new plastic blades. The material can only be “downcycled”, for instance by shredding it, which damages the fibers and makes them useless for anything but a filler reinforcement in cement or asphalt production. Other methods are being investigated, but they all run into the same problem: nobody wants the “recycled” material. Some architects have re-used windmill blades, for example to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notechmagazine.com/2015/02/a-world-made-of-rotor-blades.html&#34;&gt;build benches or playgrounds&lt;/a&gt;. But we cannot build everything out of wind turbine blades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 5 MW wind turbine contains more than 50 tonnes of unrecyclable plastic in the blades alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the limited options for recycling and re-use, windmill blades are usually landfilled (in the US) or incinerated (in the EU). The latter approach is not less unsustainable, because incinerating the blades only partially reduces the amount of material to be landfilled (60% of the scrap remains as ash) and converts the rest into air pollution. Furthermore, given that fiberglass is incombustible, the caloric value of the blades is so limited that little or no power can be produced. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dealing-with-waste--25-years-later&#34;&gt;Dealing With Waste – 25 Years Later&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the roughly 250,000 wind turbines now in operation worldwide were installed less than 25 years ago, which is their estimated life expectancy. However, the rapid growth of wind power over the last two decades will soon be reflected in a delayed but ever increasing and never-ending supply of waste materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example in Europe, the share of installed wind turbines older than 15 years increases from 12% in 2016 to 28% in 2020. In Germany, Spain and Denmark, their share increases to 41-57%. In 2020 alone, these countries will each have to dispose of 6,000 to 12,000 wind turbine blades. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/old-fashioned-windmill-sail_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Old-fashioned windmills had sails made entirely from recyclable materials. Image: Rasbak (CC BY-SA 3.0)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Old-fashioned windmills had sails made entirely from recyclable materials. Image: Rasbak (CC BY-SA 3.0) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discarded blades will not only become more numerous but also larger, reflecting a continuous trend towards ever larger rotor diameters. Wind turbines built 25 years ago had blade lengths of around 15-20 m, while today’s blades reach lengths of 75-80 m or more. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Estimates based on current growth figures for wind power have suggested that composite materials from blades worldwide will amount to 330,000 tonnes of waste per year by 2028, and to 418,000 tonnes per year by 2040. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapid growth in wind power over the last two decades will soon be reflected in a delayed but ever increasing and never-ending supply of waste materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are conservative estimates, because numerous blade failures have been reported, and because constant development of more efficient blades with higher power generating capacity is resulting in blade replacement well before their estimated lifespan. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Furthermore, this amount of waste results from wind turbines installed between 2005 and 2015, when wind power only supplied a maximum of 4% of global power demand. If wind would supply a more desirable 40% of (current) power demand, there would be three to four million tonnes of waste per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;windmill-blades-through-history&#34;&gt;Windmill Blades Through History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet a look at the history of wind power shows that plastic is not an essential material. The use of wind for mechanical power production dates back to Antiquity, and the first electricity generating windmills – now called wind turbines – were built in the 1880s. However, fiberglass blades only took off in the 1980s. For some two thousand years, windmills of whatever type were entirely recyclable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/la-cour-wind-turbine_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The first wind turbines in Europe, built by Paul La Cour in Denmark, had traditional slatted wooden sails. Image: Paul La Cour Museum.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The first wind turbines in Europe, built by Paul La Cour in Denmark, had traditional slatted wooden sails. Image: Paul La Cour Museum. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old-fashioned windmills had towers built out of wood, stone, or brick. Their “blades” or “sails” were usually made of a wood framework covered with canvas or wood boards. In later centuries, parts were increasingly made from iron, also a recyclable material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When new types of sails were invented in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries (such as spring, patent, and rolling-reefer sails), as well as in the twentieth century (Dekkerized and Bilau sails), &lt;a href=&#34;/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;the design changed but the materials remained the same (eventually including aluminum)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Furthermore, contrary to modern wind turbines, which need to be replaced regularly and in their entirety, old-fashioned windmills could last for many decades or even centuries through regular repair and maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at the history of wind power shows that plastic is not an essential material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first wind turbine in the US, built by Charles F. Brush, had a 17 m diameter annular sail with 144 thin blades made of cedar wood. The first wind turbine in Europe, built by Paul La Cour in Denmark, had four traditional slatted wooden sails with a rotor diameter of 22.8 m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La Cour’s design was copied by local enterprises in Denmark, resulting in thousands of wind turbines operating on Danish farms between 1900 and 1920. Dozens of experimental wind turbines were built during the first half of the twentieth century, including some with steel blades, such as the 1939 Smith-Putnam wind turbine in the US. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/gedser-wind-turbine_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The three-bladed Gedser wind turbine relied on an air frame superstructure for blade stiffening.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The three-bladed Gedser wind turbine relied on an air frame superstructure for blade stiffening. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1957, Johannes Juul – a student of Paul La Cour – built the three-bladed Gedser wind turbine. It had a rotor diameter of 24 m and relied on an air frame superstructure of steel wires for rotor and blade stiffening. The blades were built from steel spars, with aluminium shells supported by wooden ribs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gedser turbine remained the most successful wind turbine until the mid-1980s. It ran for 11 years without maintenance, generating up to 360,000 kWh per year, but was not repaired when a bearing failed. When the turbine was refurbished and tested in the late 1970s, it performed better than the first wind turbines with fiberglass blades. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;size-matters&#34;&gt;Size Matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first wind turbine with fiberglass blades was installed in 1978 in Denmark, where it powered a school. With its 54 m diameter rotor, the Tvind turbine was at the time the largest wind turbine ever built. After 1980, fiberglass blades became standard in Denmark and the “Danish design” was later copied all over the world. The plastic blade, so it seems, is what defines the modern wind turbine. This presents us with a dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch to fiberglass blades was mainly driven by the desire to build larger wind turbines. Larger wind turbines lower the cost per kilowatt-hour of generated electricity, for two reasons: the wind increases with height, and the doubling of the rotor radius increases power output four times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The desire to build larger wind turbines has driven the wind industry ever since. Rotor diameters increased from around 50 m in the 1990s to 120 m in the 2000s. Today’s largest off-shore wind turbines have rotor diameters of more than 160 m, and a 12 MW turbine with a 220 m rotor diameter is being constructed in the Netherlands. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/improved-windmill-sail_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Improved windmill blade from the 1940s, built and designed by P.L. Fauel. Image: Rasbak (CC BY-SA 3.0)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Improved windmill blade from the 1940s, built and designed by P.L. Fauel. Image: Rasbak (CC BY-SA 3.0) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, with increasing size, the mass of the rotor blade also increases, which requires lighter materials. At the same time, larger blades deflect more, so that their structural stiffness is of increasing importance to maintain optimal aerodynamic performance and to avoid the blade hitting the tower. In short, larger wind turbines with longer blades place ever higher demands on the materials used, and these exceed the capacities of recyclable materials. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Wind turbines have become more efficient, but also less sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larger wind turbines with longer blades place ever higher demands on the materials used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, this trend is illustrated by the increasing use of carbon fiber reinforced plastic, which is even stronger, stiffer and lighter than fiberglass reinforced plastic. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The use of carbon fibers – which further complicates potential recycling – has become standard in the largest wind turbine blades, mainly in highly stressed locations such as the blade root or the spar caps. Consequently, we have again entered a new era in which blades are now so large that they cannot be made out of fiberglass reinforced composites alone anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reinventing-the-windmill-blade&#34;&gt;Reinventing the Windmill Blade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An industry that calls itself sustainable and renewable cannot send millions of tonnes of plastic waste to landfills each year. Consequently, could we revert to building wind turbine blades from recyclable materials alone? And how large could we build them? To which extent can efficiency and sustainability be reconciled?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/bilau-sails_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Improved windmill blade from the 1930s, designed by Kurt Bilau. The tower is made of stone, the sails are made of wood and aluminum. Image: Frank Vincentz (CC BY-SA 3.0).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Improved windmill blade from the 1930s, designed by Kurt Bilau. The tower is made of stone, the sails are made of wood and aluminum. Image: Frank Vincentz (CC BY-SA 3.0). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most research into the design of more sustainable wind turbine blades sticks with plastic as the main material. Thermoplastics can be melted and re-used, making it possible to recycle the blades into new wind turbine blades, even on-site. However, due to the material’s lower strength and stiffness, these blades have not been built larger than 9 m for now. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another area of development is the substitution of glass fibers for wood or flax fibers. These blades can be larger, but they have only small sustainability advantages over fiberglass-epoxy blades. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The petroleum-based epoxy is more harmful than the glass fiber, and natural fiber based composite materials absorb more of it. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The length of wood blades is no longer limited by the availability of large tree trunks of consistent quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some engineers and scientists follow different paths and revert to more traditional wood construction. For small wind turbines, &lt;a href=&#34;/2019/06/reinventing-the-small-wind-turbine/&#34;&gt;blades can be carved out of solid wood&lt;/a&gt;. For larger wind turbines, the blades can be composed of a hollow aerodynamic shell and an internal framework of ribs and stringers supported by a beam called the spar – all built from laminated veneer wood boards, beams and panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;laminated-veneer-lumber&#34;&gt;Laminated Veneer Lumber&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laminated veneer lumber – in which the wood is peeled off the tree and then glued back together in thin layers – is a wood product that appeared in the 1980s, and which has an important advantage in relation to solid wood components. The consistency of wood can vary within a single tree. Therefore, the length of the wood spars used in pre-industrial windmills was limited by the availability of large tree trunks of consistent quality. The largest traditional windmill ever built – the 1900 Murphy mill in San Francisco – had a rotor diameter of 35 m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/patent-sails_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Patent sails with Dekker leading edges, 1940s. Image: Reboelje.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Patent sails with Dekker leading edges, 1940s. Image: Reboelje. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the process of veneering spreads out defects such as knots, giving better and more predictable stiffness properties. This allows to build larger wooden blades. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Wood laminates offer substantial cost and weight reductions as compared to fiberglass. Although the strength and stiffness are lower, much of the load that the blade must support is a consequence of its own weight, so a wood blade doesn’t need to be as strong as a fiberglass blade. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nevertheless, the low stiffness of wood makes it difficult to limit the elastic deflections for very large rotor blades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 2017 study of a 5 MW wind turbine with 61.5 m long blades, conducted at UMassAmherst in the US, it was calculated that in order to be stiff enough and withstand the forces that it’s exposed to, a blade made of laminated wood veneer panels would be 2.8 heavier than a plastic blade (48 versus 17 tonnes) and have a laminate of over 50 cm thick. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although this suggests that it’s technically possible to build a wooden blade more than 60 m long, it’s not very practical. With heavier blades, the wind turbine needs to be built much stronger, which increases the costs and the use of resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;best-of-both-worlds&#34;&gt;Best of Both Worlds?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s two ways to solve this problem. The first is to design a blade largely made from laminated veneer lumber, but reinforced with carbon composite spars and covered with an outer layer of fiberglass composite. In the above mentioned study it was found that such a wood-carbon hybrid blade is stiff enough to reach a length of 61.5 m for a 5 MW turbine, and can be built 3 tonnes lighter than a fiberglass blade. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another study for a wood-carbon blade of the same length comes to a similar conclusion, although in this case the wood-carbon blade is slightly heavier than the plastic blade. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blade largely made from laminated veneer lumber, but reinforced with carbon composite spars, can be built more than 60 metres long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wood-carbon blades contain less plastic composite material, and the plastic is not intertwined with wood throughout the blade but clearly separated from it, making blade re-use, recycling or incineration more attractive. However, according to the studies mentioned above, a wood-carbon blade still contains 2.5 tonnes &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to 6.2 tonnes &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref6:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of plastic composites, meaning that a three-bladed 5 MW wind turbine would produce 7.5 to 18.4 tonnes of unrecyclable waste – compared to 50 tonnes for a conventional blade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;smaller-wind-turbines&#34;&gt;Smaller Wind Turbines?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The environmental damage of the carbon-epoxy spars can be viewed as acceptable, if compared to the larger damage done by conventional wind turbine blades. However, the waste problem would not be solved, and further growth in wind power would still result in ever larger waste streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/carbon-spar-caps_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A laminated wooden blade with carbon spar caps. Source: [^14]&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A laminated wooden blade with carbon spar caps. Source: [^14] 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, we could define sustainability in more ambitious terms, and build wind turbine blades completely out of wood again – even if this means that we have to build them smaller. There’s an extra argument to question our focus on efficiency: the decrease in sustainability not only shows in the blades. Other parts of wind turbines are also increasingly made from plastic composites – most notably the nose cone and the nacelle cover (the housing that protects the drivetrain and the auxiliary equipment from the elements). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other trends are the increased use of electronics, which are &lt;a href=&#34;/2009/06/the-monster-footprint-of-digital-technology/&#34;&gt;not suited for recycling&lt;/a&gt;, and of permanent magnet generators based on rare earth materials, which save costs compared to a mechanical gearbox but only at the expense of more destructive mining. Larger wind turbines also kill more birds and bats. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By sacrificing some efficiency, we could gain a lot in sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By sacrificing some efficiency, we could gain a lot in sustainability. Wind power advocates may not agree, because it would make wind power less competitive with fossil fuels. However, more expensive wind power can always be counteracted by higher prices for fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s really problematic is our choice of cheap fossil fuels as a benchmark to determine the viability of wind power. It’s by aiming to compete with fossil fuels – and thus by aiming to provide the energy for a lifestyle built on fossil fuels – that wind turbines have become increasingly damaging to the environment. If we would reduce energy demand, smaller and less efficient wind turbines would not be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/first-american-wind-turbine_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The first wind turbine in the US, built by Charles F. Brush, had a 17 m diameter annular sail with 144 thin blades made of cedar wood.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The first wind turbine in the US, built by Charles F. Brush, had a 17 m diameter annular sail with 144 thin blades made of cedar wood. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How large could we build practical wind turbine blades from laminated veneer lumber alone? Nobody seems to know. I asked Rachel Koh, the scientist who calculated the requirements for the 61.5 m wood-only blade, but she couldn’t help me: “I only ran the model for the blades of a 5 MW turbine. It would be hypothetically possible to run another study to answer your question, but it&amp;rsquo;s not a small undertaking”. She also notes that it’s possible to further improve the stiffness of wood laminates with manufacturing innovations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-forest-of-wind-turbines&#34;&gt;A Forest of Wind Turbines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether we opt for large wood-carbon blades or smaller wood-only blades, in both cases we could also build the tower and the nacelle cover from laminated wood products. In 2012, the German company TimberTower built a laminated wood tower 100 m tall for a 1.5 MW wind turbine. A wooden tower seems to be besides the point, because it replaces part of a wind turbine that’s already perfectly recyclable. However, a wind turbine of which the structure is almost completely built out of wood offers extra benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2019/06/how-to-make-wind-power-sustainable-again/images/dithers/forest-detail_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Illustration: Eva Miquel for Low-tech Magazine&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Illustration: Eva Miquel for Low-tech Magazine 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wood could make the production of wind turbines entirely independent of mined materials and of fossil fuels, except for the gearwork and the electric components (but further gains can be achieved, whenever possible, by using wind power for &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;direct mechanical&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Furthermore, wooden wind turbines could become a carbon sink – sequestering CO2 from the atmosphere in their wood components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the space between wind turbines on a wind farm, which is not suited as a residential area, could be used to grow a forest that would provide the wood for the next generation of wind turbines. The lumber could be sawed, processed and assembled on-site, which eliminates the energy use associated with the transport of wind turbine parts. The energy required for manufacturing the laminates and for constructing the turbines could come from the windmills, as well as from forest biomass. Especially if blades are made of wood only, the wind turbine could become a textbook example of &lt;a href=&#34;/2018/11/how-circular-is-the-circular-economy/&#34;&gt;the circular economy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-solar-panels&#34;&gt;What about solar panels?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A forthcoming article investigates the sustainability of solar panels. Is toxic and unrecyclable waste inherent to solar PV power? Could we build solar panels using sustainable materials? And what would that mean for the affordability and efficiency of solar power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramirez-Tejeda, Katerin, David A. Turcotte, and Sarah Pike. &amp;ldquo;Unsustainable Wind Turbine Blade Disposal Practices in the United States: A Case for Policy Intervention and Technological Innovation.&amp;rdquo; NEW SOLUTIONS: A Journal of Environmental and Occupational Health Policy 26.4 (2017): 581-598. &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.wind-watch.org/ramireztejeda2016-bladedisposal.pdf&#34;&gt;http://docs.wind-watch.org/ramireztejeda2016-bladedisposal.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilburn, David R. Wind energy in the United States and materials required for the land-based wind turbine industry from 2010 through 2030. US Department of the Interior, US Geological Survey, 2011. &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2011/5036/sir2011-5036.pdf&#34;&gt;https://pubs.usgs.gov/sir/2011/5036/sir2011-5036.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jensen, Jonas Pagh. &amp;ldquo;Evaluating the environmental impacts of recycling wind turbines.&amp;rdquo; Wind Energy 22.2 (2019): 316-326. &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/we.2287&#34;&gt;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/we.2287&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martínez, Eduardo, et al. &amp;ldquo;Life cycle assessment of a multi-megawatt wind turbine.&amp;rdquo; Renewable energy 34.3 (2009): 667-673. &lt;a href=&#34;http://communityrenewables.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Life-cycle-analysis-turbines_Renewable-Energy_2009.pdf&#34;&gt;http://communityrenewables.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Life-cycle-analysis-turbines_Renewable-Energy_2009.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ziegler, Lisa, et al. &amp;ldquo;Lifetime extension of onshore wind turbines: A review covering Germany, Spain, Denmark, and the UK.&amp;rdquo;  Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 82 (2018): 1261-1271. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032117313503&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1364032117313503&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lefeuvre, Anaële, et al. &amp;ldquo;Anticipating in-use stocks of carbon fiber reinforced polymers and related waste flows generated by the commercial aeronautical sector until 2050.&amp;rdquo; Resources, Conservation and Recycling 125 (2017): 264-272. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0921344917301775&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0921344917301775&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De Decker, Kris. &amp;ldquo;Wind powered factories: history (and future) of industrial windmills.&amp;rdquo; Low-Tech Magazine. Barcelona (2009). &lt;a href=&#34;/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rise of Modern Wind Energy: Wind Power for the World. Pan Stanford Publishing, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crcpress.com/Wind-Power-for-the-World-The-Rise-of-Modern-Wind-Energy/Maegaard-Krenz-Palz/p/book/9789814364935&#34;&gt;https://www.crcpress.com/Wind-Power-for-the-World-The-Rise-of-Modern-Wind-Energy/Maegaard-Krenz-Palz/p/book/9789814364935&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lundsager, P., Sten Tronæs Frandsen, and Carl Jørgen Christensen. &amp;ldquo;Analysis of data from the Gedser wind turbine 1977-1979.&amp;rdquo; (1980). &lt;a href=&#34;http://orbit.dtu.dk/files/33441311/ris_m_2242.pdf&#34;&gt;http://orbit.dtu.dk/files/33441311/ris_m_2242.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gupta, Ashwani K. &amp;ldquo;Efficient wind energy conversion: evolution to modern design.&amp;rdquo; Journal of Energy Resources Technology 137.5 (2015): 051201. &lt;a href=&#34;http://energyresources.asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/article.aspx?articleid=2211540&#34;&gt;http://energyresources.asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/article.aspx?articleid=2211540&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brøndsted, Povl, Hans Lilholt, and Aage Lystrup. &amp;ldquo;Composite materials for wind power turbine blades.&amp;rdquo; Annu. Rev. Mater. Res. 35 (2005): 505-538. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www-eng.lbl.gov/~shuman/NEXT/MATERIALS&amp;amp;COMPONENTS/Pressure_vessels/FRP_Hutter_flange.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www-eng.lbl.gov/~shuman/NEXT/MATERIALS&amp;amp;COMPONENTS/Pressure_vessels/FRP_Hutter_flange.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Koh, Rachel. &amp;ldquo;Bio-based Wind Turbine Blades: Renewable Energy Meets Sustainable Materials for Clean, Green Power.&amp;rdquo; (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholarworks.umass.edu/dissertations_2/1102/&#34;&gt;https://scholarworks.umass.edu/dissertations_2/1102/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Murray, Robynne, et al. Manufacturing a 9-meter thermoplastic composite wind turbine blade. No. NREL/CP-5000-68615. National Renewable Energy Lab.(NREL), Golden, CO (United States), 2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nrel.gov/docs/fy18osti/68615.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.nrel.gov/docs/fy18osti/68615.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Borrmann, Rasmus. “Structural design of a wood-CFRP wind turbine blade model.” (2016) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eksh.org/fileadmin/bilder/themen/Energieforschung/02_-_Final_Report_-_Strcutural_Design_of_a_Wood-CFRP_Wind_Turbine_Blade_Model.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.eksh.org/fileadmin/bilder/themen/Energieforschung/02_-&lt;em&gt;Final_Report&lt;/em&gt;-_Strcutural_Design_of_a_Wood-CFRP_Wind_Turbine_Blade_Model.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spera, David. “Wind Turbine Technology: Fundamental Concepts in Wind Turbine Engineering, Second Edition.” (2009) &lt;a href=&#34;https://ebooks.asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/book.aspx?bookid=271&#34;&gt;https://ebooks.asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/book.aspx?bookid=271&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corona, Andrea, et al. &amp;ldquo;Comparative environmental sustainability assessment of bio-based fibre reinforcement materials for wind turbine blades.&amp;rdquo; Wind Engineering 39.1 (2015): 53-63.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://orbit.dtu.dk/files/129909032/0309_524x_2E39_2E1_2E53.pdf&#34;&gt;http://orbit.dtu.dk/files/129909032/0309_524x_2E39_2E1_2E53.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of wood for wind turbine construction. Meade Gougeon, NASA. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19800008214.pdf&#34;&gt;https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/19800008214.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loss, Scott R., Tom Will, and Peter P. Marra. &amp;ldquo;Estimates of bird collision mortality at wind facilities in the contiguous United States.&amp;rdquo; Biological Conservation 168 (2013): 201-209. &lt;a href=&#34;https://repository.si.edu/bitstream/handle/10088/35192/NZP_Marra_2013-Estimates_of_bird_collision_mortality_at_wind_facilities_in_the_contiguous_United_States.pdf?sequence=1&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;https://repository.si.edu/bitstream/handle/10088/35192/NZP_Marra_2013-Estimates_of_bird_collision_mortality_at_wind_facilities_in_the_contiguous_United_States.pdf?sequence=1&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De Decker, Kris. &amp;ldquo;Heat your house with a mechanical windmill.&amp;rdquo; Low-tech Magazine. Barcelona (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
