<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/tags/power-transmission/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline</description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mar-ver.github.io/tags/power-transmission/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Keeping Some of the Lights On: Redefining Energy Security</title>
      <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/images/dithers/lighter_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="5475" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/images/dithers/lighter_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Maintaining a steady supply of something that’s finite is impossible. Image: Camilla MP.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Maintaining a steady supply of something that’s finite is impossible. Image: [Camilla MP](https://www.flickr.com/photos/dieknochenblume/8454004839/in/photolist-nJrNa3-z9St6d-vicpX8-bjNYMa-CNWajb-PKUbFu-8TqWZX-qzaoch-r3Gb3J-28jYUV3-p3gMD1-snwVj-2chyArN-4ehCVH-cWuLz-dT3Z78-pnFKK9-5qGDSP-hxU2d7-24uoKVs-f7CoCe-93ZqZQ-jPMVaK-T4yoN-4HiX59-97Kq68-23hFdSw-jE59uD-9aFpr7-68DbEo-NvymKZ-335BtT-8RtT65-a6Jut4-nt2zNy-qrkSGP-HPM9ee-bcdyA2-5Fy731-FGSpvq-eqKSpH-8jGFmq-qcFSw4-6USSog-dJEYby-jk3JQ2-7BMzWV-jetX2F-hLnHJy-5SHzAW). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a society depends more on energy sources for its daily functioning, it becomes more vulnerable if the supply of energy is interrupted. This obvious fact is ignored in current strategies to achieve energy security, making them counter-productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-energy-security&#34;&gt;What is Energy Security?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean for a society to have “energy security”? Although there are more than forty different definitions of the concept, they all share the fundamental criterium that energy supply should always meet energy demand. This also implies that energy supply needs to be constant – there can be no interruptions in the service. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example, the International Energy Agency (IEA) defines energy security as “the uninterrupted availability of energy sources at an affordable price”, the US Department of Energy and Climate Change (DECC) defines the concept as meaning that “the risks of interruption to energy supply are low”, and the EU defines it as a “stable and abundant supply of energy”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, energy security was achieved by securing access to &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2011/09/medieval-smokestacks-fossil-fuels-in-pre-industrial-times/&#34;&gt;forests or peat bogs&lt;/a&gt; for thermal energy, and to human, animal, wind or water power sources for mechanical energy. With the arrival of the Industrial Revolution, energy security came to depend on the supply of fossil fuels. As a theoretical concept, energy security is most closely related to the oil crises from the 1970s, when embargoes and price manipulations limited oil supply to Western nations. As a result, most industrialised societies still stockpile oil reserves that are equivalent to several months of consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although oil remains as vital to industrial economies as it was in the 1970s, mainly for transportation and agriculture, it’s now recognised that energy security in modern societies also depends on other infrastructures, such as those supplying gas, electricity, and even data. Furthermore, these infrastructures increasingly interconnect and depend on each other. For example, gas is an important fuel for power production, while the power grid is now required to operate gas pipelines. Power grids are needed to run data networks, and data networks are now needed to run power grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power grids are needed to run data networks, and data networks are needed to operate power grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article investigates the concept of energy security by focusing on the power grid, which has become just as vital to industrial societies as oil. Moreover, electrification is seen as a way to decrease dependency on fossil fuels – think electric vehicles, heat pumps, and wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “security” or “reliability” of a power grid can be measured precisely by indicators of continuity such as the “Loss-of-Load Probability” (LOLP), and the “System Average Interruption Duration Index” (SAIDI). Using these indicators, one can only conclude that power grids in industrial societies are very secure. For example, in Germany, power is available for 99.996% of the time, which corresponds to an interruption in service of less than half an hour per customer per year. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even the worst performing countries in Europe (Latvia, Poland, Lithuania) have supply shortages of only eight hours per customer per year, which corresponds to a reliability of 99.90%. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The US power grid is in between these values, with supply interruptions of less than four hours per customer per year (99.96% reliability). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-secure-is-a-renewable-power-grid&#34;&gt;How Secure is a Renewable Power Grid?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the current operation of infrastructures, the paradigm is that consumers could and should have access to as much electricity, gas, oil, data or water as they want, anytime they want it, for as long as they want it. The only requirement is that they pay the bill. Looking at the power sector, this vision of energy security is quite problematic, for several reasons. First of all, most energy sources from which electricity is made are finite – and maintaining a steady supply of something that’s finite is of course impossible. In the long run, the strategy to maintain energy security is certainly doomed to fail. In the shorter term, it may disrupt the climate and provoke armed conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Energy Agency (IEA), which was set up following the first oil crisis in the early 1970s, encourages the use of renewable energy sources in order to diversify the energy supply and improve energy security in the long term. A renewable power system is not dependent on foreign energy imports nor vulnerable to fuel price manipulations – which are the main worries in an energy infrastructure that is largely based on fossil fuels. Of course, solar panels and wind turbines have limited lifetimes and need to be manufactured, which also requires resources that could come from abroad or which can become depleted. But, once they are installed, renewable power systems are “secure” in a way and for a period of time that fossil fuels (and atomic energy) are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renewable energy sources pose fundamental challenges to the current understanding of energy security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, solar and wind power provide more security concerning physical failure or sabotage, even more so when renewable power production is decentralised. Renewable power plants also have lower CO2-emissions, and the extreme weather events caused by climate change are a risk to energy security as well. However, in spite of all these advantages, renewable energy sources pose fundamental challenges to the current understanding of energy security. Most importantly, the renewable energy sources with the largest potential – sun and wind – are only intermittently available, depending on the weather and the seasons. This means that solar and wind power don’t match the criterium that all definitions of energy security consider to be essential: the need for an uninterrupted, unlimited supply of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/images/dithers/security-nl_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Eduard Bezembinder.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: [Eduard Bezembinder](https://www.flickr.com/photos/bezembinder/3560945758/in/photolist-6qEM7w-7urQui-iSeKZ-8VjqeD-dUgKQ-e4ybCy-eke2Zk-ekeCdc-eke4NV-qBE1z-6Dfw5n-68EJKh-ekk6Rs-qBE2V-NqkS-oWp8Du-psYQc1-pCDop-5JSFFH-9fr321-oguPbE-6pZ6MT-dZ9YLx-vhpHJb-3oeLdu-69J2h1-7hatWp-d26CpQ-27dVzAC-5BEpZz-sUBfz-7B8zeq-HkygG-bHhG5R-2UoYjD-bRCZnx-o1e2oL-4LcBmy-69vhwD-ekz9ec-bLqreV-5jtvAp-2GUCLK-GpCny7-s36gn-dy6aBU-8moRHP-8rrRxd-5BJJyC-8KdmGR). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reliability of a power grid with a high share of solar and wind power would be significantly below today’s standards for continuity of service. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In such a renewable power grid, a 24/7 power supply can only be maintained at very high costs, because it requires an extensive infrastructure for energy storage, power transmission, and excess generation capacity. This additional infrastructure risks making a renewable power grid unsustainable, because above a certain threshold, the fossil fuel energy used for building, installing and maintaining this infrastructure becomes higher than the fossil fuel energy saved by the solar panels and the wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renewable energy sources like wind and sun have advantages that current definitions of energy security don’t capture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intermittency is not the only disadvantage of renewable energy sources. Although many media and environmental organisations have painted a picture of solar and wind power as abundant sources of energy (“The sun delivers more energy to Earth in an hour than the world consumes in a year”), reality is more complex. The “raw” supply of solar (and wind) energy is enormous indeed. However, because of their very low power density, to convert this energy supply into a useful form solar panels and wind turbines require magnitudes of order more space and materials compared to thermal power plants – even if the mining and distribution of fuels is included. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Therefore, a renewable power grid cannot guarantee that consumers have access to as much electricity as they want, even if the weather conditions are optimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-secure-is-an-off-the-grid-power-system&#34;&gt;How Secure is an Off-the-Grid Power System?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s energy policies related to electricity try to reconcile three aims: an uninterrupted and limitless supply of power, affordability of electricity prices,  and environmental sustainability. A power grid that is mainly based on fossil fuels and atomic energy cannot achieve the aim of environmental sustainability, and it can only achieve the other goals as long as foreign suppliers do not cut off supplies or raise energy prices (or as long as national or international reserves are not depleted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a renewable power grid cannot reconcile these three goals either. To achieve an unlimited 24/7 supply of power, the infrastructure needs to be oversized, which makes it expensive and unsustainable. Without that infrastructure, a renewable power grid could be affordable and sustainable, but it could never offer an unlimited 24/7 supply of power. Consequently, if we want a power infrastructure that is affordable and sustainable, we need to redefine the concept of energy security – and question the criterium of an unlimited and uninterrupted power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look beyond the typical large-scale central infrastructures in industrial societies, it becomes clear that not all provisioning systems offer a limitless supply of resources. Off-the-grid microgeneration – the local production and storage of electricity using batteries and solar PV panels or wind turbines – is one example. In principle, off-the-grid systems can be sized in such a way that they are “always on”. This can be done by following the “worst-month method”, which oversizes generation and storage capacity so that supply can meet demand even during the shortest and darkest days of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matching supply to demand at all times makes an off-the-grid system very costly and unsustainable, especially in high seasonality climates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, just like in an imaginary large-scale renewable power grid, matching supply to demand at all times makes an off-the-grid system very costly and unsustainable, especially in high seasonality climates. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Therefore, most off-the-grid systems are sized according to a method that aims for a compromise between reliability, economic cost and sustainability. The “loss-of-load probability sizing method” specifies a number of days per year that supply does not match demand. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In other words, the system is sized, not only according to a projected energy demand, but also according to the available budget and/or the available space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/images/dithers/solar-panel-in-snow_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Stephen Yang / The Solutions Project.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: [Stephen Yang / The Solutions Project](https://www.flickr.com/photos/149368236@N06/33068752693/in/photolist-Sob15v-bBnpyx-keyKG-cuaVX3-nuP1zk-U2eVh7-cuaWEf-pskKMf-cuaswE-p27cJW-cu9SQu-cuaMky-mCLFCt-ajiCfB-4AFrsp-943usV-TyoqrN-pu9HK-erKVcJ-aYHgDT-7zrUXc-tQv77b-6xot6g-baF4gg-Xjymka-qHgAkg-ii2jys-9eD7tj-9fJDFi-Ge2Mn-guUowg-amvdKB-cvDZ15-79wfLn-c6XjSS-ddFjjF-9KYuQV-8Zp8z6-guV3wK-9P1nHp-q5c2cz-9RCRVu-cD8w4d-9YDNzC-7ehy1e-4obYkG-8tkNMS-cvDZru-4obYtN-23Aqhr). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sizing an off-the-grid power system in this way generates significant cost reductions, even if “reliability” is reduced just a little bit. For example, a calculation for an off-the-grid house in Spain shows that decreasing the reliability from 99.75% to 99.00% produces a 60% cost reduction, with similar benefits for sustainability. Supply would be interrupted for 87.6 hours per year, compared to 22 hours in the higher reliability system. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the current understanding of energy security, off-the-grid power systems that are sized in this way are a failure: energy supply doesn’t always meet energy demand. However, off-gridders don’t seem to complain about a lack of energy security, on the contrary. There’s a simple reason for this: they adapt their energy demand to a limited and intermittent power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their 2015 book &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifeoffgrid.ca/off-grid-living-the-book/&#34;&gt;Off-the-Grid: Re-Assembling Domestic Life&lt;/a&gt;, Phillip Vannini and Jonathan Taggart document their travels across Canada to interview about 100 off-the-grid households. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Among their most important observations is that voluntary off-gridders use less electricity overall and routinely adapt their energy demand to the weather and the seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voluntary off-gridders use less electricity overall and routinely adapt their energy demand to the weather and the seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, washing machines, vacuum cleaners, power tools, toasters or videogame consoles are not used at all, or they are only used during periods of abundant energy, when batteries can accommodate no further charge. If the sky is overcast, off-gridders act differently to draw less power and have some more left over for the day after. Vannini and Taggart also observe that voluntary off-gridders seem to feel perfectly happy with levels of lighting or heating that are different from the standards that many in the western world have come to expect. Often, this shows itself in concentrating activities around more localised sources of heat and light. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar observations can be made in places where people – involuntarily – depend on infrastructures that are not always on. If centralised water, electricity and data networks are present in less industrialised countries, they are often characterised by regular and irregular interruptions in the supply. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, in spite of the very low reliability of these infrastructures – according to common indicators of continuity – life goes on. Daily household routines are shaped around disruptions of supply systems, which are viewed as normal and a largely accepted part of life. For example, if electricity, water or Internet are only available during certain times of the day, household taks or other activities are planned accordingly. People also use less energy overall: the infrastructure simply doesn’t allow for a resource-intensive lifestyle. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-reliable-less-secure&#34;&gt;More Reliable, Less Secure?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very high “reliability” of power grids in industrial societies is justified by calculating the “value of lost load” (VOLL), which compares the financial loss due to power shortages to the extra investment costs to avoid these shortages. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, the value of lost load is highly dependent on how society is organised. The more it depends on electricity, the higher the financial losses due to power shortages will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current definitions of energy security consider supply and demand to be unrelated, and focus almost entirely on securing energy supply. However, alternative forms of power infrastructures like those described above show that people adapt and match their expectations to a power supply that is limited and not always on. In other words, energy security can be improved, not just by increasing reliability, but also by reducing dependency on energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/images/dithers/energy-storage-gas-security_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Natural gas storage terminal. Jason Woodhead.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Natural gas storage terminal. [Jason Woodhead](https://www.flickr.com/photos/woodhead/7150825737/in/photolist-bTTRmV-85JomL-jysSQn-fw7gTZ-5Jkm2T-eDueWy-ohYc4x-fFxZCm-eD8VG8-eDfhqy-8pCnxZ-qPTdqx-22WNtVf-fFybmb-fFxRVG-fFyhCf-mGNU1p-24mDPG2-8efS2s-fFguSX-nN4pMi-fFgpjT-6br69i-hVGdgU-9DSQQ5-cDwVt-EqVP-dp7vJX-fwmwQh-oHAfHH-fFy6QS-fFgvS8-aaCofJ-fFxW5L-agEkAL-eDfonE-fFgrrn-eD9m9a-PLLffy-fFggcX-fFgka6-nRdzs-fFgwFH-88JrU8-nN4epz-2atchc9-nN523B-24mDNL4-2atciAb-GFzRM).  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demand and supply are also interlinked, and mutually influence each other, in 24/7 power systems – but with the opposite effect. Just like “unreliable” off-the-grid power infrastructures foster lifestyles that are less dependent on electricity, “reliable” infrastructures foster lifestyles that are increasingly dependent on electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Industrial societies with “reliable” power grids are in fact the weakest and most fragile in the face of supply interruptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their 2018 book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.routledge.com/Infrastructures-in-Practice-The-Dynamics-of-Demand-in-Networked-Societies/Shove-Trentmann/p/book/9781138476165&#34;&gt;Infrastructures and Practices: the Dynamics of Demand in Networked Societies&lt;/a&gt;, Olivier Coutard and Elizabeth Shove argue that an unlimited and uninterrupted power supply has enabled people in industrial societies to adopt a multitude of power dependent technologies – such as washing machines, air conditioners, refrigerators, automatic doors, or 24/7 mobile internet access – which become “normal” and central to everyday life. At the same time, alternative ways of doing things – such as washing clothes by hand, storing food without electricity, keeping cool without air-conditioning, or navigating and communicating without mobile phones – have withered away, or are withering away. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, energy security is in fact higher in off-the-grid power systems and “unreliable” central power infrastructures, while industrial societies are the weakest and most fragile in the face of supply interruptions. What is generally assumed to be a proof of energy security – an unlimited and uninterrupted power supply – is actually making industrial societies ever more vulnerable to supply interruptions: people increasingly lack the skills and the technology to function without a continuous power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;redefining-energy-security&#34;&gt;Redefining Energy Security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To arrive to a more accurate definition of energy security requires the concept to be defined, not in terms of commodities like kilowatt-hours of electricity, but in terms of energy services, social practices, or basic needs. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; People don’t need electricity in itself. What they need, is to store food, wash clothes, open and close doors, communicate with each other, move from one place to another, see in the dark, and so on. All these things can be achieved either with or without electricity, and in the first case, with more or less electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defined in this way, energy security is not just about securing the supply of electricity, but also about improving the resilience of the society, so that it becomes less dependent on a continuous supply of power. This includes the resilience of people (do they have the skills to do things without electricity?), the resilience of devices and technological systems (can they handle an intermittent power supply?), and the resilience of institutions (is it legal to operate a power grid that is not always on?). Depending on the resilience of the society, a disruption of the power supply may or may not lead to a disruption of energy services or social practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, although our food distribution system is dependent on a cold chain that requires a continuous power supply, there are many alternatives. We could adapt refrigerators to an irregular power supply by insulating them much better, we could reintroduce cold cellars (which keep food fresh without electricity), or we could relearn older methods of food storage, like fermentation. We could also improve people’s skills in terms of fresh cooking, switch to diets based on ingredients that don’t need cold storage, and encourage local daily shopping over weekly trips to large supermarkets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve energy security, we need to make infrastructures less reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at energy security in a more holistic way, taking into account both supply and demand, it quickly becomes clear that energy security in industrial societies continues to deteriorate. We keep delegating more and more tasks to machines, computers and large-scale infrastructures, thus increasing our dependency on electricity. Furthermore, the Internet is becoming just as essential as the power grid, and trends like cloud computing, the Internet of Things, and self-driving cars are all based on several interconnected layers of continuously operating infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/12/keeping-some-of-the-lights-on-redefining-energy-security/images/dithers/abandoned-power-line_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: An abandoned power line. Miura Paulison.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: An abandoned power line. [Miura Paulison](https://www.flickr.com/photos/paulisson_miura/10318768955/in/photolist-gHQovz-kCLi9r-82pqq6-f4539G-6i3Aih-5m5G9b-6RkZvr-6V6k85-2b9wdNP-4DvxJx-WfvmJT-5CGLgF-5C1ojh-eANWrM-kjDG4Z-9QKWz-DnnTH9-ntvKWL-82sxbf-UssMS3-deJRBD-d6qh1S-5C1ooU-tkcYLj-MpbqCB-84zF9u-5CM5d7-5CM51J-82ppX6-a1H2sr-Rd9o59-a1LEed-6W3He9-VCD56X-bg3vgT-5BW5CT-82sxDb-2b1hTxi-6hpZ1g-8d19tj-qm9Cy-cgpx3-gszM15-eANtbt-MpbCWK-98h2dj-7HyrGe-5md8aD-d9fLdq-2cyGoSv). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because demand and supply influence each other, we come to a counter-intuitive conclusion: to improve energy security, we need to make the power grid less reliable. This would encourage resilience and substitution, and thus make industrial societies less vulnerable to supply interruptions. Coutard and Shove argue that “it would make sense to pay more attention to opportunities for innovation that are opened when large network systems are weakened and abandoned, or when they become less reliable”. They add that the experiences of voluntary off-gridders “provide some insights into the types of configuration at stake”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguing for a less reliable power supply is sure to be controversial. In fact, “Keeping the lights on” is a phrase that is often used to justify energy reforms such as building more atomic plants, or keeping them in operation past their planned lifetimes. To achieve real energy security, “keeping the lights on” should be replaced by phrases like “keeping some of the lights on”, “which lights should we turn off next?”, or “what’s wrong with a bit more dark?”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Obviously, a less reliable energy supply would bring &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/&#34;&gt;fundamental changes to routines and technologies&lt;/a&gt;, whether it is in households, factories, transport systems, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/09/how-to-build-a-low-tech-website/&#34;&gt;communications networks&lt;/a&gt; – but that’s exactly the point. Present ways of life in industrial societies are simply &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/01/how-much-energy-do-we-need/&#34;&gt;not sustainable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was originally written for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk&#34;&gt;UK Demand Centre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winzer, Christian. &amp;ldquo;Conceptualizing energy security.&amp;rdquo; Energy policy 46 (2012): 36-48. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.repository.cam.ac.uk/bitstream/handle/1810/242060/cwpe1151.pdf?sequence=1&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&#34;&gt;https://www.repository.cam.ac.uk/bitstream/handle/1810/242060/cwpe1151.pdf?sequence=1&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sovacool, Benjamin K., and Ishani Mukherjee. &amp;ldquo;Conceptualizing and measuring energy security: A synthesized approach.&amp;rdquo; Energy 36.8 (2011): 5343-5355. &lt;a href=&#34;https://relooney.com/NS4053-Energy/00-Energy-Security_1.pdf&#34;&gt;https://relooney.com/NS4053-Energy/00-Energy-Security_1.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kruyt, Bert, et al. &amp;ldquo;Indicators for energy security.&amp;rdquo; Energy policy37.6 (2009): 2166-2181. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301421509000883&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301421509000883&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cherp, Aleh, and Jessica Jewell. &amp;ldquo;The concept of energy security: Beyond the four As.&amp;rdquo; Energy Policy 75 (2014): 415-421. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301421514004960&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301421514004960&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy security, International Energy Agency. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iea.org/topics/energysecurity/&#34;&gt;https://www.iea.org/topics/energysecurity/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucas, Javier Noel Valdés, Gonzalo Escribano Francés, and Enrique San Martín González. &amp;ldquo;Energy security and renewable energy deployment in the EU: Liaisons Dangereuses or Virtuous Circle?.&amp;rdquo; Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 62 (2016): 1032-1046. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Javier_Valdes4/publication/303361228_Energy_security_and_renewable_energy_deployment_in_the_EU_Liaisons_Dangereuses_or_Virtuous_Circle/links/5a536f45458515e7b72eab26/Energy-security-and-renewable-energy-deployment-in-the-EU-Liaisons-Dangereuses-or-Virtuous-Circle.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Javier_Valdes4/publication/303361228_Energy_security_and_renewable_energy_deployment_in_the_EU_Liaisons_Dangereuses_or_Virtuous_Circle/links/5a536f45458515e7b72eab26/Energy-security-and-renewable-energy-deployment-in-the-EU-Liaisons-Dangereuses-or-Virtuous-Circle.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strambo, Claudia, Måns Nilsson, and André Månsson. &amp;ldquo;Coherent or inconsistent? Assessing energy security and climate policy interaction within the European Union.&amp;rdquo; Energy Research &amp;amp; Social Science 8 (2015): 1-12. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S221462961500047X&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S221462961500047X&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CEER Benchmarking Report 6.1 on the Continuity of Electricity and Gas Supply. Data update 2015/2016. Ref: C18-EQS-86-03. 26-July-2018. Council of European Energy Regulators. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceer.eu/documents/104400/-/-/963153e6-2f42-78eb-22a4-06f1552dd34c&#34;&gt;https://www.ceer.eu/documents/104400/-/-/963153e6-2f42-78eb-22a4-06f1552dd34c&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average frequency and duration of electric distribution outages vary by states. U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA). April 5, 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/detail.php?id=35652&#34;&gt;https://www.eia.gov/todayinenergy/detail.php?id=35652&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Röpke, Luise. &amp;ldquo;The development of renewable energies and supply security: a trade-off analysis.&amp;rdquo; Energy policy 61 (2013): 1011-1021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/73854/1/IfoWorkingPaper-151.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/73854/1/IfoWorkingPaper-151.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Evolutions in energy conservation policies in the time of renewables&amp;rdquo;, Nicola Lablanca, Isabella Maschio, Paolo Bertoldi, ECEEE 2015 Summer Study &amp;ndash; First Fuel Now. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eceee.org/library/conference_proceedings/eceee_Summer_Studies/2015/9-dynamics-of-consumption/evolutions-in-energy-conservation-policies-in-the-time-of-renewables/&#34;&gt;https://www.eceee.org/library/conference_proceedings/eceee_Summer_Studies/2015/9-dynamics-of-consumption/evolutions-in-energy-conservation-policies-in-the-time-of-renewables/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How not to run a modern society on solar and wind power alone”, Kris De Decker, Low-tech Magazine, September 2017. &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nedic, Dusko, et al. Security assessment of future UK electricity scenarios. Tyndall Centre for Climate Change Research, 2005. &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.461.4834&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.461.4834&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhou, P., R. Y. Jin, and L. W. Fan. &amp;ldquo;Reliability and economic evaluation of power system with renewables: A review.&amp;rdquo; Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 58 (2016): 537-547. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136403211501727X&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S136403211501727X&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smil, Vaclav. Power density: a key to understanding energy sources and uses. MIT Press, 2015. &lt;a href=&#34;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/power-density&#34;&gt;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/power-density&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landeira, Cristina Cabo, Ángeles López-Agüera, and Fernando Núñez Sánchez. &amp;ldquo;Loss of Load Probability method applicability limits as function of consumption types and climate conditions in stand-alone PV systems.&amp;rdquo; (2018). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Cristina_Cabo2/publication/324080184_Loss_of_Load_Probability_method_applicability_limits_as_function_of_consumption_types_and_climate_conditions_in_stand-alone_PV_systems/links/5abca9fa45851584fa6e1efd/Loss-of-Load-Probability-method-applicability-limits-as-function-of-consumption-types-and-climate-conditions-in-stand-alone-PV-systems.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Cristina_Cabo2/publication/324080184_Loss_of_Load_Probability_method_applicability_limits_as_function_of_consumption_types_and_climate_conditions_in_stand-alone_PV_systems/links/5abca9fa45851584fa6e1efd/Loss-of-Load-Probability-method-applicability-limits-as-function-of-consumption-types-and-climate-conditions-in-stand-alone-PV-systems.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singh, S. Sanajaoba, and Eugene Fernandez. &amp;ldquo;Method for evaluating battery size based on loss of load probability concept for a remote PV system.&amp;rdquo; Power India International Conference (PIICON), 2014 6th IEEE. IEEE, 2014. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7117729&#34;&gt;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7117729&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How sustainanle is stored sunlight? Kris De Decker, Low-tech Magazine. &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2015/05/how-sustainable-is-stored-sunlight/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapman, R. N. &amp;ldquo;Sizing Handbook for Stand-Alone Photovoltaic.&amp;rdquo; Storage Systems, Sandia Report, SAND87-1087, Albuquerque (1987). &lt;a href=&#34;https://prod.sandia.gov/techlib-noauth/access-control.cgi/1987/871087.pdf&#34;&gt;https://prod.sandia.gov/techlib-noauth/access-control.cgi/1987/871087.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posadillo, R., and R. López Luque. &amp;ldquo;A sizing method for stand-alone PV installations with variable demand.&amp;rdquo; Renewable Energy33.5 (2008): 1049-1055. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S096014810700184X&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S096014810700184X&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khatib, Tamer, Ibrahim A. Ibrahim, and Azah Mohamed. &amp;ldquo;A review on sizing methodologies of photovoltaic array and storage battery in a standalone photovoltaic system.&amp;rdquo; Energy Conversion and Management 120 (2016): 430-448. &lt;a href=&#34;https://staff.najah.edu/media/published_research/2017/01/19/A_review_on_sizing_methodologies_of_photovoltaic_array_and_storage_battery_in_a_standalone_photovoltaic_system.pdf&#34;&gt;https://staff.najah.edu/media/published_research/2017/01/19/A_review_on_sizing_methodologies_of_photovoltaic_array_and_storage_battery_in_a_standalone_photovoltaic_system.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vannini, Phillip, and Jonathan Taggart. Off the grid: re-assembling domestic life. Routledge, 2014. &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifeoffgrid.ca/off-grid-living-the-book/&#34;&gt;http://lifeoffgrid.ca/off-grid-living-the-book/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Materialising energy and water resources in everyday practices: insights for securing supply systems&amp;rdquo;, Yolande Strengers, Cecily Maller, in &amp;ldquo;Global Environmental Change 22 (2012), pp. 754-763. &lt;a href=&#34;http://researchbank.rmit.edu.au/view/rmit%3A17990/n2006038376.pdf&#34;&gt;http://researchbank.rmit.edu.au/view/rmit%3A17990/n2006038376.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pillai, N. &amp;ldquo;Loss of Load Probability of a Power System.&amp;rdquo; (2008). &lt;a href=&#34;https://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/6953/1/MPRA_paper_6953.pdf&#34;&gt;https://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/6953/1/MPRA_paper_6953.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al-Rubaye, Mohannad Jabbar Mnati, and Alex Van den Bossche. &amp;ldquo;Decades without a real grid: a living experience in Iraq.&amp;rdquo; International Conference on Sustainable Energy and Environment Sensing (SEES 2018). 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;https://biblio.ugent.be/publication/8566224&#34;&gt;https://biblio.ugent.be/publication/8566224&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telson, Michael L. &amp;ldquo;The economics of alternative levels of reliability for electric power generation systems.&amp;rdquo; The Bell Journal of Economics (1975): 679-694. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3003250?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&#34;&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/3003250?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schröder, Thomas, and Wilhelm Kuckshinrichs. &amp;ldquo;Value of lost load: an efficient economic indicator for power supply security? A literature review.&amp;rdquo; Frontiers in energy research 3 (2015): 55. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fenrg.2015.00055/full&#34;&gt;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fenrg.2015.00055/full&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ratha, Anubhav, Emil Iggland, and Goran Andersson. &amp;ldquo;Value of Lost Load: How much is supply security worth?.&amp;rdquo; Power and Energy Society General Meeting (PES), 2013 IEEE. IEEE, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ethz.ch/content/dam/ethz/special-interest/itet/institute-eeh/power-systems-dam/documents/SAMA/2012/Ratha-SA-2012.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.ethz.ch/content/dam/ethz/special-interest/itet/institute-eeh/power-systems-dam/documents/SAMA/2012/Ratha-SA-2012.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;De Nooij, Michiel, Carl Koopmans, and Carlijn Bijvoet. &amp;ldquo;The value of supply security: The costs of power interruptions: Economic input for damage reduction and investment in networks.&amp;rdquo; Energy Economics 29.2 (2007): 277-295. &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/40102922/The_Value_of_Supply_Security_The_Costs_o20151117-24458-1eo081r.pdf?AWSAccessKeyId=AKIAIWOWYYGZ2Y53UL3A&amp;amp;Expires=1544213977&amp;amp;Signature=d01qoyIcopj1rE5HpSWkCGcQzRk%3D&amp;amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B%20filename%3DThe_value_of_supply_security.pdf&#34;&gt;https://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/40102922/The_Value_of_Supply_Security_The_Costs_o20151117-24458-1eo081r.pdf?AWSAccessKeyId=AKIAIWOWYYGZ2Y53UL3A&amp;amp;Expires=1544213977&amp;amp;Signature=d01qoyIcopj1rE5HpSWkCGcQzRk%3D&amp;amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B%20filename%3DThe_value_of_supply_security.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coutard, Olivier, and Elizabeth Shove. &amp;ldquo;Infrastructures, practices and the dynamics of demand.&amp;rdquo; Infrastructures in Practice. Routledge, 2018. 10-22. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.routledge.com/Infrastructures-in-Practice-The-Dynamics-of-Demand-in-Networked-Societies/Shove-Trentmann/p/book/9781138476165&#34;&gt;https://www.routledge.com/Infrastructures-in-Practice-The-Dynamics-of-Demand-in-Networked-Societies/Shove-Trentmann/p/book/9781138476165&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demand Dictionary of Phrase and Fable, seventeenth edition. Jenny Rinkinen, Elizabeth Shove, Greg Marsden, The Demand Centre, 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/Demand-Dictionary.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.demand.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/Demand-Dictionary.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History and Future of the Compressed Air Economy</title>
      <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hiscox-straight-line-air-compressor_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="41611" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hiscox-straight-line-air-compressor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Hiscox straight line air compressor&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Hiscox straight line air compressor 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compressed air energy storage (CAES) is considered to be an important component of a renewable power grid, because it could store surplus power from wind turbines and solar panels on a large scale. However, in its present form, the technology suffers from large energy losses and depends on natural gas to operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A look at the 4,000 year long history of compressed air makes clear that this is not unavoidable. Although our ancestors were dependent on less energy efficient technology, they used compressed air in more intelligent configurations that had fewer energy conversion losses and were independent of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These historical systems hold the key to the design of a low-tech, low-cost, robust, sustainable and relatively energy efficient energy storage medium. The compressed air economy could be the practical and realistic alternative to the hydrogen or all-electric utopias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-promise-of-compressed-air&#34;&gt;The Promise of Compressed Air&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the potential of wind and solar energy is more than sufficient to supply the electricity demand of industrial societies, &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/&#34;&gt;these resources are only available intermittently&lt;/a&gt; – is one way to deal with the variability and uncertainty of renewable power, but it has its limits. Therefore, a renewable power grid needs at least some energy storage, and the same goes for an off-the-grid system based on solar or wind power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, more than 99% of worldwide electrical storage capacity consists of pumped hydropower energy storage plants, where surplus electrical energy from solar or wind power plants is stored for later use by pumping water from a lower to a higher reservoir. Pumped hydropower energy storage is pretty efficient and low-tech, but it requires a suitable geography for two large water bodies, separated vertically, and one or two dams. It also floods large areas of land. Most suitable sites are already in use, which means that there is little potential for further growth. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hiscox-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why many people are seeing a promising alternative in Compressed Air Energy Storage (CAES), another form of mechanical energy storage. In these systems, electricity is used to compress air, which is stored in an underground cavern. To make use of the stored energy, the air is decompressed and converted back to electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although CAES also requires favourable geography to provide the underground air storage caverns, it is believed that there are many more suitable sites worldwide than for pumped hydropower energy storage. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the energy stored over the lifetime of a storage device is compared to the amount of primary energy required to build the device, CAES is vastly superior to electrochemical batteries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, CAES is the most sustainable energy storage around. Unlike pumped hydropower energy storage, compressed air energy storage presents no environmental issues caused by the flooding of land and the damming of rivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, if the energy stored over the lifetime of a storage device is compared to the amount of primary energy required to build the device, CAES surpasses pumped hydropower energy storage and is vastly superior to electrochemical batteries, which require 10 to 100 times more embodied energy for a given storage capacity. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a crucial advantage, because high energy use for the production of the energy storage can &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;greatly decrease the sustainability of a renewable power grid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem-with-compressed-air&#34;&gt;The Problem with Compressed Air&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of these advantages, there are currently only two large-scale CAES plants in operation worldwide: one in Germany, built in 1979, and one in the USA, built in 1991. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This limited uptake is mainly attributed to the fact that more than half of the energy is lost when charging and discharging a compressed air “battery”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While pumped hydropower storage has a charge/discharge efficiency of 70-85%, and chemical batteries reach 65-90%, the CAES plants in operation in Germany and the US have an electric-to-electric efficiency of only 40-42% and 51-54%, respectively. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low energy conversion efficiency is mainly due to the fact that air increases in temperature when being compressed to high pressures (both CAES plants operate at 50-70 bar, which is 10 to 20 times the air pressure in a bicycle tyre). Because the energy density of air decreases with rising temperature, both CAES plants remove the heat prior to storage and dump it into the atmosphere. This implies a significant source of energy loss. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/vintage-three-stage-compressor_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Vintage three-stage compressor&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Vintage three-stage compressor 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, when air is decompressed from a high pressure, the temperature decreases to such an extent that the water vapour in the air can freeze, thereby damaging the valves and the expander of the storage system. To prevent this, and to increase power output, both CAES plants heat the air in combusters using natural gas fuel prior to expansion. Obviously, this further decreases the energy efficiency of the overall process, rendering the present CAES systems entirely dependent on fossil fuels for their operation. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conversion efficiency of 40-50% means that &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;wind or solar power generation capacity must be doubled to make up for that loss&lt;/a&gt;. Consequently, we need more energy, more materials, and more space for the same energy output. The environmental friendliness of CAES is thus at least partly negated by its low efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, CAES&amp;rsquo;s low energy conversion efficiency is inherently linked to its low energy density, which means it relies on very large storage reservoirs. In principle, the energy density of compressed air can be greatly improved by using higher air pressures, but as the air pressure increases, more energy is turned into waste heat and the efficiency of the whole process further deteriorates. Consequently, a CAES system – in its current configuration – is always a compromise between efficiency and energy density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4000-years-of-history&#34;&gt;4,000 Years of History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very low energy efficiency of today’s compressed air energy storage systems is remarkable in a historical context. The use of compressed air dates back more than 4,000 years and has always been an important driver of technological progress. Although these historical applications were not aimed at energy storage, they offer inspiration to improve both the energy efficiency and energy density of today’s CAES systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earliest and arguably most important use of compressed air throughout history has been fueling the fire. This happened in the kitchen and in all heat-based production processes, but it was especially important in metal making processes. An unaided charcoal fire could reach 900°C, but a powerful forced air supply could raise its temperature to nearly 2000°C. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/bellows-blacksmith_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The earliest use of compressed air in history has been fueling the fire.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The earliest use of compressed air in history has been fueling the fire. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there were important regional differences, the history of metal smelting shows an evolution from metals with relatively low melting points, such as tin (230°C), to metals with higher melting points, first copper (1050°C) and then iron (1500°C).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This progress was in part driven by the improvements in air compressor technology, which evolved from air treading bags, wooden cylinders and pistons, and various forms of bellows, all human powered, to much larger and more powerful accordion bellows made of wood and bull hides, which were double-acting and operated by water power. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress in metal smelting was in large part driven by improvements in air compressor technology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in the 1860s and continuing into the 1900s, compressed air (or “pneumatics”) was at the centre of another technological revolution. This time, pneumatics established itself as the most versatile and widely used power transmission technology before the introduction of electricity. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because electric power was still distributed &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2016/03/power-water-networks/&#34;&gt;at low voltages&lt;/a&gt; (“hydraulics”) had better transmission efficiencies over longer distances. However, compressed air has a very practical advantage over water under pressure: air is available anywhere and its exhaust poses no problems, while hydraulic systems require a sufficient water supply as well as a means to drain the fluid after use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/pneumatic-rock-drill_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a power transmission technology, compressed air was first applied in tunneling and mining. It provided an answer to the pressing need for a mechanical rock drill in the building of canals and railways, where tunnel construction formed a major bottleneck. Under severe hard-rock conditions, tunnel advance with hand drilling – using a pickaxe and explosives – was measured in inches per day, and tunnels of as little as half a mile in length could take years to complete. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new configuration, steam engines above-ground produced compressed air that was piped into the shafts or tunnels. The breakthrough of compressed air power transmission and pneumatic drilling tools happened with the digging of the 13.7 km long Mont Cenis tunnel in the Alps, which was completed in just 14 years (1857-1871). The technology quickly spread to the mining industry, especially in the US, where compressed air not only powered rock drills but also other machinery, such as hauling, pumping and stamping machines. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-paris-compressed-air-network&#34;&gt;The Paris Compressed Air Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its effectiveness demonstrated so dramatically in power drilling, compressed air was adapted to a widening range of industrial operations: hammering, riveting, painting and spraying, pressure handling of fluids in processing, and a host of other uses. In the US, pneumatics came to be widely introduced as an auxiliary power system in manufacturing from the 1880s. The Census of 1900 referred to the widespread introduction of small pneumatic tools as possibly “the most important single tool development of the decade”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time in Europe, the French took pneumatic power transmission one step further by setting up a city-wide power distribution network in Paris. It would remain in use for more than 100 years (from 1881 to 1994), distributing compressed air at a relatively low pressure of 5-6 bar over a network of (eventually) more than 900 km of mains, serving more than 10,000 customers. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/distribution-room-pneumatic-clock-network_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Distribution room for the pneumatic clock network in Paris.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Distribution room for the pneumatic clock network in Paris. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Paris compressed air network started as a system designed exclusively for regulating clocks by impulses of compressed air sent through subterranean pipes. By 1889, the network in Paris was regulating 8,000 clocks through 65 km of mains. The clock regulating service was retired in 1927, after it became clear that electricity was better suited for the job. However, by that time, the compressed air network in Paris had proved highly successful in small industrial and service establishments. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French set up a city-wide power distribution network in Paris, which served more than 10,000 customers and remained in use for 100 years&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already in 1892, F.E. Idell wrote that “among the smaller industrial purposes for which the air motors are used in Paris, I find the driving of lathes for metal and wood, of circular saws, drills, polishing machines, and many others. They are also used in the workshops of carpenters, joiners and cabinet-makers, of smiths, of umbrella makers, of collar-makers, of bookbinders, and naturally in a great many places where sewing machines are used, both by dressmakers, tailors, and shoemakers, from the smallest to the largest scale.” &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/power-station-compressed-air-network-paris_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Power station of the compressed air network in Paris. Source: Tom Bates, The Manufacturer and Builder, 1889. Image found online at the Museum of Retrotechnology&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Power station of the compressed air network in Paris. Source: Tom Bates, The Manufacturer and Builder, 1889.
Image found online at the [Museum of Retrotechnology](http://www.douglas-self.com/MUSEUM/POWER/airnetwork/airnetwork.htm) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, the share of commercial and domestic use of compressed air decreased, as electricity became more important. However, industrial consumption of compressed air kept growing, and many large factories in Paris – from car producers to glass manufacturers – were connected to the unique power distribution network until the very end. Dentists became new users during the 1970s and 1980s. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref6:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-lesson-avoid-energy-conversions&#34;&gt;First Lesson: Avoid Energy Conversions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can be learned from comparing historical and current technologies based on compressed air? A first and crucial difference is the number of energy conversions involved. In historical systems, mechanical energy (for example, from a waterwheel or a steam engine) was directly converted to compressed air (using an air compressor), and then – most often – converted back to mechanical energy (for example, moving a pneumatic hammer). Consequently, there were only two sources of energy conversion loss: in the air compressor, and in the air expander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compressed air is still vital to the productivity of many industries and services around the globe, being used in thousands of applications – from food packaging and metal smelting to the manufacturing of microchips and plastics. However, compressed air is now produced by air compressors that run on electricity. This introduces two additional sources of energy loss: the electric generator (which converts mechanical energy from an energy source into electricity) and the electric motor (which converts electric energy back into mechanical energy to run the air compressor).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, today’s industrial use of compressed air is very wasteful: assuming each converter is 75% efficient, and assuming no other energy losses, only 30% of the energy input is converted into useful output. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/pneumatic-tubes-paris-sewer-network_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;In Paris, compressed air was piped through the sewer system.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 In Paris, compressed air was piped through the sewer system. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall system efficiency of the two existing CAES plants is even worse than that: not only is there the extra conversion step at the beginning of the chain (the energy loss in the windmill generator and in the electric motor running the compressor), but also at the end of the chain. This contrasts with industrial applications, where the end product is compressed air &amp;ndash; a CAES plant converts the compressed air back into electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the efficiency of a CAES plant is said to be 40-50%, this only refers to the losses in the air compressor and the air expander (electric-to-electric efficiency). However, if we include the conversions to and from electricity, the overall system efficiency decreases to less than 20%, again assuming that each converter has an efficiency of 75%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hiscox-pneumatic-hammer-stone-dressing_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Stone dressing using pneumatic hammers.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Stone dressing using pneumatic hammers. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine that a factory uses electricity from a CAES plant to power its industrial air compressors – a perfectly possible scenario. We then get the following energy conversion chain: mechanical energy is converted into electricity, electricity is converted into compressed air, compressed air is converted into electricity, electricity is converted into compressed air, and compressed air is converted in mechanical energy. That’s not two, or four, but six sources of energy conversion losses. Assuming each converter is 75% efficient, overall system efficiency now drops below 10%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we would connect a CAES plant directly to a factory that uses pneumatic tools, by piping compressed air from one to the other, there would be no need to convert compressed air into electricity and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if we would connect a CAES plant directly to a factory that uses pneumatic tools, by piping compressed air from one to the other, we would suffer just four sources of energy loss (generator, motor, compressor, expander). In the CAES plant, there is no longer a need to convert the stored compressed air back to electricity, while in the factory there is no need to compress the air a second time, using electricity. CAES and a factory could be up to 25 km apart &amp;ndash; the distance up to which compressed air can be distributed efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/paris-compressed-air-network-1962_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Map via Museum of Retrotechnology&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Map via [Museum of Retrotechnology](http://www.douglas-self.com/MUSEUM/POWER/airnetwork/airnetwork.htm) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious next step is to compress the air in a CAES plant using a direct mechanical link between the wind mill and the air compressor, thus skipping the conversion from direct mechanical energy to electricity and back. Such an approach – which has been demonstrated on a small scale, in slightly different configurations &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; – would make CAES entirely independent of electricity and would bring the energy conversion steps back to two, as in all historical systems. The only remaining energy conversion losses would be in the air compressor and in the air expander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rigid connection between windmill shaft and air compressor would also improve the efficiency of a CAES plant that is not connected to a factory but supplies electricity for general purposes, although the efficiency gain will be smaller. Obviously, compressing the air mechanically only works with windmills and not with solar PV panels, which do not produce mechanical energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-lesson-use-heat-and-cold-for-other-purposes&#34;&gt;Second Lesson: Use Heat and Cold for Other Purposes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second, related difference between present and historical uses of compressed air is how to deal with the temperature differences caused by compression and expansion of air. To improve efficiency, both CAES plants in operation use multiple air compressors. Multi-stage compression progressively increases the pressure and cools the air after each compression stage, using circulating water that is pumped to a cooling tower and released into the atmosphere. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, most CAES engineers are focused on further improving efficiency by using the waste heat of compression to reheat the compressed air upon expansion. This method is called “Advanced Adiabatic CAES” (AA-CAES) or “fuelless CAES” and removes the need to reheat with natural gas as in the standard “diabatic” CAES. The technology is expected to reach an overall efficiency of roughly 70%, bringing it closer to the efficiency of chemical batteries and pumped hydropower storage plants. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hiscox-detail-edited_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;In Paris, compressed air was usually heated by a coke fire before it was used by an air motor, increasing the power output in a way that is very similar to the use of natural gas in present-day CAES systems. Source: Hiscox, Gardner D. Compressed air, its production, uses, and applications; comprising the physical properties of air from a vacuum to its highest pressure, its thermodynamics, compression, transmission and uses as a motive power… New York: N. W. Henley (1909): 271.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 In Paris, compressed air was usually heated by a coke fire before it was used by an air motor, increasing the power output in a way that is very similar to the use of natural gas in present-day CAES systems. Source: Hiscox, Gardner D. Compressed air, its production, uses, and applications; comprising the physical properties of air from a vacuum to its highest pressure, its thermodynamics, compression, transmission and uses as a motive power… New York: N. W. Henley (1909): 271. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, AA-CAES remains an unproven technology so far: a number of plants have been proposed, but none have yet made it past the design stage. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The problem is twofold: first, the process enhancement increases the costs of a CAES plant by 20 to 40%; second, re-using the waste heat of the compression process is technologically challenging. To transfer heat at a high rate with a minimal temperature difference requires a very large surface area of contact. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Paris compressed air power network, the cooling provided by the expansion of air was used for refrigeration, freezing, cooling and ventilation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at older pneumatic systems, we see that there are other, easier ways to take advantage of temperature differences due to compression and expansion. In the Paris compressed air power network, engineers took advantage of the cooling that is provided by the expansion of air. In Paris, compressed air was usually heated by a coke fire before it was used by an air motor, increasing the power output in a way that is very similar to the use of natural gas in present-day CAES systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/air-reheater_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in bars and restaurants, these reheaters were not used. Instead, the cold air was used for refrigeration, freezing, cooling or ventilation purposes. In 1892, F.E. Idell described a Paris restaurant where “the exhaust was carried through a brick flue into the beer cellar. In this flue the carafes were set to freeze, and large moulds of block ice were also being made for table use, while the air was still cold enough in passing away through the beer cellar to render the use of ice for cooling quite unnecessary, even in the hottest weather.” &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of compressed air for cooling or freezing sometimes went together with the production of electricity for lighting, driving a dynamo. In these cases, the air motors were basically worked for their exhaust, with electric light being the by-product. Taking advantage of temperature differences also happened in the earlier mining applications, where the exhaust of the rock drills helped to cool (and ventilate) the mines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar and promising idea today, is compressed air energy storage combined with thermal storage to provide electricity, heating, cooling, refrigeration and/or ventilation at the same time. In fact, this approach also avoids several energy conversions, as it could replace refrigerators, freezers, air-conditioners and heating systems running on electricity. The method could work at the level of a city district or an industrial area &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/ditch-the-batteries-off-grid-compressed-air-energy-storage/&#34;&gt;especially interesting for decentralised energy storage using aboveground storage containers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hiscox-pressure-vessels_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, a higher air pressure can greatly reduce the size of a compressed air storage vessel, but only at the expense of increased waste heat. In individual buildings, space for storage vessels is limited, while there is a large demand for heat and cold, as well as electricity. Increasing the air pressure makes the storage vessel smaller and increases the production of heat and cold, meeting all energy needs of a household.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some proposed designs follow other approaches to deal with the heat of compression, and these could work for both large-scale and small-scale CAES systems. One interesting idea is a compressed air energy storage system that runs on wind energy as well as solar energy. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Wind energy is stored in the form of compressed air by compressor chain, as in the other CAES plants. However, solar energy from a &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2011/07/the-bright-future-of-solar-thermal-powered-factories/&#34;&gt;parabolic dish&lt;/a&gt; is stored in an insulated solar thermal tank and used to reheat the compressed air prior to expansion. Because the heat from the compression process is no longer needed to warm the air upon expansion, it is used to produce hot water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar concept for a hybrid thermal and compressed air energy storage design uses electric heating instead of solar thermal power. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:25&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Because the workload in these systems is shifted from pure conversion to investing partially in thermal storage, energy densities well in excess of traditional CAES can be achieved, and the size of the air storage can be reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;third-lesson-improve-the-air-compressorspanh2&#34;&gt;Third Lesson: Improve the Air Compressor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third way to improve the efficiency of compressed air energy storage is by using more energy efficient air compressors and expanders. This strategy is opposite to the one we explained before. Instead of taking advantage of heat and cold to make the system more efficient, it tries to minimize waste heat production during compression (and, consequently, to limit cooling during expansion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, it pays to look to the past for inspiration. Surprisingly, the holy grail of “isothermal” air compression – in which no waste heat is produced at all – was found at least 400 years ago. The hydraulic air compressor – or “trompe”, as it was originally known – was an Italian invention first mentioned by name in 1588, but possibly already known in Antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the 1600s onwards, dozens of “trompes” furnished a continuous air blast to early iron and brass-smelting furnaces in the French/Spanish Pyrenees. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:27&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Compared to a waterwheel running a wooden piston compressor, it was roughly three times more efficient, allowing higher iron production with less water power resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img  vertical&#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/italian-trompe-agricola_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The trompe compressed air without any moving parts, other than valve gates to shut off incoming water flow.
De Re Metallica, Georgius Agricola, 1556.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The trompe compressed air without any moving parts, other than valve gates to shut off incoming water flow.
De Re Metallica, Georgius Agricola, 1556. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trompe consisted of one or more vertical wooden tubes through which water was channeled by gravity. Upon its descent, the water absorbed air through holes in the tube and acted as a continuous piston in compressing the air. At the bottom of the tube, the air was separated from the water in a receptacle, after which it was sent to the furnace nozzle by adjustable pressure. Remarkably, the hydraulic air compressor produced compressed air without any moving parts, other than gate valves to shut off incoming water flow. This made it an extremely reliable device. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:26&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydraulic air compressor produced compressed air without any moving parts, which made it an extremely reliable and efficient device&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 19th century, the design of the hydraulic air compressor was further improved, making it more efficient and practical. In 1861, a hydraulic air compressor was built to power the rock drills for the construction of the Mont Cenis tunnel in the Alps, but the technology reached its heydays only at the end of the nineteenth century, this time in the mining industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over a 33-year period starting in 1896, eighteen gigantic hydraulic air compressors were built, mostly in the US, Canada, Germany and Sweden. In the largest of these installations, which were partly or completely built underground, water and air fell through pipes and shafts – hewn out of the rocks – which could be more than 100 metres deep and up to 4 metres wide. The delivery pressure amounted to 8 bar and the power output could reach 3,000 kilowatts. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/taylor-compressor-1_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Scientists gather to study the Taylor air compression system. Image: Canadian Journal of Fabrics,
septembre 1897.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Scientists gather to study the Taylor air compression system. Image: Canadian Journal of Fabrics,
septembre 1897. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first installations used a multitude of small downward air pipes, as in the original trompe, while later installations would use only two shafts. Leets and penstocks delivered water to air-water ‘mixing heads’ of various designs, and the compressed air was often subdivided to reach different mines and piped over distances of many kilometres. Most hydraulic air compressors operated for decades, the last one until 1981. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:30&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;30&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance tests, periodically carried out between the 1890s and 1950s, report that the hydropower-to-pneumatic power conversion efficiency ranged between 53% and 88%. More recent research has lowered these numbers to account for gas solubility effects, reporting efficiencies of 40 to 78%. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although hydraulic air compression produces little waste heat, a new type of energy loss is introduced: some of the air dissolves in the water and thus bypasses the air-water separation process, reducing the mass flow of air at outlet. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydraulic air compressor has seen renewed interest lately. A Canadian research team developed a 30-m tall hydraulic air compressor demonstrator rig in a former mine elevator shaft. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The “HAC Demonstrator Project” measures and verifies the energy savings potential of the technology primarily for deep mining applications. However, it could also be an alternative for multi-stage compressors used in industry and in CAES systems. This is because the new design can also be set up in closed-loop configuration, using a pump instead of a natural head of water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/history-and-future-of-the-compressed-air-economy/images/dithers/hac-drone_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: A newly developed hydraulic air compressor in Canada. Source: HAC Demonstrator Project (https://electrale.com).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: A newly developed hydraulic air compressor in Canada. Source: HAC Demonstrator Project (https://electrale.com). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the pump introduces extra energy use, a closed-loop configuration has two important advantages. First, it could be applied anywhere, rather than just in proximity to an exploitable water source and a large height difference. Second, it offers the opportunity to suppress the undesirable effects of solubility physics, for example through the addition of salt to the circulating water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the researchers, a closed-loop hydraulic air compressor could have an efficiency of 75%, taking into account the extra energy use from the pump. This is 13% more efficient than a three-stage centrifugal compressor, and cost advantages will be larger because of lower maintenance requirements. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref5:29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:31&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;31&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydraulic air compressor seems like a perfect match for large-scale CAES systems with underground reservoirs. In fact, many of the 19th and 20th century hydraulic air compressors used the lower air separator chamber also for compressed air energy storage, in what could be considered the first large-scale use of CAES. The storage – which could be as large as 5,600 m3 – was used to meet a short-time excess demand for air, meaning that the hydraulic air compressor did not have to be designed for the largest loads. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:28&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future-of-compressed-air&#34;&gt;The Future of Compressed Air&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these ideas will make CAES plants 100% energy efficient. However, they could help make them reach similar efficiencies to batteries, but with much lower environmental issues and much less energy invested. In the next article, we focus in more detail on &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2018/05/ditch-the-batteries-off-grid-compressed-air-energy-storage/&#34;&gt;small-scale CAES systems, which promise to be a sustainable alternative to chemical batteries in off-the-grid systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to George Fleming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chen, Haisheng, et al. &amp;ldquo;Compressed air energy storage.&amp;rdquo; Energy Storage-Technologies and Applications. InTech, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.intechopen.com/books/energy-storage-technologies-and-applications/compressed-air-energy-storage&#34;&gt;https://www.intechopen.com/books/energy-storage-technologies-and-applications/compressed-air-energy-storage&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luo, Xing, et al. &amp;ldquo;Overview of current development in electrical energy storage technologies and the application potential in power system operation.&amp;rdquo; Applied Energy 137 (2015): 511-536. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306261914010290&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306261914010290&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barnhart, Charles J., and Sally M. Benson. &amp;ldquo;On the importance of reducing the energetic and material demands of electrical energy storage.&amp;rdquo; Energy &amp;amp; Environmental Science 6.4 (2013): 1083-1092. &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcep.stanford.edu/pdfs/EES_reducingdemandsonenergystorage.pdf&#34;&gt;https://gcep.stanford.edu/pdfs/EES_reducingdemandsonenergystorage.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one of these CAES plants is (partially) used to store surplus wind energy. Both were designed as peaker plants based on economic motives.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kaiser, Friederike. &amp;ldquo;Steady State Analyse of existing Compressed Air Energy Storage Plants.&amp;rdquo; Power and Energy Student Summit (PESS). Dortmund, Germany (2015). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.efzn.de/uploads/tx_wiwimitarbeiter/S02.2.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.efzn.de/uploads/tx_wiwimitarbeiter/S02.2.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highest efficiencies are reached under optimal operation conditions. Additional efficiency loss is caused by the fact that during expansion the storage reservoir is being discharged and the pressure drops. Meanwhile, the input pressure for the expander is required to vary only in a minimal range to assure high efficiency during expansion. To bring together both requirements, air can be stored in a tank with surplus pressure and throttled down to the required expander input pressure – which is obviously linked to efficiency loss. [5]&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advanced Adiabatic Compressed Air Energy Storage (AA-CAES), Energy Storage Association. Retrieved May 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;http://energystorage.org/advanced-adiabatic-compressed-air-energy-storage-aa-caes&#34;&gt;http://energystorage.org/advanced-adiabatic-compressed-air-energy-storage-aa-caes&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sun, Hao, Xing Luo, and Jihong Wang. &amp;ldquo;Feasibility study of a hybrid wind turbine system–Integration with compressed air energy storage.&amp;rdquo; Applied Energy 137 (2015): 617-628. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306261914006680&#34;&gt;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306261914006680&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, today’s CAES plants are essentially conventional gas turbines in which the compression of the combustion air is separated from the actual gas turbine process. Unlike conventional gas turbines, which consume about two-thirds of their input fuel to compress the air at the time of power generation, CAES precompresses the air using low cost electricity from the power grid at off-peak times, and utilizes it with some gas fuel to generate electricity when required.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smil, Vaclav. &amp;ldquo;Energy in world history.&amp;rdquo; (1994).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ewbank, Thomas. A Descriptive and Historical Account of Hydraulic and Other Machines for Raising Water, Ancient and Modern: Including the Progressive Development of the Steam Engine. No. 32707. Tilt and Bogue, 1842.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nye, David E. &amp;ldquo;Hunter Louis C. and Bryant Lynwood. A History of Industrial Power in the United States, 1780–1930. Volume 3: The Transmission of Power. Cambridge, Mass, and London: MIT Press, 1991. Pp. xxv+ 596 ISBN 0-262-08198-9.&amp;rdquo; The British Journal for the History of Science 25.4 (1992): 476-477.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Compressed air: experiments upon the transmission of power by compressed air in Paris (Popp&amp;rsquo;s system)&amp;rdquo;, F.E. Idell, 1892&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The transmission and distribution of power from central stations by compressed air&amp;rdquo;. William Cawthorne Unwin, B. 1891.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Compressed air, its production, uses, and applications; comprising the physical properties of air from a vacuum to its highest pressure, its thermodynamics, compression, transmission and uses as a motive power&amp;rdquo;, Gardner D. Hiscox, 1909&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;La SUDAC, un siècle d&amp;rsquo;air comprimé au bord de la Seine&amp;rdquo;, Denis Cosnard, Des usines à Paris, 2011.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Histoire de la SUDAC (1877-1996)&amp;rdquo; (PDF), Tristan de la Broise &amp;amp; Florence Meffre, 1996&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The transmission of power by compressed air&amp;rdquo;, Robert Zahner, 1890&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy conversions are not necessarily a bad thing. Mechanical power transmission involves no energy conversions, but it has very high energy losses when transported over longer distances and when subdivided to a large number of machines. This is why so-called “fluid powers” – pneumatics, hydraulics and electricity – came onto the scene in the 19th century. Although their conversion to another form of energy involves energy loss, this loss is compensated for by their much higher efficiency in transmission and subdivision. However, combining two fluid powers – such as compressed air and electricity – is wasteful by definition.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ibrahim, Hussein, et al. &amp;ldquo;Study and design of a hybrid wind–diesel-compressed air energy storage system for remote areas.&amp;rdquo; Applied Energy 87.5 (2010): 1749-1762. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.academia.edu/download/42460658/Study_and_design_of_a_hybrid_winddiesel-20160209-23813-kip9us.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.academia.edu/download/42460658/Study_and_design_of_a_hybrid_winddiesel-20160209-23813-kip9us.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheng, Jie. Configuration and optimization of a novel compressed-air-assisted wind energy conversion system. The University of Nebraska-Lincoln, 2016. &lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=https://www.google.es/&amp;amp;httpsredir=1&amp;amp;article=1081&amp;amp;context=elecengtheses&#34;&gt;https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=https://www.google.es/&amp;amp;httpsredir=1&amp;amp;article=1081&amp;amp;context=elecengtheses&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zakeri, Behnam, and Sanna Syri. &amp;ldquo;Electrical energy storage systems: A comparative life cycle cost analysis.&amp;rdquo; Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 42 (2015): 569-596. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Behnam_Zakeri/publication/281277805_Electrical_energy_storage_systems_A_comparative_life_cycle_cost_analysis_2015/links/55deac0008ae79830bb58ede.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Behnam_Zakeri/publication/281277805_Electrical_energy_storage_systems_A_comparative_life_cycle_cost_analysis_2015/links/55deac0008ae79830bb58ede.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bagdanavicius, Audrius, and Nick Jenkins. &amp;ldquo;Exergy and exergoeconomic analysis of a Compressed Air Energy Storage combined with a district energy system.&amp;rdquo; Energy Conversion and Management 77 (2014): 432-440. &lt;a href=&#34;https://lra.le.ac.uk/bitstream/2381/37140/2/ECM_CAESpaper_final.pdf&#34;&gt;https://lra.le.ac.uk/bitstream/2381/37140/2/ECM_CAESpaper_final.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ji, Wei, et al. &amp;ldquo;Thermodynamic analysis of a novel hybrid wind-solar-compressed air energy storage system.&amp;rdquo; Energy Conversion and Management 142 (2017): 176-187.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:25&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Houssainy, Sammy, et al. &amp;ldquo;Thermodynamic analysis of a high temperature hybrid compressed air energy storage (HTH-CAES) system.&amp;rdquo; Renewable Energy 115 (2018): 1043-1054.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:25&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:26&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torrence, Euart Carl. &amp;ldquo;Hydraulic air compressors.&amp;rdquo; (1898). &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholarsmine.mst.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1385&amp;amp;context=bachelors_theses&#34;&gt;http://scholarsmine.mst.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1385&amp;amp;context=bachelors_theses&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:26&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:27&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomàs, Estanislau. &amp;ldquo;The Catalan process for the direct production of malleable iron and its spread to Europe and the Americas.&amp;rdquo; Contributions to science (2000): 225-232. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raco.cat/index.php/Contributions/article/viewFile/157654/209545&#34;&gt;https://www.raco.cat/index.php/Contributions/article/viewFile/157654/209545&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:27&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:28&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schulze, Leroy E. Hydraulic air compressors. Vol. 7683. Dept. of the Interior, Bureau of Mines, 1954. &lt;a href=&#34;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015078460238;view=1up;seq=11&#34;&gt;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015078460238;view=1up;seq=11&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:28&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:29&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hydraulic Air Compressor (HAC) Demonstrator Project, Dean Millar, 2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://aceee.org/files/proceedings/2017/data/polopoly_fs/1.3687890.1501159068!/fileserver/file/790271/filename/0036_0053_000034.pdf&#34;&gt;https://aceee.org/files/proceedings/2017/data/polopoly_fs/1.3687890.1501159068!/fileserver/file/790271/filename/0036_0053_000034.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5:29&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:30&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hartenberg, R. S., and J. Denavit. &amp;ldquo;The fabulous air compressor.&amp;rdquo; Mach. Des 21 (1960): 168-170.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:30&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:31&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millar, Dean L. &amp;ldquo;A review of the case for modern-day adoption of hydraulic air compressors.&amp;rdquo; Applied Thermal Engineering 69.1-2 (2014): 55-77.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:31&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Run the Economy on the Weather</title>
      <link>https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/stoneferry-detail_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="38294" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/stoneferry-detail_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Stoneferry (detail), a painting by John Ward of Hull.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Stoneferry (detail), a painting by John Ward of Hull. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the Industrial Revolution, people adjusted their energy demand to a variable energy supply. Our global trade and transport system — which relied on sail boats — operated only when the wind blew, as did the mills that supplied our food and powered many manufacturing processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same approach could be very useful today, especially when improved by modern technology. In particular, factories and cargo transportation — such as ships and even trains — could be operated only when renewable energy is available. Adjusting energy demand to supply would make switching to renewable energy much more realistic than it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;renewable-energy-in-pre-industrial-times&#34;&gt;Renewable Energy in Pre-Industrial Times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the Industrial Revolution, both industry and transportation were largely dependent on intermittent renewable energy sources. Water mills, windmills and sailing boats have been in use since Antiquity, but the Europeans brought these technologies to full development from the 1400s onwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At their peak, right before the Industrial Revolution took off, there were an estimated &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2009/10/wind-powered-factories-history-and-future-of-industrial-windmills/&#34;&gt;200,000 wind powered mills and 500,000 water powered mills&lt;/a&gt; in Europe. Initially, water mills and windmills were mainly used for grinding grain, a laborious task that had been done by hand for many centuries, first with the aid of stones and later with a rotary hand mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/summer-landscape_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: &amp;amp;quot;Een zomers landschap&amp;amp;quot; (&amp;amp;quot;A summer landscape&amp;amp;quot;), a painting by Jan van Os.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: \&#34;Een zomers landschap\&#34; (\&#34;A summer landscape\&#34;), a painting by Jan van Os. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, soon water and wind powered mills were adapted to industrial processes like sawing wood, polishing glass, making paper, boring pipes, cutting marble, slitting metal, sharpening knives, crushing chalk, grinding mortar, making gunpowder, minting coins, and so on. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Wind- and water mills also processed a host of agricultural products. They were pressing olives, hulling barley and rice, grinding spices and tobacco, and crushing linseed, rapeseed and hempseed for cooking and lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it relied on intermittent wind sources, international trade was crucial to many European economies before the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So-called &amp;lsquo;industrial water mills&amp;rsquo; had been used in Antiquity and were widely adopted in Europe by the fifteenth century, but &amp;lsquo;industrial windmills&amp;rsquo; appeared only in the 1600s in the Netherlands, a country that took wind power to the extreme. The Dutch even applied wind power to reclaim land from the sea, and the whole country was kept dry by intermittently operating wind mills until 1850. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/river-landscape_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Abraham Storck - A river landscape with fishermen in rowing boats, 1679.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Abraham Storck - A river landscape with fishermen in rowing boats, 1679. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of wind power for transportation – in the form of the sailboat – also boomed from the 1500s onwards, when Europeans &amp;lsquo;discovered&amp;rsquo; new lands. Wind powered transportation supported a robust, diverse and ever expanding international trading system in both bulk goods (such as grain, wine, wood, metals, ceramics, and preserved fish), luxury items (such as precious metals, furs, spices, ivory, silks, and medicin) and human slaves. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it relied on intermittent wind sources, international trade was crucial to many European economies. For example, the Dutch shipbuilding industry, which was centred around some 450 wind-powered saw mills, imported virtually all its naval stores from the Baltic: wood, tar, iron, hemp and flax. Even the food supply could depend on wind-powered transportation. Towards the end of the 1500s, the Dutch imported two thousand shiploads of grain per year from Gdansk. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Sailboats were also important for fishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dealing-with-intermittency-in-pre-industrial-times&#34;&gt;Dealing with Intermittency in Pre-Industrial Times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although variable renewable energy sources were critical to European society for some 500 years before fossil fuels took over, there were no chemical batteries, no electric transmission lines, and no balancing capacity of fossil fuel power plants to deal with the variable energy output of wind and water power. So, how did our ancestors &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;deal with the large variability of renewable power sources&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some extent, they were counting on technological solutions to match energy supply to energy demand, just as we do today. The water level in a river depends on the weather and the seasons. &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2010/11/boat-mills-water-powered-floating-factories/&#34;&gt;Boat mills and bridge mills&lt;/a&gt; were among the earliest technological fixes to this problem. They went up and down with the water level, which allowed them to maintain a more predictable operating regime. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some extent, our ancestors were counting on technological solutions to match energy supply to energy demand, just as we do today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, water power could also be stored for later use. Starting in the middle ages, dams were built to create mill ponds, a form of energy storage that&amp;rsquo;s similar to today&amp;rsquo;s hydropower reservoirs. The storage reservoirs evened out the flow of streams and insured that water was available when it was needed. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/horse-mill_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Horse Mill, a painting by James Herring. Ca. 1850.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Horse Mill, a painting by James Herring. Ca. 1850. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But rivers could still dry out or freeze over for prolonged periods, rendering dams and adjustable water wheels useless. Furthermore, when one counted on windmills, no such technological fixes were available. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A technological solution to the intermittency of both water and wind power was the &amp;lsquo;beast mill&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;horse mill&amp;rsquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In contrast to wind and water power, horses, donkeys or oxen could be counted on to supply power whenever it was required. However, beast mills were expensive and energy inefficient to operate: feeding a horse required a land area capable of feeding eight humans. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Consequently, the use of animal power in large-scale manufacturing processes was rare. Beast mills were mostly used for the milling of grain or as a power source in small workshop settings, using draft animals. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, beast mills were not a viable backup power source for sailing ships either. In principle, sailing boats could revert to human power when wind was not available. However, a sufficiently large rowing crew needed extra water and food, which would have limited the range of the ship, or its cargo capacity. Therefore, rowing was mainly restricted to battleships and smaller boats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;adjusting-demand-to-supply-factories&#34;&gt;Adjusting Demand to Supply: Factories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of their limited technological options for dealing with the variability of renewable energy sources, our ancestors mainly resorted to a strategy that we have largely forgotten about: they adapted their energy demand to the variable energy supply. In other words, they accepted that renewable energy was not always available and acted accordingly. For example, windmills and sailboats were simply not operated when there was no wind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/windmills-monet_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Painting: Mills in the Westzijderveld near Zaandam, a painting by Claude Monet.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Painting: [Mills in the Westzijderveld near Zaandam](https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Claude_Monet_Mills_in_the_Westzijderveld_near_Zaandam.jpg), a painting by Claude Monet. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In industrial windmills, work was done whenever the wind blew, even if that meant that the miller had to work night and day, taking only short naps. For example, a document reveals that at the Union Mill in Cranbrook, England, the miller once had only three hours sleep during a windy period lasting 60 hours. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A 1957 book about windmills, partly based on interviews with the last surviving millers, reveals the urgency of using wind when it was available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Often enough when the wind blew in autumn, the miller would work from Sunday midnight to Tuesday evening, Wednesday morning to Thursday night, and Friday morning to Saturday midnight, taking only a few snatches of sleep; and a good windmiller always woke up in bed when the wind rose, getting up in the middle of the night to set the mill going, because the wind was his taskmaster and must be taken advantage of whenever it blew. Many a village has at times gone short of wheaten bread because the local mill was becalmed in a waterless district before the invention of the steam engine; and barley-meal bread or even potato bread had to suffice in the crisis of a windless autumn.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In earlier, more conservative times, the miller was punished for working on Sunday, but he didn&amp;rsquo;t always care. When a protest against Sunday work was made to Mr. Wade of Wicklewood towermill, Norfolk, he retorted: &amp;ldquo;If the Lord is good enough to send me wind on a Sunday, I&amp;rsquo;m going to use it&amp;rdquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; On the other hand, when there was no wind, millers did other work, like maintaining their machinery, or took time off. Noah Edwards, the last miller of Arkley tower mill, Hertfordshire, would “sit on the fan stage of a fine evening and play his fiddle”. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;adjusting-demand-to-supply-sailboats&#34;&gt;Adjusting Demand to Supply: Sailboats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar approach existed for overseas travel, using sail boats. When there was no wind, sailors stayed ashore, maintained and repaired their ships, or did other things. They planned their trips according to the seasons, making use of favourable seasonal winds and currents. Winds at sea are not only much stronger than those over land, but also more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sailors planned their trips according to the seasons, making use of favourable seasonal winds and currents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lower atmosphere of the planet is encircled by six major wind belts, three in each hemisphere. From Equator to poles these &amp;lsquo;prevailing winds&amp;rsquo; are the trade winds, the westerlies, and the easterlies. The six wind belts move north in the northern summer and south in the northern winter. Five major sea current gyres are correlated with the dominant wind flows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/maas-at-dordrecht_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The Maas at Dordrecht, a painting by Aelbert Cuyp, 1660.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The Maas at Dordrecht, a painting by Aelbert Cuyp, 1660. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually, European sailors deciphered the global pattern of winds and currents and took full advantage of them to establish new sea routes all over the world. By the 1500s, Christopher Columbus had figured out that the combination of trade winds and westerlies enabled a round-trip route for sailing ships crossing the Atlantic Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trade winds reach their northernmost latitude at or after the end of the northern summer, bringing them in reach of Spain and Portugal. These summer trade winds made it easy to sail from Southern Europe to the Caribbean and South America, because the wind was blowing in that direction along the route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/wind-map-of-the-atlantic_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Wind map of the Atlantic, September 9, 2017. Source: Windy&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Wind map of the Atlantic, September 9, 2017. Source: [Windy](https://www.windy.com) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the same route back would be nearly impossible. However, Iberian sailors first sailed north to catch the westerlies, which reach their southernmost location at or after the end of winter and carried the sailors straight back to Southern Europe. In the 1560s, Basque explorer Andrés de Urdaneta discovered a similar round-trip route in the Pacific Ocean. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of favourable winds made travel times of sailboats relatively reliable. The fastest Atlantic crossing was 21 days, the slowest 29 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of favourable winds made the travel times of sailboats relatively predictable. &lt;em&gt;Ocean Passages for the World&lt;/em&gt; mentions that typical passage times from New York to the English Channel for a mid-19th to early 20th century sailing vessel was 25 to 30 days. From 1818 to 1832, the fastest crossing was 21 days, the slowest 29 days. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey from the English Channel to New York took 35-40 days in winter and 40-50 days in summer. To Cape Town, Melbourne, and Calcutta took 50-60 days, 80-90 days, and 100-120 days, respectively. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These travel times are double to triple those of today&amp;rsquo;s container ships, which &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2009/04/cargo-ships-then-and-now/&#34;&gt;vary their speed based on oil prices and economic demand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-approach-new-technology&#34;&gt;Old Approach, New Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a strategy to deal with variable energy sources, adjusting energy demand to renewable energy supply is just as valuable a solution today as it was in pre-industrial times. However, this does not mean that we need to go back to pre-industrial means. We have better technology available, which makes it much easier to synchronise the economic demands with the vagaries of the weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/shipping-in-a-calm_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Shipping in a calm, a painting by Charles Brooking, first half 18th century.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Shipping in a calm, a painting by Charles Brooking, first half 18th century. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following paragraphs, I investigate in more detail how industry and transportation could be operated on variable energy sources alone, and demonstrate how new technologies open new possibilities. I then conclude by analysing the effects on consumers, workers, and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;industrial-manufacturing&#34;&gt;Industrial Manufacturing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a global scale, industrial manufacturing accounts for nearly half of all energy end use. Many mechanical processes that were run by windmills are still important today, such as sawing, cutting, boring, drilling, crushing, hammering, sharpening, polishing, milling, turning, and so on. All these production processes can be run with an intermittent power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes for food production processes (mincing, grinding or hulling grains, pressing olives and seeds), mining and excavation (picking and shovelling, rock and ore crushing), or textile production (fulling cloth, preparing fibres, knitting and weaving). In all these examples, intermittent energy input does not affect the quality of the production process, only the production speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many production processes are not strongly disadvantaged by an intermittent power supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running these processes on variable power sources has become a lot easier than it was in earlier times. For one thing, wind power plants are now completely automated, while the traditional windmill required constant attention. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/how-to-rig-a-windmill-sail_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: “Travailler au moulin / Werken met molens”, Jean Bruggeman, 1996.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: “Travailler au moulin / Werken met molens”, Jean Bruggeman, 1996. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, not only are wind turbines (and water turbines) more practical and powerful than in earlier times, we can now make use of solar energy to produce mechanical energy. This is usually done with solar photovoltaic (PV) panels, which convert sunlight into electricity to run an electric motor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, a factory that requires mechanical energy can be run on a combination of wind and solar power, which increases the chances that there&amp;rsquo;s sufficient energy to run its machinery. The ability to harvest solar energy is important because it&amp;rsquo;s by far the most widely available renewable power source. Most of the potential capacity for water power is already taken. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thermal-energy&#34;&gt;Thermal Energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another crucial difference with pre-industrial times is that we can apply the same strategy to basic industrial processes that require thermal energy instead of mechanical energy. Heat dominates industrial energy use, for instance, in the making of chemicals or microchips, or in the smelting of metals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In pre-industrial times, manufacturing processes that required thermal energy were powered by the burning of biomass, peat and/or coal. The use of these energy sources caused grave problems, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2011/09/medieval-smokestacks-fossil-fuels-in-pre-industrial-times/&#34;&gt;large-scale deforestation, loss of land, and air pollution&lt;/a&gt;. Although solar energy was used in earlier times, for instance, to evaporate salt along seashores, to dry crops for preservation, or to sunbake clay bricks, its use was limited to processes that required relatively low temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can apply the same strategy to basic industrial processes that require thermal energy instead of mechanical energy, which was not possible before the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, renewable energy other than biomass can be used to produce thermal energy in two ways. First, we can use wind turbines, water turbines or solar PV panels to produce electricity, which can then be used to produce heat by electrical resistance. This was not possible in pre-industrial times, because there was no electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/solar-powered-printing-press_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Augustin Mouchot&amp;amp;rsquo;s solar powered printing press, 1882.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Augustin Mouchot&#39;s solar powered printing press, 1882. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we can apply solar heat directly, using water-based flat plate collectors or evacuated tube collectors, which collect solar radiation from all directions and can reach temperatures of 120 degrees celsius. We also have solar concentrator collectors, which track the sun, concentrate its radiation, and can generate temperatures &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2011/07/the-bright-future-of-solar-thermal-powered-factories/&#34;&gt;high enough to melt metals or produce microchips and solar cells&lt;/a&gt;. These solar technologies only became available in the late 19th century, following advances in the manufacturing of glass and mirrors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;limited-energy-storage&#34;&gt;Limited Energy Storage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running factories on variable power sources doesn&amp;rsquo;t exclude the use of energy storage or a backup of dispatchable power plants. Adjusting demand to supply should take priority, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;other strategies&lt;/a&gt; can play a supportive role. First, energy storage or backup power generation capacity could be useful for critical production processes that can&amp;rsquo;t be halted for prolonged periods, such as food production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, short-term energy storage is also useful to run production processes that are disadvantaged by an intermittent power supply. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Third, short-term energy storage is crucial for computer-controlled manufacturing processes, allowing these to continue operating during short interruptions in the power supply, and to shut down safely in case of longer power cuts. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/binnenshaven-rotterdam_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Binnenshaven Rotterdam, a painting by Jongkind Johan Berthold (1857)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Binnenshaven Rotterdam, a painting by Jongkind Johan Berthold (1857) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to pre-industrial times, we now have more and better energy storage options available. For example, we can use biomass as a backup power source for mechanical energy production, something pre-industrial millers could not do – before the arrival of the steam engine, there was no way of converting biomass into mechanical energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the arrival of the steam engine, there was no way of converting biomass into mechanical energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have chemical batteries, and we have low-tech systems like flywheels, compressed air storage, hydraulic accumulators, and pumped storage plants. Heat energy can be stored in well-insulated water reservoirs (up to 100 degrees) or in salt, oil or ceramics (for much higher temperatures). All these storage solutions would fail for some reason or another if they were tasked with storing a large share of renewable energy production. However, they can be very useful on a smaller scale in support of demand adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-new-age-of-sail&#34;&gt;The New Age of Sail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cargo transportation is another candidate for using renewable power when it&amp;rsquo;s available. This is most obvious for shipping. Ships still carry about 90 percent of the world&amp;rsquo;s trade, and although shipping is the most energy efficient way of transportation per tonne-kilometre, total energy use is high and today&amp;rsquo;s oil powered vessels are extremely polluting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/arne-list_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image by Arne List [CC BY-SA 2.0], via Wikimedia Commons&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image by Arne List [CC BY-SA 2.0], via Wikimedia Commons 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common high-tech idea is to install wind turbines off-shore, convert the electricity they generate into hydrogen, and then use that hydrogen to power seagoing vessels. However, it&amp;rsquo;s much more practical and energy efficient to use wind to power ships directly, like we have done for thousands of years. Furthermore, oil powered cargo ships often float idle for days or even weeks before they can enter a port or leave it, which makes the relative unpredictability of sailboats less problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s much more practical and energy efficient to use wind to power ships directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with industrial manufacturing, we now have much better technology and knowledge available to base a worldwide shipping industry on wind power alone. We have new materials to build better and longer-lasting ships and sails, we have more accurate navigation and communication instruments, we have more predictable weather forecasts, we can make use of solar panels for backup engine power, and we have more detailed knowledge about winds and currents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/seven-masted-schooner_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Thomas W. Lawson was a seven-masted, stell-hulled schooner built in 1902 for the Pacific trade. It had a crew of 18.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Thomas W. Lawson was a seven-masted, stell-hulled schooner built in 1902 for the Pacific trade. It had a crew of 18. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the global wind and current patterns were only fully understood when the age of sail was almost over. Between 1842 and 1861, American navigator Matthew Fontaine Maury collected an extensive array of ship logs which enabled him to chart prevailing winds and sea currents, as well as their seasonal variations. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maury&amp;rsquo;s work enabled seafarers to shorten sailing time considerably, by simply taking better advantage of prevailing winds and sea currents. For instance, a journey from New York to Rio de Janeiro was reduced from 55 to 23 days, while the duration of a trip from Melbourne to Liverpool was halved, from 126 to 63 days. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, yacht racing has generated many innovations that have never been applied to commercial shipping. For example, in the 2017 America&amp;rsquo;s Cup, the Emirates Team New Zealand introduced stationary bikes instead of hand cranks to power the hydraulic system that steers the boat. Because our legs are stronger than our arms, pedal powered &amp;lsquo;grinding&amp;rsquo; allows for quicker tacking and gybing in a race, but it could also be useful to reduce the required manpower for commercial sailing ships. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/fast-sailing_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speed sailing records are also telling. The fastest sailboat in 1972 did not even reach 50 km/h, while the current record holder — the Vestas Sailrocket 2 — sailed at 121 km/h in 2012. While these types of ships are not practical to carry cargo, they could inspire other designs that are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wind-and-solar-powered-trains&#34;&gt;Wind and Solar Powered Trains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could follow a similar approach for land-based transportation, in the form of wind and solar powered trains. Like sailing boats, trains could be running whenever there is renewable energy available. Not by putting sails on trains, of course, but by running them on electricity made by solar PV panels or wind turbines along the tracks. This would be an entirely new application of a centuries-old strategy to deal with variable energy sources, only made possible by the invention of electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wind and solar powered trains would be an entirely new application of a centuries-old strategy to deal with variable energy sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running cargo trains on renewable energy is a great use of intermittent wind power because they are usually operated at night, when wind power is often at its best and energy demand is at its lowest. Furthermore, just like cargo ships, cargo trains already have unreliable schedules because they often sit stationary in train-yards for days, waiting to become fully loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/cardiff-docks_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Cardiff Docks, a painting by Lionel Walden, 1894&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Cardiff Docks, a painting by Lionel Walden, 1894 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the speed of the trains could be regulated by the amount of renewable energy that is available, just as the wind speed determines the speed of a sailing ship. A similar approach could also work with other electrical transportation systems, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2009/07/get-wired-again-trolleybuses-and-trolleytrucks/&#34;&gt;trolleytrucks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2009/12/trolley-canal-boats/&#34;&gt;trolleyboats&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2011/01/aerial-ropeways-automatic-cargo-transport-for-a-bargain/&#34;&gt;aerial ropeways&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining solar and wind powered cargo trains with solar and wind powered factories creates extra possibilities. For example, at first sight, solar or wind powered passenger trains appear to be impossible, because people are less flexible than goods. If a solar powered train is not running or is running too slow, an appointment may have to be rescheduled at the last minute. Likewise, on cloudy days, few people would make it to the office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/solar-covered-railway_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Solar PV panels cover a railway in Belgium, 2016. Image: Infrabel.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Solar PV panels cover a railway in Belgium, 2016. Image: Infrabel. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this could be solved by using the same renewable power sources for factories and passenger trains. Solar panels along the railway lines could be sized for cloudy days, and thus guarantee a minimum level of energy for a minimum service of passenger trains (but no industrial production). During sunny days, the extra solar power could be used to run the factories along the railway line, or to run extra passenger (or cargo) trains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;consequences-for-society-consumption--production&#34;&gt;Consequences for Society: Consumption &amp;amp; Production&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we&amp;rsquo;ve seen, if industrial production and cargo transportation became dependent on the availability of renewable energy, we would still be able to produce a diverse range of consumer goods, and transport them all over the globe. However, not all products would be available all the time. If I want to buy new shoes, I might have to wait for the right season to get them manufactured and delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Production and consumption would depend on the weather and the seasons. Solar powered factories would have higher production rates in the summer months, while wind powered factories would have higher production rates in the winter months. Sailing seasons also need to be taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I want to buy new shoes, I might have to wait for the right season to get them manufactured and delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But running an economy on the rhythms of the weather doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean that production and consumption rates would go down. If factories and cargo transportation adjust their energy use to the weather, they can use the full annual power production of wind turbines and solar panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/windmill-zaandam_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A Windmill at Zaandam, a painting by Claude Monet, 1871.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A Windmill at Zaandam, a painting by Claude Monet, 1871. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturers could counter seasonal production shortages by producing items &amp;lsquo;in season&amp;rsquo; and then stocking it close to consumers for sale during low energy periods. In fact, the products themselves would become &amp;rsquo;energy storage&amp;rsquo; in this scenario. Instead of storing energy to manufacture products in the future, we would manufacture products whenever there is energy available, and store the products for later sale instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, seasonal production may well lead to lower production and consumption rates. Overproducing in high energy times requires large production facilities and warehouses, which would be underused for the rest of the year. To produce cost-efficiently, manufacturers will need to make compromises. From time to time, these compromises will lead to product shortages, which in turn could encourage people to consider other solutions, such as repair and re-use of existing products, crafted products, DIY, or exchanging and sharing goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;consequences-for-the-workforce&#34;&gt;Consequences for the Workforce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjusting energy demand to energy supply also implies that the workforce adapts to the weather. If a factory runs on solar power, then the availability of power corresponds very well with human rhythms. The only downside is that workers would be free from work especially in winter and on cloudy days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if a factory or a cargo train runs on wind power, then people will also have to work during the night, which is considered unhealthy. The upside is that they would have holidays in summer and on good weather days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/night-works-docks_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Nachtelijk werk in de dokken (Night work at the docks), a painting by Henri Adolphe Schaep, 1856.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Nachtelijk werk in de dokken (Night work at the docks), a painting by Henri Adolphe Schaep, 1856. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a factory or a transportation system is operated by wind or solar energy alone, workers would also have to deal with uncertainty about their work schedules. Although we have much better weather forecasts than in pre-industrial times, it remains difficult to make accurate predictions more than a few days ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is not only renewable power plants that are now completely automated. The same goes for factories. The last century has seen increasing automation of production processes, based on computers and robots. So-called “dark factories” are already completely automated (they need no lights because there is nobody there).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not only renewable power plants that are now completely automated. The same goes for factories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a factory has no workers, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter when it&amp;rsquo;s running. Furthermore, many factories already run for 24 hours per day, partly operated by millions of night shift workers. In these cases, night work would actually decrease because these factories will only run through the night if it&amp;rsquo;s windy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we could also limit the main share of industrial manufacturing and railway transportation to normal working hours, and curtail the oversupply during the night. In this scenario, we would simply have less material goods and more holidays. On the other hand, there would be an increased need for other types of jobs, like craftsmanship and sailing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-the-internet&#34;&gt;What About the Internet?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, industrial manufacturing and cargo transportation — both over land and over sea — could be run almost entirely on variable renewable power sources, with little need for energy storage, transmission networks, balancing capacity or overbuilding renewable power plants. In contrast, the modern high-tech approach of matching energy supply to energy demand at all times requires a lot of extra infrastructure which makes renewable power production a &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-not-to-run-a-modern-society-on-solar-and-wind-power-alone/&#34;&gt;complex, slow, expensive and unsustainable undertaking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjusting energy demand to supply would make switching to renewable energy much more realistic than it is today. There would be no curtailment of energy, and no storage and transmission losses. All the energy produced by solar panels and wind turbines would be used on the spot and nothing would go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2017/09/how-to-run-the-economy-on-the-weather/images/dithers/marina_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Marina, a painting by Carol Popp de Szathmary, 1800s.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Marina, a painting by Carol Popp de Szathmary, 1800s. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, adjusting energy demand to energy supply can be less straightforward in other sectors. Although the internet could be entirely operated on variable power sources — using &lt;a href=&#34;https://mar-ver.github.io/2015/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-internet/&#34;&gt;asynchronous networks and delay-tolerant software&lt;/a&gt; — many newer internet applications would then disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At home, we probably can’t expect people to sit in the dark or not to cook meals when there is no renewable energy. Likewise, people will not come to hospitals only on sunny days. In such instances, there is a larger need for energy storage or other measures to counter an intermittent power supply.
That&amp;rsquo;s for a next post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the research for this article happened during a fellowship at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Demand Centre&lt;/a&gt;, Lancaster, UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucas, Adam. &lt;em&gt;Wind, Water, Work: Ancient and Medieval Milling Technology&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 8. Brill, 2006.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hills, Richard Leslie. &lt;em&gt;Power from wind: a history of windmill technology&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press, 1996.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paine, Lincoln. The sea and civilization: a maritime history of the world. Atlantic Books Ltd, 2014.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reynolds, Terry S. Stronger than a hundred men: a history of the vertical water wheel. Vol. 7. JHU Press, 2002.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest large hydropower dams was the Cento dam in Italy (1450), which was 71 m long and almost 6 m high. By the 18th century, the largest dams were up to 260 m long and 25 m high, with power canals leading to dozens of water wheels. [2]&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although windmills had all kinds of internal mechanisms to adapt to sudden changes in wind speed and wind direction, wind power had no counterpart for the dam in water power.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This explains why windmills became especially important in regions with dry climates, in flat countries, or in very cold areas, where water power was not available. In countries with good water resources, windmills only appeared when the increased demand for power created a crisis because the best waterpower sites were already occupied.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tide mills were technically similar to water mills, but they were more reliable because the sea is less prone to dry out, freeze over, or change its water level than a river.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sieferle, Rolf Peter, and Michael P. Osman. The subterranean forest: energy systems and the industrial revolution. Cambridge: White Horse Press, 2001.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freese, Stanley. Windmills and millwrighting. Cambridge University Press, 1957&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wailes, Rex. The English windmill. London, Routledge &amp;amp; K. Paul, 1954&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global wind pattern is complemented by regional wind patterns, such as land and sea breezes. The Northern Indian Ocean has semi-annually reversing Monsoon winds. These blow from the southwest from June to November, and from the northeast from December to May. Maritime trade in the Indian Ocean started earlier than in other seas, and the established trade routes were entirely dependent on the season.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenkins, H. L. C. &amp;ldquo;Ocean passages for the world.&amp;rdquo; The Royal Navy, Somerset (1973).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windmillers had to be alert to keep the gap between the stones constant however choppy the wind, and before the days of the centrifugal governor this was done by hand. The miller had to watch the power of the wind, to judge how much sail cloth to spread, and to be prepared  to stop the mill under sail and either take in or let out more cloth, for there were no patent sails. And before the fantail came into use, he had to watch the direction of the wind as well and keep the sails square into the wind&amp;rsquo;s eye. [11]&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from electricity, the Industrial Revolution also brought us compressed air, water under pressure, and improved mechanical power transmission, which can all be valuable alternatives for electricity in certain applications.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar distinction was made in the old days. For example, when spinning cloth, a constant speed was required to avoid gearwheels hunting and causing the machines to deliver thick and thin parts in rovings or yarns. [3] That&amp;rsquo;s why spinning was only mechanised using water power, which could be stored to guarantee a more regular power supply, and not wind power. Wind power was also unsuited for processes like papermaking, mine haulage, or operating blast furnace bellows in ironworks.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very short-term energy storage is required for many mechanical production processes running on variable power sources, in order to smooth out small and sudden variations in energy supply. Such mechanical systems were already used in pre-industrial windmills.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leighly, J. (ed) (1963) The Physical Geography of the Sea and its Meteorology by Matthew Fontaine Maury, 8th Edition, Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press. Cited by Knowles, R.D. (2006) &amp;ldquo;Transport shaping space: the differential collapse of time/space&amp;rdquo;, Journal of Transport Geography, 14(6), pp. 407-425.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rival teams rejected pedal power because they feared radical change, says Team New Zealand designer. The Telegraph, May 24, 2017.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
