<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LOW←TECH MAGAZINE English</title>
    <link>/tags/buildings/</link>
    <description>This is a solar-powered website, which means it sometimes goes offline </description>
    <generator>Hugo 0.115.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/buildings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Printed Website: Volume III &amp; The Comments</title>
      <link>/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="14598" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/all-four-books_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The Printed Website.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The Printed Website. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-volume-iii&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest Low-tech Magazine book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;collects 18 articles published between 2018 and 2021&lt;/a&gt;. At 368 pages it’s a thin book compared to earlier volumes. When we started the book series, the challenge was to unlock an archive of almost 12 years. It made sense to pack this content into as few volumes as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, looking ahead, we will publish more often, once every one to three years, depending on the number of articles written. From now on, the articles will be arranged chronologically, from oldest to newest, and no longer the other way around. This volume contains 184 images in black and white. It is &lt;a href=&#34;/fr/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/&#34;&gt;also available in French&lt;/a&gt; (400 pages).
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;low-tech-magazine-the-comments&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also launched a book which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;collects almost 3,000 comments&lt;/a&gt; on the roughly 100 articles which are published in the three other books. This volume has 688 pages and no images. We included all feedback up to November 7, 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;/low-tech-magazine-the-printed-comments/&#34;&gt;Read more about the comments book here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, readers have often stated that the comments on the website are (at least) as interesting as the articles themselves. We agree. Low-tech Magazine would not have been even half what it is now without the comments. You can even take this literally, because this is one of the thickest books we have published so far, despite the extra small font we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-edition&#34;&gt;New Edition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have published a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;second edition of the first book we published&lt;/a&gt; in 2019. This new edition has almost twice as many images and follows the same design as the other volumes. In contrast to the first edition, the images are not &amp;ldquo;dithered&amp;rdquo; and of higher quality. We use a smaller font to pack more content on fewer pages. This second edition also fixes some errors in the articles and the references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/comments-book-cover_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2021/12/the-printed-website-volume-iii-and-more/images/dithers/low-tech-magazine-volume-III-montage_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021).&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021). 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents-volume-iii&#34;&gt;Contents Volume III&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Circular is the Circular Economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping Some of the Lights On: Redefining Energy Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat your House with a Mechanical Windmill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinventing the Small Wind Turbine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Wind Power Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mist Showers: Sustainable Decadence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too Much Combustion, Too Little Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is a Solar Powered Website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fruit Trenches: Cultivating Subtropical Plants in Freezing Temperatures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thermoelectric Stoves: Ditch the Solar Panels?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Make Biomass Energy Sustainable Again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How and Why I Stopped Buying New Laptops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical Farming Does not Save Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Sustainable is High-tech Health Care?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Urban Fish Ponds: Low-tech Sewage Treatment for Towns and Cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Design a Sailing Ship for the 21st Century?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Build a Low-tech Solar Panel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fascine Mattresses: Basketry Gone Wild&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;print-on-demand&#34;&gt;Print on Demand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The books are printed on demand, meaning that there are no unsold copies (and no large upfront investment costs). Our US publisher Lulu.com works with printers all over the world, so that most copies are produced locally and travel relatively short distances. Note that it takes 3 to 5 work days to print the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2007-2012/paperback/product-1z742pek.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume I (2007-2012)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2012-2018-second-edition/paperback/product-zvz55m.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume II (2012-2018)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-2018-2021/paperback/product-q7r49d.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine Volume III (2018-2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/kris-de-decker/low-tech-magazine-the-comments-2008-2021/paperback/product-9457rd.html&#34;&gt;Low-tech Magazine: The Comments (2008-2021)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Curse of the Modern Office</title>
      <link>/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/fantasy-skyline_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="40533" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/fantasy-skyline_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The information society promises to dematerialise society and make it more sustainable, but modern office and knowledge work has itself become a large and rapidly growing consumer of energy and other resources. Image: Fantasy skyline. Skyscrapercity.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The information society promises to dematerialise society and make it more sustainable, but modern office and knowledge work has itself become a large and rapidly growing consumer of energy and other resources. Image: Fantasy skyline. Skyscrapercity.  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;welcome-to-the-office&#34;&gt;Welcome to the Office&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, it&amp;rsquo;s rather easy to define an &amp;ldquo;office worker&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s someone who sits in front of a computer screen for most of the working day, often in a space where others are doing the same, but sometimes alone in a &amp;ldquo;home office&amp;rdquo; or with a few others in a &amp;ldquo;shared office&amp;rdquo;. In earlier times, many office workers were used not for their knowledge or intelligence, but for the mere objective capacity of their brains to store and process information. For example, &amp;ldquo;computers&amp;rdquo; were office workers who made endless calculations with the help of mechanical calculating machines. This category of office workers has become comparatively less important, because inanimate computers have taken over many of their jobs. Most office workers — so-called &amp;ldquo;knowledge workers&amp;rdquo; — are now paid to actually think and be creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a big chance that you are one of them. Roughly 70% of those in employment in industrial nations now have office jobs. The share of office workers in the total workforce has increased continuously throughout the twentieth century. For example, in the USA, the information sector employed 13% of workers in 1900, about 40% of workers in 1950, and more than 60% of workers in 2000. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The spectacular and so far unstoppable growth in the number of office workers is believed to have led to a so-called information society, an idea popularised by Fritz Machlup in his 1962 book &lt;em&gt;The Production of Knowledge in the United States&lt;/em&gt;, and since then repeated by many others. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/downtown-chicago_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Downtown Chicago. Modified from image by Charles Voogd, Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Downtown Chicago. Modified from image by Charles Voogd, Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, there&amp;rsquo;s no agreement as to what an information society actually is, but the most widely accepted definition is a society where more than half of the labour force engages in informational activities and where more than half of the GNP is generated from informational goods and services. Some say that the information society is characterised by the use of modern IT equipment, but that does not explain the growth of office work during the first half of the twentieth century. Others have argued that there is a transition from an economy based on material goods to one based on knowledge. Their claim is that this shift from the &amp;ldquo;industrial society&amp;rdquo; to the &amp;ldquo;information society&amp;rdquo; would make the economy less resource intensive. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, unlike workers in manufacturing, service or agricultural industries, office workers don&amp;rsquo;t really produce anything besides paper documents, electronic files, and a lot of chatter during formal and informal meetings. However, the rise of office work has not lowered the use of resources, on the contrary. For one thing, supporters of the sustainable information society ignore the fact that we have moved most of our manufacturing industries (and our waste) to low wage countries. We are producing and consuming more material goods than ever before, but the energy use of these activities has vanished from national energy statistics. Second, modern office work has itself become a large and rapidly growing consumer of energy and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-energy-footprint-of-office-work&#34;&gt;The Energy Footprint of Office Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy use of office work consists of multiple components: the energy use of the building itself (office equipment, heating, cooling and lighting), the energy used for commuting to and from the office, and the energy used by the communications networks that office work depends on. It also includes people who are not working in the office but who plug in their laptops in a place outside the office, which is also lighted, heated or cooled. As far as I could find out, nobody has ever tried to calculate the energy footprint of office work, taking all these components into account. We know more or less how much energy is used by commuting and telecommunication, but we don&amp;rsquo;t know how much of that is due to office work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most information is available for the energy use of office buildings &amp;ndash; the icons of today&amp;rsquo;s global knowledge economy. However, even in this case information is limited because most national statistics do not distinguish between different types of commercial buildings. The main exception is the &lt;em&gt;US Commercial Buildings Energy Consumption Survey&lt;/em&gt; (CBECS), which is undertaken since 1979 and is the most comprehensive dataset of its type in the world. It further categorises offices into administrative or professional offices (such as real estate sales offices and university administration buildings), government offices (such as state agencies and city halls), banks and financial offices, and health service administrative centers. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/moscow-international-business-center_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Moscow International Business Center. Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Moscow International Business Center. Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern, American-style office building—a design increasingly copied all over the world—is an insult to sustainability. Per square metre of floorspace, US office buildings are twice as energy-intensive as US residential buildings (which are no examples of energy efficiency either). &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2003, the most recent year for which a detailed analysis of office buildings was presented (published in 2010), there were 824,000 office buildings in the USA, which consumed 300 trillion Btu of heat and 719 trillion Btu of electricity. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The electricity use alone corresponds to 210 TWh, which equals a quarter of total US electricity produced by nuclear power in 2015 (797 Twh with 99 reactors). In other words, the US needs 25 atomic reactors to power its office buildings. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; From 2003 to 2012, the number of US office buildings grew by more than 20%. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-we-get-here&#34;&gt;How Did we Get Here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US office building, which appeared with the arrival of the Industrial Revolution, was initially quite energy efficient. From the 1880s until the 1930s, sunlight was the principal means of illuminating the workplace and the most important factor in setting the dimensions and layout of the standard office building in the US. According to the NYC-based &lt;em&gt;Skyscraper Museum&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rentability depended on large windows and high ceilings that allowed daylight to reach as deeply as possible into the interior. The distance from exterior windows to the corridor wall was never more than 28 feet (8.5 m), which was the depth some daylight penetrated. Ceilings were at least 10 to 12 feet (3 - 3.65 m) in height, and windows were as big as possible without being too heavy to open, generally about 4 to 5 feet (1.2 - 1.5 m) wide and 6 to 8 feet (1.8 - 2.4 m) high. If the office was subdivided, partitions were made of translucent glass to transmit light.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many office buildings had window accomodating H-, T-, and L-shaped footprints to encourage natural lighting, ventilation, and cooling. This changed after the introduction of fluorescent light bulbs and air conditioning. Produced at an affordable price in the late 1930s, fluorescent lighting provided high levels of illumination without excessive heat and cost. The first fully air-conditioned American office buildings appeared around the 1930s. The combination of artificial lighting and air-conditioning made it possible to design office space much deeper than the old standard of 28 feet. Light courts and high ceilings were ditched, and office buildings were reconceived as massive cubes—which were much cheaper to build and which maximised floor space. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Air-conditioning also enabled the most characteristic feature of the modern office building: its glazed façade. From the 1950s onwards, under the influence of Modernist architecture, glass came to dominate in America—early examples of this trend are the Lever Building (1952) and the Seagram building (1958). The US Modernist office building, a cube with a steel skeleton and glass curtain walls, is essentially a massive greenhouse that would be unbearable for most of the year without artificial cooling. Because glazed façades don&amp;rsquo;t insulate well, energy use for heating is also high. In spite of all the glass, most US office buildings require artificial lighting throughout the day because many office workers are too far from a window to receive enough natural light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/canary-wharf-london_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Canary Wharf, London. Photo credit: David Illiff, Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Canary Wharf, London. Photo credit: David Illiff, Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;/2016/11/why-the-office-needs-a-typewriter-revolution/&#34;&gt;arrival of electric office equipment from the 1950s onwards&lt;/a&gt; further increased energy use. According to the CEBECS survey, &amp;ldquo;more computers, dedicated servers, printers, and photocopiers were used in office buildings than in any other type of commercial building&amp;rdquo;. According to the latest analysis, concerning the year 2003, American office buildings were using 27.6 million computers, 11.6 million printers, 2.1 million photocopiers, and 2.5 million dedicated servers. In addition to electricity consumed directly, this electronic equipment requires additional cooling, humidity control, and/or ventilation that also increase energy use. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While heating was the main energy use in pre-1950s office buildings, today cooling, lighting and electronic equipment (all operated by electricity), use 70% of all energy on-site. Note that this ratio doesn&amp;rsquo;t include the energy that is lost during the generation and distribution of electricity. Depending on how electricity is produced, energy use at the source can be up to three times higher than on-site. Assuming thermal generation of electricity (coal or natural gas), the average US office building consumes up to twice as much energy for electricity than for heating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cultural-differences&#34;&gt;Cultural Differences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology alone, however, does not explain the rise of the typical air-conditioned office building, nor its high energy use today. Although fluorescent light bulbs and air conditioning soon became available in Europe, the all-glass, cube-like office building remained for a long time a uniquely North American phenomenon. In the 1920s, office work in the USA came under the influence of Frederick Taylor&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Scientific Managament&amp;rsquo;. Time and motion studies, which had been carried out in factories since the 1880s, were now applied to office work as well. Men with stopwatches recorded the actions of (mostly female) employees with the aim of improving labour productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor&amp;rsquo;s ideas were translated into office design through the concept of large, open floor spaces with an orderly arrangement of desks, all facing the direction of the supervisor. Private office rooms were abolished. By the late 1940s, American offices resembled factories in their appearance and methods. Although Taylorism left its mark on European offices, it was taken up with less enthusiasm and faced more resistance rooted in tradition than in the US. In the 1960s and 1970s, the Europeans rejected the application of Taylorist principles to office work more strongly, and developed their own type of office building. British office expert Frank Duffy calls it the &amp;ldquo;social democratic&amp;rdquo; office. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These buildings, &amp;ldquo;groundscrapers&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;skyscrapers&amp;rdquo;, were designed like small cities, cut into separate &amp;ldquo;houses&amp;rdquo; that are united by internal &amp;ldquo;streets&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;squares&amp;rdquo;. They were built with corridors and spacious rooms on either side, all naturally lit and ventilated, with employees working next to a window. The social democratic office building focuses on user comfort, a consequence of the fact that office workers in Europe, unlike those in the USA, obtained the right to form democratically elected workers&amp;rsquo; councils that could participate in organisational decision making. The UK, with its more American style of business, embraced the US approach in the 1980s.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important difference between the &amp;ldquo;social democratic&amp;rdquo; office building and the &amp;ldquo;Taylorist&amp;rdquo; US/UK office building is that the first is usually owner-occupied, while the latter is generally a speculative building: It is built or refurbished to provide a return on investment, and rented by the room or floor. The speculative model is gaining ground: over the last two decades, US/UK-style office buildings have finally started spreading all over Europe, and beyond. Roughly 50% of new office buildings under construction in France and Germany—the largest European markets outside the UK—are now speculative buildings, roughly double their share in the 1980s. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is bad news, because speculative office buildings exclude lower energy alternatives and raise energy use. First, in order to maximise the return on investment, they are usually designed as square or rectangular buildings with deep floor plans and low ceilings, and built as high as planning regimes allow. Naturally lit and cooled buildings require a more horizontal build and higher ceilings, both aspects that conflict with maximising floorspace. Second, those who design speculative office buildings don&amp;rsquo;t know who will occupy the finished spaces, which leads to an over-provision of services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Developers and letting agents focus on the &amp;rsquo;needs&amp;rsquo; of the most demanding tenants, and hence what is required for an office to be marketable to any tenant&amp;rdquo;, write the authors of a recent study that looks into the energy demand of UK office buildings—and concludes that 92% of such buildings are over-provisioned. Lighting, cooling and heating systems are attuned to unrealistic occupancy rates and are consequently producing more light, heat and cold than is necessary. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-promise-of-remote-working&#34;&gt;The Promise of Remote Working&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the high energy use of office work is questioned at all, it&amp;rsquo;s usually followed by the proposal to work outside the office building. At least since the 1980s, home working has been touted as a trend with potential environmental benefits. Alvin Toffler&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Third Wave&lt;/em&gt; (1980) predicted that in the near future it would no longer be necessary to build offices because computers would enable people to work anywhere they wanted. In 1984, when personal computers had become common equipment in offices, Frank Duffy stated that &amp;ldquo;many office buildings quite suddenly are becoming obsolete&amp;rdquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/Chicago-Sears-Tower_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Downtown Chicago. Image by Charles Voogd (CC BY-SA 3.0)&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Downtown Chicago. Image by Charles Voogd (CC BY-SA 3.0) 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, no such thing happened: in spite of the personal computer, there are now more office buildings than ever before. However, the utopian vision of a radically changed work environment is still among us. Since the arrival of mobile phones, portable computers and the internet in the 1990s, the focus has shifted to &amp;ldquo;remote&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;agile&amp;rdquo; working, which includes working at home but also on the road and in so-called third places: coffeeshops, libraries or co-working offices. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These concepts suggest that offices will become meeting places for &amp;rsquo;nomadic&amp;rsquo; employees equipped with mobile phones and laptops, how the office will become a more diverse and informal environment, or how in the near future offices may no longer be necessary because we can work anywhere and at any time. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref4:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to a 2014 consultancy report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The term &amp;lsquo;office&amp;rsquo; will become obsolete in the coming years. The modern workplace evolves into more of a shared workspace with flexible working arrangements that acts as more of a hub for workers on the go than an official place of work. The vast majority of jobs in most organisations can be accomplished from virtually any PC or mobile device, from just about anywhere&amp;rdquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frank Duffy, building further upon his 1980s predictions, writes in &lt;em&gt;Work and the City&lt;/em&gt; (2008):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The development of the knowledge economy and achievement of sustainability will both be made possible by the power of information technology&amp;hellip; Office work can be carried out anywhere&amp;hellip; In the knowledge economy more and more businesses, both large and small, will be operated as networks, depending at least as much on virtual communications as on face-to-face interactions. Networked organisations do not need to operate, manage or define themselves within conventional categories of workplaces or conventional working hours.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;does-it-matter-where-we-work&#34;&gt;Does it Matter Where We Work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the face of it, more people working outside the office has obvious potential for energy savings. Home workers don&amp;rsquo;t have to travel to and from the office, which can save energy—after all, commuting has become energy-intensive since the democratisation of the car in the 1950s. Furthermore, home office workers tend to use less energy for heating, cooling and lighting than they do in the office, a finding that corresponds with the fact that office buildings consume double the energy per square metre of floorspace compared to residential homes. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are many ways in which the environmental advantages of remote working can disappear or become disadvantages. First, remote workers make use of &lt;a href=&#34;/2016/11/why-the-office-needs-a-typewriter-revolution/&#34;&gt;the same office equipment&lt;/a&gt;, the same data centers and &lt;a href=&#34;/2015/10/why-we-need-a-speed-limit-for-the-internet/&#34;&gt;the same internet and phone infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; as people working in an office—and these are now the main drivers behind the increasing energy use of office buildings. In fact, a networked office would surely increase energy use by communication services, because face-to-face meetings at the office are replaced and complemented by virtual meetings and other forms of electronic communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Work and the City&lt;/em&gt;, Frank Duffy recalls his participation in a videoconferencing talk, expressing his awe for the quality of the experience. What he doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to realise, is that the Cisco Telepresence system that he was using requires between 1 and 3 kW of power (and 200W in standby) at either side &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, plus the energy use of routing and switching all those data through the network infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/frankfurt-offices_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Frankfurt, Germany. Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Frankfurt, Germany. Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if work is done not at home but in third places, people might actually increase their energy use for transport when they visit different working spaces during the day. They might work from home in the morning and drive to the office in the afternoon, or they might go to the office in morning and to a co-working space later in the day. Likewise, if organisations shorten the distance between the office and the office worker by inviting them to work in shared spaces closer to their home, employees might actually decide to go live further away from their new working space, and keep the same time budget for commuting. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, for an employee working at home, on the road, or in a third place, the heating, cooling and lighting of that alternative workspace is now often an extra load because his or her now empty space in the office is still being heated, cooled and lit. In most cases, today&amp;rsquo;s home and remote workers occasion additional energy consumption. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This problem is recognised by the supporters of remote working, who stress that office buildings have to adapt to the new reality of the networked office by reducing floorspace and increasing the occupancy rates. This can happen through &amp;ldquo;hot-desking&amp;rdquo;, sharing a smaller amount of desks between office workers who decide not to work at home—and hope that not everybody will show up at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noel Cass, who investigates energy demand in offices for the UK&amp;rsquo;s at Lancaster University, has his doubts about this approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hot-desking requires the depersonalisation of the desk, as if it was a coffee bar or a library, and that&amp;rsquo;s easier said than done. Internet companies such as Google and Yahoo, who pioneered hot-desking arrangements and whose productivity is the rationale behind this trend, have gone back to giving each employee their personal space. In fact, these companies not only left behind the &amp;ldquo;non-territorial&amp;rdquo; office, they also have recognised that productivity is best secured by physical co-presence, discouraging telecommuting.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Office spaces now tend to be conceptualised as a &amp;lsquo;destination&amp;rsquo; with increasing amenities on the job, in an effort to attract and retain talent and encourage them to spend more time there. Examples are domestic-like interiors, gym facilities, indoor swimming pools, dry cleaners, or dentists on site. So, who knows, instead of working at home, the future could be living at the office. Obviously, increasing amenities at the office might negate the energy savings obtained by fewer and shared office desks.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, office work will always include buildings, commuting, office equipment and a communication infrastructure. The focus on the location of office work—at home, in the office, or elsewhere—conceals the real cause that impacts energy use: the high energy use of all its components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/shanghai-offices_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Lujiazui, Shanghai. Patrick Fisher, Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Lujiazui, Shanghai. Patrick Fisher, Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the commute happens, or could happen, by walking, biking, or taking a commuter train, instead of by car, the energy use advantage of working at home would be zero or insignificant. Similarly, if an office building is designed in such a way that it can be naturally lit and cooled, like in the old days, working from home would not save energy for cooling and lighting. Finally, the use of &lt;a href=&#34;/2016/11/why-the-office-needs-a-typewriter-revolution/&#34;&gt;low energy office equipment&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&#34;/2015/10/how-to-build-a-low-tech-internet/&#34;&gt;low energy internet infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; would lower the energy use regardless of where people are working. In short, for energy use it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter so much where office work happens. What really matters is what happens at these places and in between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-much-office-work-do-we-need&#34;&gt;How Much Office Work Do We Need?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his 1986 book &lt;em&gt;The Control Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, James Beniger states that there is a tight relationship between the volume and speed of energy conversion and material processing in an industrial system on the one hand, and the importance of bureaucratic organisation and information processing, in other words, office work, on the other hand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Innovation in matter and energy processing create the need for further innovation in information processing and communication—an increased need for control. Until the nineteenth century, the extraction of resources, even in the largest and most developed national economies, were still carried out with processing speeds enhanced only slightly by draft animals and wind and water power.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So long as the energy used to process and move material throughputs did not much exceed that of human labour, individual workers could provide the information processing required for its control. The Industrial Revolution sped up society&amp;rsquo;s entire material processing system, thereby precipitating a crisis of control.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;As the crisis in control spread through the material economy, it inspired a continuing stream of innovations in control technology—a steady development of organisational, information-processing, and communication technology that lags industrialisation by perhaps 10 to 20 years. By the 1930s, the crisis of control had been largely contained.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Beniger makes no reference whatsoever to sustainability issues, what he suggests here is another strategy to lower the energy use of office work: reduce the demand for it. If office work depends on the material and energy throughput in the industrial system, it follows that reducing this throughput will lower the need for office work. A slower, low energy, and more low-tech industrial system would decrease the need for control and thus for office work. An economy with smaller organisations operating more locally, would need less office work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/11/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/images/dithers/madrid-offices_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Cuatro Torres Business Area, Madrid. Xauxa Hakan Svensson, Wikipedia Commons.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Cuatro Torres Business Area, Madrid. Xauxa Hakan Svensson, Wikipedia Commons. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 1900s, all management techniques and office tools that would be used for the next 70 years had been invented. James Beniger was not impressed by the arrival of the digital computer, which was becoming ubiquitous in offices when he wrote his book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Contrary to prevailing views, which locate the origins of the information society in WWII or in the commercial development of television or computers, the basic societal transformation from industrial to information society had been essentially completed by the late 1930s.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Microprocessing and computer technology, contrary to currently fashionable opinion, do not represent a new force recently unleashed on an unprepared society but merely the most recent installment in the continuing development of the control revolution.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Energy utilisation, processing speeds, and control technologies have continued to co-evolve in a positive spiral, advances in any one factor causing, or at least enabling, improvements in the other two. Furthermore, information processes and flows need themselves to be controlled, so that informational technologies must continue to be applied at higher and higher layers of control—certainly an ironic twist to the control revolution.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our so-called information economy mainly serves to manage an ever faster, larger and more complex production and consumption system, of which we have only outsourced the manufacturing part. Consequently, without the information economy—without the office—the industrial system would collape. Without the industrial system, there would be no need for the information society or the office—in fact, office work could be like it was before 1850, when the biggest bank in the US was run by just three people with a quill. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sustainable image of the information society—as contrasted to the dirty image of the industrial society—is built on an obsession with dividing energy use into different statistical categories, fiddling around with figures on electronic calculating tools. In other words, it&amp;rsquo;s a product of office work, hiding the true nature of office work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was written for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk&#34;&gt;The Demand Centre&lt;/a&gt;, one of six academic research centres funded by the Research Councils UK to address &amp;ldquo;End Use Energy Demand Reduction&amp;rdquo;. This article is a shortened version of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk/22/11/2016/the-curse-of-the-modern-office/&#34;&gt;original piece&lt;/a&gt;, which is on Demand&amp;rsquo;s website. The Demand Centre focuses on the use of energy as part of accomplishing social practices at home, at work and in moving around. It investigates how energy demand is shaped by material infrastructures and institutional arrangements, and how these systems reproduce interpretations of normal and acceptable ways of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Control Revolution: Technological and Economic Origins of the Information Society, James Beniger, 1986.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Growth of Information Workers in the US Economy, Edward N. Wolff, in &amp;ldquo;Communications of the ACM, October 2005/Vol.48, No.10, 2005.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theories of the Information Society (Third Edition), PDF, Frank Webster, 2006.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainability and the Information Society [PDF], Christian Fuchs, IFIP International Conference on Human Choice and Computers, 2006.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2012 Commercial Buildings Energy Consumption Survey (CBECS), U.S. Energy Information Administration.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A review on Buildings Energy Consumption Information [PDF], Luis Pérez-Lombard, José ortiz, Christine Pout. In &amp;ldquo;Energy and Buildings 40 (2008), pp.394-398.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power Density: A Key to Understanding Energy Sources and Uses (MIT Press), Vaclav Smil, 2015.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BSD-152: Building Energy Performance Metrics. Building Science Corporation, 2010.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. Energy Use Intensity by Property Type, Technical Reference [PDF]. Energy Star, 2016.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wnew.www.eia.gov/consumption/commercial/data/archive/cbecs/cbecs2003/officereport/office1.html&#34;&gt;Office Buildings&lt;/a&gt;, CBECS, 2010.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US Nuclear Power Plants, Nuclear Energy Institute.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Look at the US Commercial Building Stock: Results from EIA&amp;rsquo;s 2012 Commercial Buildings Energy Consumption Survey (CEBECS). US Energy Information Administration, 2015.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downtown New York: The Architecture of Business / The Business of Buildings. Virtual Exhibition. The Skyscraper Museum.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Losing Our Cool: Uncomfortable Truths About Our Air-Conditioned World (and Finding New Ways to Get Through the Summer), Stan Cox, 2010.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The European Office: Office Design and National Context&lt;/em&gt;, Juriaan van Meel, 2000.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Work and the City (Edge Futures)&lt;/em&gt;, Frank Duffy, 2008.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Office Buildings Go Up on Mere Speculation, Alessio Pirolo, The Wall Street Journal, October 7, 2014.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standards, Design and Energy Demand: The Case of Commercial Offices &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DEMAND2016_Full_paper_8-Faulconbridge.pdf&#34;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;. James Faulconbridge &amp;amp; Noel Cass, 2016. Paper prepared for DEMAND Centre Conference, Lancaster, 13-15 April 2016.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papers in preparation, Noel Cass, The Demand Centre, Lancaster University, UK.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study: The Traditional Office Will Soon be Extinct. PC World, Tony Bradley, June 17, 2014. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pcworld.com/article/439848/study-the-traditional-office-will-soon-be-extinct.html&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Practice of Working from Home and the Place of Energy &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.demand.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DEMAND2016_Full_paper_33-Hampton.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;, Sam Hampton. Paper prepared for DEMAND Centre Conference, Lancaster, 13-15 April, 2016.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/products/collaboration-endpoints/immersive-telePresence/index.html&#34;&gt;Immersive TelePresence&lt;/a&gt;. Cisco.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Get Your Apartment Off the Grid</title>
      <link>/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/</link>
      
      <enclosure url="/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-panels-window-sills_dithered.png" type="image/png" length="24299" ></enclosure>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-panels-window-sills_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The solar panels. Image by Kris de Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The solar panels. Image by Kris de Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical solar PV power installation requires access to a private roof and a big budget. However, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be possible to get around these obstacles by installing small solar panels on window sills and balconies, connected to a low-voltage direct current (DC) distribution network? To put this theory to the test, I decided to power Low-tech Magazine&amp;rsquo;s home office in Spain with solar energy, and write my articles off the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solar panels have become cheaper and more efficient in recent years, but they are far from a universal solution, even in sunny regions. One reason is that a typical solar photovoltaic (PV) installation is still beyond the budget of many people. The average pricing for a 5kW residential PV system completed in 2014 varied from $11,000 in Germany to $16,450 in the USA. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Roughly half of that amount concerns the installation costs. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second obstacle for solar power is that not everybody lives in a single-family dwelling with access to a private roof. Those who reside in apartment buildings have little chance of harvesting solar power with a conventional roof-mounted system. Furthermore, in apartment buildings, the roof would quickly become too crowded to cover the electricity use of all residents, a problem that grows larger the more floors there are in a building. Lastly, a typical solar installation is problematic when you&amp;rsquo;re renting a place, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a house or an apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m one of those people who runs into every one of these obstacles: I live in a flat, I rent the place, and I don&amp;rsquo;t have the budget for a conventional solar system. However, I receive a lot of sunshine. My apartment is located near Barcelona in Spain, a city with an average solar insolation of almost 1,700 kWh/m2/year (which is also the average figure across the USA). Furthermore, the 60 m2 apartment has the balcony and all windows facing south-south-west, and there is no shading by trees or other buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/view-from-home-office_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The view from my home office. Image by Kris de Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The view from my home office. Image by Kris de Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These conditions allow me to get through the winter without a heating system, relying only on &lt;a href=&#34;/2012/03/the-solar-envelope-how-to-heat-and-cool-cities-without-fossil-fuels/&#34;&gt;solar heat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/2011/02/insulation-first-the-body-then-the-home/&#34;&gt;thermal underclothing&lt;/a&gt;. Hot water is supplied by a solar boiler, which was installed by the landlord. Clothes are dried on the balcony. While tinkering with solar panels for an art project, I got an idea: with the sun already powering so much of my living space, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it also be possible to harvest solar power from the window sills and the balcony and take my apartment off the electricity grid? Such a PV installation would solve my problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t need access to the roof.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can install the system myself, which makes it much cheaper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can take the solar installation with me if I move to another place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the big question is whether or not such an unconventional solar system could generate the necessary electricity. As a first experiment, I decided to power my 10 m2 home office with solar panels placed on the 2.8 m long window ledge that runs along the windows of the office and the adjacent bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solar-powered-home-office&#34;&gt;Solar Powered Home Office&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The window in my office is quite small (at 1.5 m2, it takes up only half of one wall). However, there&amp;rsquo;s no need for power in the bedroom, which has been lighted by three &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ikea.com/ms/en_GB/sunnan/sunnan.html&#34;&gt;IKEA SUNNAN lamps&lt;/a&gt; for years. Consequently, the full window ledge is available to power the home office. It offers enough space for five solar panels of 10W each, providing me with 50 watt-peak of solar power. The balcony will serve to power the rest of the apartment, and the plans for that second project are outlined at the end of this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-powered-home-office_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: The solar panels on the window sills. Image by Kris de Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: The solar panels on the window sills. Image by Kris de Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With their placement on the window sill, the panels are shaded by the building itself in the morning. They receive direct sunlight from about 10 am to 5 pm in the pit of winter (a total of 7 hours), and from roughly 1 pm to 9 pm in the height of summer (a total of 8 hours). The maximum energy production is thus roughly 400 Wh per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solar panels are connected in parallel and coupled to a solar charge controller and 550 Wh of lead-acid batteries. Assuming a 33% Depth-Of-Discharge (DoD) and a round-trip battery efficiency of 80%, this gives me a maximum energy storage of roughly 150 Wh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you power a home office with 50 watt-peak solar panels and 150 Wh of energy storage?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s look at the energy use of my home office, before it was solar powered. I sit here working most of the days, either researching, writing, or building and repairing stuff. Devices that regularly use electricity are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A laptop, which requires an average 20 watts of power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An external computer screen, which needs 16.5W of power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two CFL lamps (20W and 12W) and one LED-lamp (3W).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;home-office-power-use&#34;&gt;Home Office Power Use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds up to 35W of power during the day (with only the laptop and the screen in use) and 70W after sunset (the laptop, the screen, and the lights). I usually work in the mornings and evenings, roughly from 10 am to 2 pm and from 8 pm to 1 am. During the afternoon, I do other stuff or I work in the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total electricity use in my office is thus (on average) 500 Wh per day, with little variation between winter and summer. On cloudy days I also use lights in morning, which can raise energy use to 640 Wh per day. Then there are some devices that occasionaly need power:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A laser printer, which uses 4Wh of energy for warming up and printing eight text pages. This corresponds to operating my desk lamp (5W) for more than 45 minutes.
A pair of PC loudspeakers (1.5W of power).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three USB bicycle lights (each use 1.4W of power while charging).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A digital camera, which uses 3W while charging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fan, which uses 30-40 watts of power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mobile phone (a dumb one) that&amp;rsquo;s charged once every few weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-panel-on-window-sill_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image: Solar panel on window sill.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image: Solar panel on window sill. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, my solar PV system doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce enough energy to power my home office. While regular electricity use is at least 500 Wh on a 9-hour working day, the window sills give me a maximum of 400 Wh per day. On overcast days, energy production can be as low as 40 to 200 Wh per day, depending on the type of cloud cover. Furthermore, energy storage is only 150 Wh under ideal circumstances, while most energy use (350 Wh) is after sunset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, here I am, typing this article on a solar powered laptop in a room that&amp;rsquo;s lit by solar power. How is this possible? By &lt;strong&gt;following these strategies&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize solar power production by tilting the panels according to the season.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimize power use by installing a low-voltage DC grid and using DC appliances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Force yourself to lower energy demand on dark days by going off the grid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, we look at these points in more detail. My solar system has been in operation since November 2015, initially with only two 10W panels. Three more panels were added in early spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-adjust-the-tilt-of-the-solar-panels&#34;&gt;1. Adjust the Tilt of the Solar Panels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roof-mounted solar panels usually have a fixed angle in relation to the sun. Because the elevation of the sun varies throughout the year, a fixed angle is always a compromise. Panels that lay horizontal on a flat roof are relatively well positioned for energy production in summer, but much less so for use in winter. On the other hand, tilted solar panels perform much better in winter but not as well as in summer. On sloped roofs, the angle of the panels is often determined by the angle of the roof, which isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily the best angle for solar power production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A PV panel that&amp;rsquo;s optimally tilted towards the winter sun can triple electricity generation compared to a horizontally placed panel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the angle of a solar panel according to the season can increase electricity production significantly in winter. In December, a PV panel in Barcelona that&amp;rsquo;s optimally tilted towards the winter sun can triple electricity generation compared to a horizontally placed panel. Because the advantage is much smaller in other seasons, the average annual increase in power production is less than 10%. However, tilting the panels is the key to harvesting enough solar power during the winter months, when power shortages are most probable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/home-made-solar-system_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;One of the solar panels. Image by Adriana Parra.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 One of the solar panels. Image by Adriana Parra. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/home-made-solar-system2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;One of the solar panels. Image by Adriana Parra.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 One of the solar panels. Image by Adriana Parra. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of a balcony or window sill solar PV system, adjusting the angle of the solar panels is as simple as watering the plants. Although you could make small adjustments every hour, day or month, adapting the angle two or four times per year is as far as you should go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s another advantage to having the solar panels so close at hand: they can be cleaned regularly. Roof-mounted solar panels rarely get cleaned because the roof usually isn&amp;rsquo;t very accessible. Losses due to dust and dirt are assumed to be 1% of generated energy, but in dry and dusty regions, as well as in traffic-heavy areas, they can be as high as 4-6% if washing is not undertaken on a regular basis. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the angle of a window sill solar panel is as simple as watering the plants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial that the panels don&amp;rsquo;t fall off the window ledge, no matter what happens. Window sills differ in shapes and sizes, which calls for a custom-made supporting structure. I have a fixed metal bar at my window sill, aimed at protecting plant containers, which allows me to securely lock the solar panels in place. I guess I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to have this, but it also shows how small design changes can make a big difference. As an additional safety measure, I loaded the wooden base of each panel with some heavy rocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding a mechanism to vary the tilt of the panels complicates the design, because the moving part has to be just as sturdy as the base. Following some failed attempts, I found a mechanism that seems to work, using vintage Meccano rods (2-3 layers thick and with larger nuts and bolts). One rod is connected to the base of the structure, while another is connected to the wooden board that carries the panel. Both rods are connected to each other in the middle. Loosening this connection allows me to adjust the length of the supports and thus the angle of the solar panels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solar-pv-windows&#34;&gt;Solar PV Windows?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some readers might consider my approach soon-to-be-obsolete, because several companies are working on &amp;ldquo;solar PV windows&amp;rdquo;: glass that doubles as an electricity generator. However, this technology would not perform as well as adjustable solar panels on window sills, for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-panels-apartment_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The panels on the left are optimally tilted for spring, the two panels on the right are still in winter position.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The panels on the left are optimally tilted for spring, the two panels on the right are still in winter position. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, solar PV windows are most often entirely vertical, which is never an efficient angle to generate solar power — their power generation is about 3 times lower than horizontal panels. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Secondly, in summer it would be impossible to open the windows or lower the shutters, which would quickly overheat my office and introduce a need for air-conditioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solar PV installation, on the other hand, can produce power when the shutters are closed and when the windows are open. Last but not least, a window-integrated solar panel can&amp;rsquo;t be taken with you when you move, while my system is entirely mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-opt-for-a-low-voltage-dc-system&#34;&gt;2. Opt for a Low-Voltage DC System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical solar PV systems convert the direct current (DC) electricity produced by solar panels into alternating current (AC) in order to make it compatible with the AC distribution system in a building. Because many modern appliances operate internally on DC, the AC electricity is then converted back to DC. The DC/AC-conversion is done by an inverter, which sits between the solar charge controller and the load. The second conversion happens in the (external or internal) AC/DC adapter of the devices that are being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble with this double energy conversion is that it generates substantial energy losses. This is especially true in the case of solid-state devices such as LEDs and computers, where the combined losses of the DC/AC/DC conversion amount to roughly 30% — &lt;a href=&#34;/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&#34;&gt;see our previous article&lt;/a&gt; for further detail. Because these are also the devices that make up most of the load in my home office, it makes a lot of sense to avoid these losses by building a low-voltage DC system instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-controller_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;A solar controller. Image by Kris de Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 A solar controller. Image by Kris de Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like in a boat or a camper, the 12V DC electricity of my solar panels is used directly by 12V DC appliances, or stored in 12V DC batteries. If my solar panels generate their maximum output of 50W, my devices have 50W available. When battery power is involved, charging and discharging the battery adds 20% of energy loss, which leaves 40W available for the appliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice for a low voltage DC system raises energy efficiency by 40%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, in a typical solar PV installation where a DC/AC/DC energy conversion takes place, the devices would only have 35W available, and the rest would be lost as heat during energy conversion. If lead-acid battery storage is used in such a system, only 28W of power remains. In short, in my specific case, choosing a DC system multiplies power production by 1.4 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice for a DC system saves not only energy but also space and costs. Less solar panels are needed and there&amp;rsquo;s no need to buy a DC/AC inverter, which is a costly device that needs to be replaced at least once during the life of a solar system. Most importantly, you can build a DC solar power system yourself, even if you&amp;rsquo;re as clumsy as I am. A low-voltage DC grid (up to 24V) is safe to handle because it carries no risk of electric shock. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Adding up all costs, I took my home office off the grid for less than 400 euro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-to-find-dc-appliances&#34;&gt;Where to Find DC Appliances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mounting a DC system implies the use of DC-compatible devices. However, because so many modern appliances operate internally on DC, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that you have to buy everything anew. To adapt the lighting in my office, I simply cut the mains plugs from the power cords, replaced them with DC-compatible plugs that fit straight into my solar charge controller, and substituted the light bulbs with 12V LED-bulbs. To run the laptop on DC, I replaced the power adapter by a DC-compatible power cord, which is available for use in cars. These power cords can be bought for every laptop model you can imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/DC-lamp_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;My 3W DC lamp. Image by Kris de Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 My 3W DC lamp. Image by Kris de Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/DC-laptop_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;My laptop with DC power cord. Image by Kris de Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 My laptop with DC power cord. Image by Kris de Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other devices are harder to adapt because the AC/DC adapter is located in the device itself. For example, I haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out yet how to convert my external computer screen to operate directly on DC power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appliances that cannot be converted are usually available in a 12V &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.12volt-travel.com/&#34;&gt;DC version&lt;/a&gt;. Examples are refrigerators, slow cookers, televisions, air compressors, or power tools. These can be more expensive than their AC counterparts, because they are produced in much smaller quantities. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geinnovations.net/solarrefrigerator.html&#34;&gt;DC refrigerators&lt;/a&gt; are very expensive because they use vacuum insulation. While this makes sense in a camper or sailboat where space is restricted, it&amp;rsquo;s a needless cost in a common building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cigarette lighter receptacle in cars, initially designed to power an electrically heated cigarette lighter, has been the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; standard DC connector for decades. More recently, it has been joined by another low voltage DC distribution system, the USB connector. USB cables operate on 5V DC and can transfer both data and energy. Many consumer electronics are now powered by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, these devices are charged by the USB-port of a laptop or desktop computer, but they could be plugged straight into a solar PV system. While the standard USB-cable carries a maximum power of only 10 watts, the newer USB-PD standard accommodates devices with a power consumption of up to 100 watts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overcast-days&#34;&gt;Overcast Days&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice for a DC system has lowered power consumption in my home office considerably. My laptop&amp;rsquo;s energy use has decreased by about 20%. Switching to DC-direct LED-lamps has halved power use for lighting from 35 to 16W. Based on the 9-hour working day described earlier, daily energy use of regularly used devices in my home office has come down from 500 to 350 Wh/day. This brings average energy use below energy production on sunny days (400 Wh), which are plentiful where I live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/three-solar-panels-on-window-sills_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Three 10W solar panels on the window sill of the bedroom.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Three 10W solar panels on the window sill of the bedroom. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, the external computer screen and the laser printer are still running on grid power. The 350 Wh of energy use mentioned above includes the hypothetical use of a DC external screen (saving 15% of power compared to the AC version), but not the energy use of the printer. However, on sunny days, I have a significant surplus of electricity, which suggests that I could also operate the external screen and the printer. Even on partly cloudy days energy is abundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, energy use remains too high during overcast days, when power production is between 40 and 200 Wh per day. Obviously, adding more solar panels and batteries would solve the issue, but that&amp;rsquo;s not the way to go because the solar PV system would become more expensive, less practical, and less sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On sunny or partly cloudy days, I have more than enough electricity. On overcast days, I have to reduce energy demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To guarantee a daily 350 Wh of electricity during three consecutive heavy overcast days in December (a worst case scenario of only 40 Wh energy production per day), I would need to increase solar power capacity fourfold, from 50 to 200W peak capacity, and provide at least five times more batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it would be possible to install 200W on the window sills, in that case the solar panels would stop solar light and heat from entering the rooms, which would be counterproductive. Furthermore, I would produce way too much electricity for most of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-adjust-energy-demand-to-meet-available-supply&#34;&gt;3. Adjust Energy Demand to Meet Available Supply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-controller-view_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The solar charge controller and half of the home office battery storage. Image by Adriana Parra.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The solar charge controller and half of the home office battery storage. Image by Adriana Parra. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s another option to make the numbers match if there&amp;rsquo;s not enough sun available, and that&amp;rsquo;s using less energy. Suggesting a reduction in energy use is rather controversial, but there are a surprisingly large number of ways to reduce energy use, without having to revert to a typewriter and candles. Here are some possibilities for my home office:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;install a second working desk right next to the window&lt;/strong&gt;. This eliminates the need for artificial lighting on dark winter days, which saves me at least another 40 Wh on days that electricity production is at its lowest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;use less lights in evening during low solar power days&lt;/strong&gt;. For most of the year, I have sufficient energy available to use all the lights in the room. However, most of the days I get by with only two lamps, and if necessary I could use a single 5W or even 3W lamp. When solar production is at its lowest, the latter still gives me more than 13 hours of light. I will never have to spend a night in the dark.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;shift loads towards sunny afternoons&lt;/strong&gt;. Even in winter, the batteries can already be fully charged by around 2 or 3 pm on sunny days. Adding extra load to the system during these periods takes advantage of solar energy that would otherwise get wasted. This is when I can charge the bicycle lights, the digital camera or the phone, or when I can use the 12V soldering iron (my only power tool) or the printer. In summer I can use the surplus of energy to power two small USB-fans, and of course that&amp;rsquo;s the time when I need the fans the most.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a surprisingly large number of ways to reduce energy use, without having to revert to a typewriter and candles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;change my working schedule&lt;/strong&gt;. If I could manage to work from 9 am to 6 pm instead of in morning and evening, I obtain a double energy savings. I would need no more lighting, except for one hour or so in winter (which saves 70 to 80 Wh/day). Secondly, I would use more electricity while it&amp;rsquo;s being generated, avoiding 20% battery charging and discharging losses while operating the laptop at night and in mornings (which saves another 30Wh). Changing my working schedule would lower daily electricity use to roughly 125Wh, less than half of maximum power production. Furthermore, all battery capacity would be available for overcast days, because there is no energy use at night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;adapt computer work to solar conditions&lt;/strong&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s a remarkable difference in power use for the laptop between writing (roughly 15W) and surfing the web (roughly 25W). In other words, I can work almost twice as long when I&amp;rsquo;m writing, which I could do whenever available energy is low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;ditch my external computer screen&lt;/strong&gt;. It can be very handy for some work, giving both a screen to read and a screen to write, but most of the time it&amp;rsquo;s just wasting energy without being very useful. Ditching the external screen would save me another 150 Wh per day. However, it would probably increase the use of the printer, so it remains to be seen if this option really saves energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During consecutive, heavy overcast days, I could revert to more drastic measures, like working in the library or not working at all. Or, I could do &lt;strong&gt;work that doesn&amp;rsquo;t involve any energy use&lt;/strong&gt; during the day, such as reading books and taking notes by hand. This would bring extra advantages; it can be refreshing to disconnect and concentrate on something in the old-fashioned way. Going out one evening is a fun and easy way to keep the power level high enough during periods of bad weather.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;strong&gt;build a &lt;a href=&#34;/2022/03/how-to-build-a-practical-household-bike-generator/&#34;&gt;pedal powered generator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for when I really need more electricity during overcast days. Strictly speaking, this is not a reduction of energy demand, but of course it implies an effort from my side. Pedalling for 1 to 1.5 hours would generate roughly 100 Wh of electricity, which would allow me to work on the computer for 3 to 5 hours, or to operate the 5W LED-light throughout the night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/barometer_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;My barometer.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 My barometer. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By keeping an eye on my barometer and being a bit flexible, it&amp;rsquo;s not that hard to plan work according to the weather. However, until now I managed to take advantage of these opportunities mostly when it comes to lighting, and less so when using the laptop. This has nothing to do with computer use being less flexible than lighting. Rather, it&amp;rsquo;s a consequence of how the system is built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This became clear due to the rather clumsy way that I set up my experiment. Obviously, I wanted to test the installation in the depth of winter before writing about it. However, I only had two solar panels at the time. Therefore, I first tested my solar powered home office by running the laptop on solar energy for two weeks (while running the lights on grid power), followed by a two-week test of running the lights on solar energy (and the computer on grid power).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lighting, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to fall back on grid power because I had to cut the power cords of all lamps to make them compatible with the 12V DC grid&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results were remarkably different for both periods. With the laptop, I could always fall back on grid power by simply switching the power cord. Consequently, there were no external factors that forced me to change my way of working in order to remain within the limits of the energy budget on a dark day. For lighting, however, it was impossible to fall back on grid power. I had to cut the power cords of all lamps to make them compatible with the 12V DC grid, which meant that I could not run them on AC grid power anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During low power periods, I had no other choice than to lower energy demand for lighting, and that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what I did, quite effortlessly I must say. I quickly made an extra desk at the window to avoid using artificial lights in morning, I switched the lights off whenever I left the room, and I worked with just a 5W or even a 3W light bulb if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five months later, I have become totally accustomed to adjusting light levels to available solar power. On the other hand, I keep plugging my laptop into the grid if energy runs low. Why? Because I can. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/new-desk-at-window_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The new desk at the window.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The new desk at the window. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, going off-grid seems to be the key to lowering energy demand considerably. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Having a limited energy supply also encourages the use of more energy efficient technology. For example, the energy savings I made by replacing the two remaining CFL lamps by LEDs could also have been achieved without building a solar PV system. However, the option only occurred to me after I took up the challenge of powering the office with solar energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress in energy efficient technology will steadily increase the possibilities of my off-grid system, with no risks of rebound effects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I would not be able to fall back on grid power, I would probably also get a more energy efficient laptop. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the future, I could also switch to lithium-ion batteries, which have lower losses than lead-acid batteries. Investing in more energy efficient technology would allow me to run the computer and the lights longer with the same amount of solar panels. With a limited power supply, there&amp;rsquo;s no risk of rebound effects that negate these benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-multiple-solar-pv-systems&#34;&gt;Build Multiple Solar PV Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned at the beginning of the article, the solar powered home office is only the first step towards converting the whole apartment to solar power and going totally off-grid. The second project will be the installation of a solar system on the 6-metre long balcony in front of the living room and the (open) kitchen. It will power the lights, the stereo-installation, the Wifi-router, all computer use outside the office, and all kitchen appliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-lamps_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;The bedroom&amp;amp;rsquo;s electricity system.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 The bedroom&#39;s electricity system. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This second experiment is much more challenging for two reasons. First, the living room and kitchen will also be used by the second person in this household, which will make it more complicated to manage energy use. Furthermore, although we don&amp;rsquo;t have a toaster, a coffeemaker, or a microwave, the kitchen houses a much used high power appliance: the electric cookstove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it would take too many solar panels and batteries to power the electric cookstove by solar PV panels, the plan is to replace it by non-electric alternatives: one or two solar cookers, a &lt;a href=&#34;/2014/07/if-we-insulate-our-houses-why-not-our-cooking-pots/&#34;&gt;fireless cooker&lt;/a&gt;, and a &lt;a href=&#34;/2014/06/well-tended-fires-outperform-modern-cooking-stoves/&#34;&gt;rocket stove&lt;/a&gt; for the morning coffee. By using direct solar heat, we can make much more efficient use of the space on the balcony. Another plan is to build a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notechmagazine.com/2012/01/saving-food-from-the-fridge.html&#34;&gt;low-tech food storage system&lt;/a&gt; that can store most of the food outside the refrigerator, keeping this energy-intensive appliance as small as possible or eliminating it altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The balcony solar PV system will be totally independent of the window sill solar PV system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The balcony solar PV system will be totally independent of the window sill solar PV system. There are several advantages to this approach. As we have seen in the previous article, &lt;a href=&#34;/2016/04/slow-electricity-the-return-of-dc-power/&#34;&gt;cable losses are relatively high in a low-voltage DC system&lt;/a&gt;. Setting up several independent systems greatly limits cable length (and cable clutter).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, installing separate systems allows total power use to surpass 150 watts — which is the safety limit for a 12V DC system. Thirdly, multiple systems make it possible to start small and gradually expand the system. This avoids large upfront costs and allows you to learn from your mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-from-your-mistakes&#34;&gt;Learning from your Mistakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, it was one such mistake that made me decide to install two separate systems even in my relatively small 10 m2 home office. The two solar panels in front of the office are connected to half of the batteries (powering the lights), while the three solar panels in front of the bedroom are connected to the other half (powering the laptop).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because I short-circuited my first solar charge controller and had to buy a second one while the first one was being repaired. It was that or go without lights for three weeks. Thus, a final advantage of multiple systems is increased reliability: if one system fails, there is still electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;article-img &#34;&gt;
&lt;figure data-imgstate=&#34;dither&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/2016/05/how-to-get-your-apartment-off-the-grid/images/dithers/solar-powered-office2_dithered.png&#34; alt=&#39;Image by Kris De Decker.&#39; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
 Image by Kris De Decker. 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the second experiment succeeds, and of course this remains to be seen, the plan is to stop the contract with our power provider, which is to be renewed in December. Obviously, it would be handy to keep a connection to the grid, but there are two important reasons not to do this. The first has been outlined above: going off-grid unleashes the creativity and willingness to lower energy demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, installing a solar system and holding on to a grid connection is financially disadvantageous. At least here in Spain, more than two-thirds of the electricity bill consists of fixed costs. Even if we would use much less grid electricity because of the solar system, our bill would remain more or less the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the second experiment succeeds, and of course this remains to be seen, the plan is to stop the contract with our power provider&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some important challenges remain, most notably the washing machine, the bathroom and the laser printer. The problem with washing machine and bathroom is that they&amp;rsquo;re on the north side of the building, far from the solar panels. We could go to a laundromat but there are none in town. A pedal powered washing machine requires space that we don&amp;rsquo;t have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laser printer could be operated with an inverter, which can also be handy to power any other occasional device that doesn&amp;rsquo;t run on 12V DC power. However, a relatively large and expensive inverter would be needed, because the startup power of the machine is above 400 watts. Luckily, I found that out before I fried another costly device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-you-start&#34;&gt;Before You Start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some things to keep in mind before you decide to install a low-tech solar PV system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;need enough sun&lt;/strong&gt;. Solar panels on balconies and window ledges won&amp;rsquo;t work everywhere. A similar system like mine, but 1,000 km further up north, would produce on average only half the electricity, with a much larger difference between winter and summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;need the right exposure&lt;/strong&gt;. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re in a sunny climate, don&amp;rsquo;t think of harvesting solar power if windows or balconies are oriented towards the north, the northwest, or the northeast. Shading by other buildings or trees can also smother your ambitions. You need at least 4 hours of direct sunshine on the panels each day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to be prepared to &lt;strong&gt;lower your energy use&lt;/strong&gt;. Few apartment dwellers will have enough space available to generate sufficient solar power for an energy-intensive lifestyle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It may be impossible to &lt;strong&gt;close some windows&lt;/strong&gt; completely. The cables from the panels enter my apartment by slightly opening the sliding window of the office. In winter, I cover this gap with cork. I don&amp;rsquo;t use heating so no energy gets lost, but this might be problematic in other circumstances. You probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t drill a hole through the window or the wall if you are renting the place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Converting your apartment to solar power &lt;strong&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t make you &amp;ldquo;100% sustainable&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. Fossil fuels are used to produce solar panels and batteries. The electricity I generate is likely more CO2-intensive per kWh than Spanish grid electricity, especially since my panels and batteries &lt;a href=&#34;/2015/04/how-sustainable-is-pv-solar-power/&#34;&gt;are manufactered in China&lt;/a&gt;. The only reason why my system is more sustainable than using grid electricity is because it forces me to lower electricity use considerably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written by Kris De Decker. Edited by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jenna-collett-0b39251a&#34;&gt;Jenna Collett&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.irena.org/documentdownloads/publications/irena_re_power_costs_2014_report.pdf&#34;&gt;Renewable Power Generation Costs in 2014&lt;/a&gt; (PDF), International Renewable Energy Agency (IRENA), January 2015&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nrel.gov/docs/fy14osti/62558.pdf&#34;&gt;Photovoltaic System Pricing Trends: Historical, Recent, and Near-Term Projections&lt;/a&gt; (PDF), 2014 Edition, SunShot, U.S. Departmennt of Energy, September 2014&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pv-magazine.com/news/details/beitrag/soft-costs-account-for-most-of-pv-residential-installation-costs_100013637/#axzz477QaYckc&#34;&gt;Soft costs account for most of PV residential installation costs&lt;/a&gt;, PV Magazine, December 2013&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/144199436X/&#34;&gt;Spain&amp;rsquo;s Photovoltaic Revolution: The Energy Return on Investment (SpringerBriefs in Energy)&lt;/a&gt;, Pedro A. Prieto &amp;amp; Charles A. Hall, 2013&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0262029146/&#34;&gt;Power Density: A Key to Understanding Energy Sources and Uses (MIT Press)&lt;/a&gt;, Vaclav Smil, 2015&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Provided that total power use is below 100-150 watts (which corresponds to between 8 and 12 ampère for a 12V system). Also make sure to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.windynation.com/jzv/inf/how-properly-fuse-solar-pv-system%22&#34;&gt;properly fuse your solar PV system&lt;/a&gt; to avoid electric fires.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laptop use is further complicated by the laptop battery. If the battery is not 100% charged, the computer will automatically try to charge it when you connect it to the solar system. However, power use of the laptop triples during charging, and unless there is full sun on the panels my system refuses to provide this amount of power. I &amp;ldquo;solved&amp;rdquo; this by keeping the battery 100% charged.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is interesting academic research about the relationship between energy infrastructures and energy demand, which we will discuss in a forthcoming article.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;/2009/06/the-monster-footprint-of-digital-technology/&#34;&gt;most energy use of a laptop is in the manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;. Switching to a more energy-efficient laptop isn&amp;rsquo;t always a sustainable choice. Buying a second-hand device could be a solution.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
